<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The popes ware-house, or, The merchandise of the whore of Rome published for the common good by Titus Oates.</title>
            <author>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 256 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O49</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16997</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12210295</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12210295</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56276</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53471)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56276)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 613:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The popes ware-house, or, The merchandise of the whore of Rome published for the common good by Titus Oates.</title>
                  <author>Oates, Titus, 1649-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 67 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst, Dorman Newman, Thomas Cockerill, and Tho. Simmons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title: The monstrous and abominable cheats of the Romish-pedlars.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Indulgences.</term>
               <term>Relics.</term>
               <term>Reliquaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:56276:1"/>
            <p>I Do Appoint <hi>Thomas Parkhurst, Dorman Newman, Thomas Cockerill,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Simmons,</hi> to Print this Book, Entituled, <hi>The</hi> POPES WARE-HOUSE, or the MERCHANDISE of the WHORE of ROME.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>July</hi> 24. 1679.</date>
               <signed>TITUS OATES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56276:1"/>
            <p>THE Popes Ware-houſe, OR THE MERCHANDISE OF THE WHORE OF ROME.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for Common Good.</p>
            <p>By <hi>TIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S OATES,</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurst, Dorman Newman, Thomas Cockerill,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Simmons,</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:56276:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56276:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>ANTHONY</hi> EARL of SHAFTSBURY, Baron Aſhly of <hi>Wimbourne</hi> St. <hi>Gyles;</hi> Lord <hi>Cooper</hi> of <hi>Pawlet;</hi> Lord Preſident of His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Council.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Publiſhers affectionate good Friend, and ſingular good Lord.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE greatneſs of Your Lordſhips favours conferred on me ſince the firſt of your Honours acquaintance with my poor ſelf, hath obliged me from time to time to conſider of ſome return; and upon due conſideration I find, that it is next to an impoſſibility for me to perform that to Your Lordſhip, to which the Laws of Duty and Reſpect ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige me; yet, My Lord, I thought it my Duty, (although my Returns will appear inconſiderable) not to omit any oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of making my Juſt acknowledgments. All good men have highly reſented Your Lordſhips Favour to me in this Great Affair: And the whole Kingdom judgeth it ſelf en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to Your Lordſhip for ſtanding by its Evidence and Cauſe; to the great Confuſion of the <hi>Romiſh Beaſt,</hi> and thoſe that wonder after it: from all which I conclude, that it becomes me to make to your good Lordſhip ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of my Gratitude: And although, My Lord, it be in me a great boldneſs to make this Addreſs to your good Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, yet for all that, ſince I have Your Lordſhips Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,
<pb facs="tcp:56276:3"/>I pray your Favour and your Patronage for this poor Piece: In the Publication of which, by many Reviews and Remarks, I have been at ſome pains; and now, My Lord, it is upon the Travel, Your Lordſhips Countenance may beget the Countenances of many more Perſons of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; ſo that I may not to all intents and purpoſes be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged in this War that I have vowed to make againſt the Whore and Dragon of <hi>Rome,</hi> and all her Votaries, as long as I have a day to live; and will, to the utmost of my power, diſcover her Cheats and Villanies.</p>
            <p>My Lord, this Tract is a Catalogue of the Romiſh Lies and Cheats, many of which are, to mine own knowledge, maintained and practiſed to this day in the Romiſh Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, to the great Diſhonour of God, and Contempt of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion; great occaſion being given by ſuch inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate practices, to the Enemies (both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi>) of Jeſus Christ, to Blaſpheme our Holy Profeſſion; ſo that if Your Lordſhip ſhall perſevere in this good work of oppoſing this Deviliſh Intereſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> to its ruine, you may be an happy Inſtrument, under God, to preſerve this Kingdom from its Superſtition, Idolatry and Tyranny: And Your Lordſhip may remember what pains Your Honour hath taken, whilſt in place, to ſuppreſs it, and the growing Greatneſs of that <hi>French</hi> Tyrant; for the which, Your Lordſhip hath abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly drank of the Cup of Afflictions, which you may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure your ſelf hath redounded highly to your Honour in this your Countrey: Therefore may it pleaſe Your Lordſhip to continue your Care and Zeal for the ſecuring of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant
<pb facs="tcp:56276:3"/>and Engliſh Interest, to the Honour of God, the Safety, Welfare and Advantage of our King and His Kingdoms, then Your Lordſhip may aſſure your ſelf of a laſting Repute in this Life, and of Peace at your Death, and a joyful Reſurrection to the World to come. As for Apostates and Traytors, though they flatter themſelves; and for their own Applauſe, ſuffer Paraſites and Hypocrites to do the like, yet they are the Objects of good mens Scorn and Contempt; and will certainly, without true Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, of which, God knows, there is but little hope, ſuffer the Vengeance of God upon them and their Poſterities in this Life, and Eternal Vengeance in the next; and though Your Lordſhip hath not had one Popiſh Maſs ſaid for the preſervation, either of your Body or your Soul, or both, yet it is not to be queſtioned, but that Your Lordſhip will grow as great in the Esteem of your Country, and in the Favour of your God; and greater than he, who for the Safety of his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, hath had above One Hundred Thouſand: And though Your Lordſhip, I believe, never beſtowed one Farthing for a ſmall quantity of Romiſh Reliques, I queſtion not, but your Name and Fame will endure to the end of the World, when his, that gave <hi>600 <abbr>l.</abbr>
               </hi> to Endow and Adorn an Altar with ſtores of ſuch ſtuff, ſhall Periſh: Yet this fowl Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster goeth for a Proteſtant; and I ſuppoſe, and verily believe, he is permitted ſo to do by a 'Diſpenſation from thoſe Dogs, whom he hath ſuffered to devour the Childrens bread. My Lord, I crave Your Lordſhips Pardon for this my boldneſs, which I proteſt, is out of the ſincerity of my heart to Your Lordſhip, and it is becauſe I do ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
<pb facs="tcp:56276:4"/>deſire your Honours welfare; and in order to this, I will not ceaſe my humble Addreſſes to Heaven in the behalf of Your Lordſhip and Family; and ſo concluding, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly take leave to ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips very humble Servant,</hi> TIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S OATES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:56276:4"/>
            <head>To all that profeſs the Proteſtant Religion within this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England,</hi> Grace, Mercy, and Peace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dearly beloved brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the Impieties of this Kingdom have cauſed many Judgments to fall upon it and its Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants; yet there hath not been any one like unto that of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e want of the knowledg of God, and his Word (or, if I may preſume to uſe the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>the removing of the Candleſtick</hi>): For although rumours of Wars, Peſtilence, and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Commotions, be very unpleaſant to the ſenſe of Mankind; yet as they are puniſhments which only affect the body and its ſenſes, they are the effects many times of Gods Fatherly love to a Kingdom and people, and are ſo received and judged by good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en. But when God dealeth with a people as he dealt with the Seven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and depriveth a Kingdom and people of his Word and Ordinances, and delivers it up to ſtrange Diabolical deluders and deluſions, then nothing can be judged to be the cauſe of all this, but the fierce anger and wrath of God, and its effects and conſequents, to be eternal vengeance and ruin; and as the ſoul exceeds the body, and is much to be valued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove it, and preferred before it, in reſpect of its worth and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; ſo it is certain, and admits of no debate in any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whatever, That thoſe Judgments which are ſpiritual, and the very Harbingers of an Eternal ruin, muſt needs ſurmount thoſe which are only corporal, and perhaps ſent in order to prevent this fiery wrath and indignation of the Moſt High God. Afflictions that are temporal, may well be compared to whips; but this Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of removing the Candleſtick, deſerveth to be compared to a fiery Scorpion.</p>
            <p>Under this diſmal burthen did this our native Countrey for ſome Hundreds of years groan; for when God in his anger for its ſin, had removed the Candleſtick from it, what Plagues at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended this dealing of Almighty God with out forefathers, I ſhall not need, my Brethren, to report to you; for I queſtion not your care and zeal, and therefore I humbly conceive that you do at
<pb facs="tcp:56276:5"/>your leiſure conſult and will enquire into thoſe Memoirs left up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Record in order to your more ample ſatisfaction in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; and beſides all this, the experience of thoſe ſober men who have and do ſtill converſe in thoſe Countreys and Kingdoms where the true Goſpel of our Lord Chriſt is ſtill oppoſed and perſecuted, and in its place trifling Ceremonies, unworthy Cheats, and Devilliſh Idolatries, are uſed and practiſed, might be a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent teſtimony in this caſe; yet for your ſakes, my Brethren, I did think it not at all inconvenient to expoſe to publick view the great vanity and unſpeakable deluſion to which God hath given up the Synagogue of <hi>Rome,</hi> even to believe a lye, ſo that her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Votaries might be damned for not receiving the truth of Gods word in the love thereof.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, my Brethren, God hath raiſed up his Servants, who have been very vigilant in the diſcovering of the Intrigues of the Whore of <hi>Rome,</hi> both in reſpect of her profeſſion and practiſes, who by their pains and skill have exploded her pretended Miracles, and have in a lively manner painted her Phanaticiſm, and expoſed her abominable Cheats to the world. Of theſe labours and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of good men we have enjoyed the benefits; and as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſe have had the happineſs and opportunity of doing Gods Church very eminent ſervices, by improving their parts and learning for her advantage; I thought it my duty to imploy ſome ſpare hours for your ſervice, in reviewing her old Trade of Merchandizing, and to revive the memory of the great advantage ſhe hath made of her Mock-Indulgences, and Mock Pardons, and Mock-Miracles, Cheats and Villanies, ſo that the conſideration of theſe things may ſtir you up to hate this abominable Strumpet, and burn her fleſh with ſire.</p>
            <p>Of this Traſh and Trumpery you have an exact Catalogue in this Book; an incredible gain of which, hath been made to their Popes, Biſhops, and Clergy, both Secular and Regular; to the latter eſpecially, who to mine own knowledg have judged their Reliques and Indulgences more advantageous to their Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Convents, than the enjoyments of Lands and Tenements are to thoſe that are of the Laity; for a teſtimony of which, the conſideration of the vaſt Treaſure that was found in their Dens when theſe Foxes were un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ennell'd by <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th,</hi> is proof ſufficient; and to this very day the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Regulars (ſo called) have gotten, and do ſtill get yearly Four thouſands of pounds <hi>ſterling</hi> out of <hi>England</hi> from their Votaries, to the great
<pb facs="tcp:56276:5"/>damage of this our Native Countrey, againſt which they are ſworn Enemies; nay, ſome that would have the honour of being called <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> have been highly guilty of an underhand con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution to their Devilliſh Idolatry, and Abominable Cheats, to the great diſhonour of Almighty God, and of Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to the diſparagement of their Prince and Countrey, to whoſe Laws they pretend to pay all manner of obedience, and when at home can ſwear their Prince into a belief of their loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and fidelity. I will not name that perſon in whom his Prince and Countrey have repoſed great Truſt, witneſs the Employ he hath had for ſome years; for whoſe ſake, to mine own knowledg, many thouſands of Maſſes have been ſaid for the health of his ſoul, for the preſervation of his body, and for the rectifying of his unſtable Judgment, and all this at their priviledged Altars, endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſtores of Indulgences, and with a goodly crop of their Reliques and Trumpery. But I ſhall leave him (as I fear God hath done) to believe the lyes and cheats of thoſe ſons of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt whom he hath moſt heartily entertained at his Table, tho Traytors to his Prince and Countrey, haters of Almighty God, and of all his Servants.</p>
            <p>So that (my dear Brethren) you may perceive, that by means of theſe Reliques and Merchandize, and of their pretended pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of conferring grace, holineſs, and eternal life, many profeſſing the ſame holy Faith with us, have fell away by the ſubtilty of the crafty ſons of the Synagogue of <hi>Rome,</hi> whom they have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from paying their duty to Almighty God, and from the profeſſion and practice of Gods true Religion; and ſome of theſe have become either monſtrous Monks, chattering Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, flattering Friars, heretical Hermites, Antichriſtian Ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, ſuperſtitious Nuns, railing Recluſes, Limbs of Antichriſt, nay of the Devil himſelf; and have denied the Lord that bought them with no leſs price than with his own blood, and have been led into a deplorable ſtate of Captivity by theſe Votaries of that filthy and abominable Strumpet, and deteſtable Dragon of <hi>Rome;</hi> who have ſet up and continued the Trade of making Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize of our fellow-ſubjects and brethren, and have devoured the Houſes of our Widows by their pretended zeal and devotion to and for this traſh, and of which in this Book you have a fair ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; and they have privily for well near an hundred years, acted this part, till theſe twenty years laſt paſt, in which they have had more countenance and indulgence; yet their ingratitude
<pb facs="tcp:56276:6"/>is ſuch, that they have returned evil for the good-will of our Magiſtrates, one of whom you know they have wickedly mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, our City of <hi>London</hi> they fired, and ſeveral Rapes and Cheats they have with that impudence acted, ſo that it is next to an impoſſibility for us to be ſafe whilſt they ſubſiſt; for our Peace they have diſturbed, our Intereſt, Property, and Liberty, they have endeavoured to betray into the hands of a <hi>French</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villiſh Power, and have attempted once more to bring us under the <hi>Roman</hi> yoke, which yoke we nor our Fathers were ever able to bear. Yea, they have endeavoured the death of our Prince, and to overthrow the Government and Laws by which we ſubſiſt and live, and without which we muſt of neceſſity run into confuſion, did not God appear in mercy to prevent our Ruin and their Malice. But I do not much admire their Impiety, becauſe I well know their damnable and wicked Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, of which their Practices are neceſſary Conſequences; of which I ſhall here give you a ſhort account.</p>
            <p n="1">I. They ſay, That to comply with <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in obedience to Laws and Government, would be an act unreaſonable, irreligious and damnable. Now what ſecurity can we have from ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and irreligious Miſcreants and Cut-throats? that (my Brethren) I ſhall leave to your graveſt judgments and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="2">II. That the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Miniſtry is falſe and intruded, and with it they ought not upon pain of damnation to communicate: This Propoſition being by them believed as an Article neceſſary to ſalvation; I ſuppoſe it will be by all wiſe and conſiderate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons concluded, That all means, methods, and ſtratagems ſhall be by them uſed and contrived for the rooting out and overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the eſtabliſhed Government of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church and Churches, ſeeing their Miniſtry is by them believed and aſſerted to be falſe and intruded.</p>
            <p n="3">III. They ſay, That <hi>Proteſtants</hi> have not the preaching of the word of God: This they have aſſerted, to render the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches vile and contemptible, and the Worſhip of God amongſt us, and our Brethren in the Goſpel, of no value; by which means many of our Religion have been ſeduced to follow their fopperies, and to worſhip their traſh, and to wonder after this foul Dragon of <hi>Rome:</hi> Therefore we may eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
<pb facs="tcp:56276:6"/>That they who thus revile us, and our Religion, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in this material part, to wit, the Miniſtry of Gods Word, which they have villanouſly denied us to have and enjoy, would ſoon deſtroy us, and that with their hands, (could they find opportunity) ſince their impudence hath been ſuch as to revile us, and it, with their tongues.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. That Proteſtants want the due Adminiſtration of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. If the Miniſtry of the Proteſtant Churches be falſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded, and uſurped, this then, I confeſs, will undoubtedly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. But in this we may, my dear Brethren, eaſily ſee what Calumnies they lay upon that holy Faith, for the profeſſion of which, many of our Forefathers loſt their dear Lives by theſe curſed Locuſts: and this they would continue to this day, if they were again Lords over us; for if the Religion which we profeſs, upon which moſt of the good Laws under which we live are founded and eſtabliſhed, lyes under ſuch notorious Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures; then there is no man living that will exerciſe the reaſon God hath given him, but will judge that theſe Vipers will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour and contrive the Subverſion of ſuch Laws, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Government of our Prince will be alſo attempted and ſtruck at.</p>
            <p n="5">V. That the Proteſtant Church is not the true Church of God. This being Preached, many of the more ignorant Proteſtants have been wounded in their Conſciences, perverted in their Principles, corrupted in their Judgments, and are brought to Queſtion, and at laſt to oppoſe the Juriſdiction of the King in things Eccleſiaſtical; by which diſmal change, the more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent part of the Government is by them endeavoured to be made and declared to be null and void. And by means of this ſtrange perverſion, thoſe who before were quiet in their ſeveral Stati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſubject to Laws, are become heady and high-minded Traytors, without the leaſt ſpark of Obedience and Love to their Prince and Countrey, to the great damage of our Countrey in which we live.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. That the Proteſtants are notorious Hereticks. Upon which poſition and principle they eſtabliſh thoſe wicked and diabolical practiſes, of Fires, Rapes, Thefts, Murders, Felonies, Treaſons, to the great confuſion of our Countrey, and diſquiet of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Religion. Have they not, I ſay, burnt the Bodies of
<pb facs="tcp:56276:7"/>our Forefathers, becauſe they would not debauch their Souls and Conſciences in their Idolatrous Communion, and all becauſe they judged them Hereticks? Upon which principle they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Kings, and then ſay it is no Treaſon to Murther them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are Hereticks, if they do only countenance, and not practiſe their Religion.</p>
            <p>Yet we find them very brisk in the denial of all their wicked Attempts upon this Nation, even to their deaths, as appears by the Five Speeches of the Five <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, lately Executed for Conſpiring the Death of the King, and Subverſion of the Proteſtant Religion and Government? Who indeed would not deny all thoſe things, that were in their circumſtances? For ſhould they have confeſſed, What would have become of their zealous Votaries, the conduct of whoſe ſouls they had been entruſted withall, who would not have continued this truſt in ſuch hands, if they had known their inclinations to ſuch Treaſons? What would become of the Plot, which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly goerh on ſtill againſt us and our Liberties, as faſt and as fierce as ever? The conſcious, of whom we have not yet a certain intelligence, would much abate in their courage, and would not be in that capacity to ſerve the Intereſt of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Dragon, if that theſe Martyrs (or indeed Malefactors) had confeſſed. How thoſe conſiderable Traytors now in hold would have been damnified, ſhould they have confeſſed, I leave to you, my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, to judg, and how the whole Intereſt of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue muſt have ſunk and periſhed to all intents and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, had they ſpoken that which their Conſciences knew to be true. Moreover, they had an Oath of Secrecy, a branch of which was to enjoin them, if diſcovered, to deny the deſign to the laſt breath; and not only a diſpenſation, but alſo a command from the Pope to do the ſame, and damnation threatned if they had not denied the fact to the laſt. But that which is above all, their cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning way of abſolving one another, juſt before the Cart was drawn from under them. So that had not theſe conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons been inducements, nor the diſpenſation of the Pope judged by them to be authentick, nor his command ſafe; yet behold a Plaiſter of Abſolution is applied to this diſeaſe of theirs, which certainly muſt be owned by them to be very effectual for the cure of a Lye; and what if the Hangman had debarred them of this opportunity? it would have been cured by a few Twelve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penny Maſſes; and after a little frying in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> they would
<pb facs="tcp:56276:7"/>have had Heaven for their pains; and who would not endure a little heating in <hi>Purgatory,</hi> for the advantage of their Mother the Church, which lay at ſtake upon the diſcovery of their Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany plotted and contrived againſt our Prince, Religion, Lives, and Liberties.</p>
            <p>And now, Brethren, let this ſhort reflection ſuffice from me, ſeeing it is done to all intents and purpoſes by far better hands; and it being not to the purpoſe here, I ſay no more to that. Yet I ſhall bleſs the Moſt High God, before whoſe Judgment-ſeat I muſt one day ſtand, That though they have made a pretended denial, yet my comfort is, I have that within me which teacheth me to laugh the Cenſorious and Malicious to ſcorn; and it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obligeth me to go on with Courage in my Evidence againſt theſe obſtinate and lying Cut-throats, and I hope the Charity of my Brethrens credit will be ſooner extended to their Friends that are living, than to thoſe implacable and forſworn Enemies that by the juſt hand of vengeance are now dead; and God knowing that I ſpeak the truth, I am ſure will juſtifie me in this management of his own Cauſe and my Countreys.</p>
            <p>But now, Brethren, I commend you to God and the Word of his Grace, which is able to build you up, and give you an inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance among them that are ſanctified. So, my Brethren, I bid you heartily farewell in the Lord, and remain for ever</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Whitehall, <date>July 12. 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your affectionate Brother in the Goſpel of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>TITUS OATES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:56276:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56276:8"/>
            <head>The Monſtrous and Abominable CHEATS OF THE Romiſh-PEDLARS.</head>
            <head type="sub">OF RELIQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ES.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Introduction.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the Holy Prophets of old made it their buſineſs to ſhew the vanity and folly of the Apoſtate Church of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and wherein they had gone away from God, to the fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh inventions of idolatrous and ſuperſtitious men: So our late zealous Reformers laboured to diſcover the madneſs and folly of them which did abide ſtill in the Communion of the Popiſh Religion, by ſhewing wherein the people were cheated by the ſuperſtitious pretences, feigned mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and uſeleſs reliques with which the ſeducing Prieſts, Fryers, Monks, and Antichriſtian Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> had deceived the poor ſons and daughters of men: And herein the faithful Servants of God, in the days of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> have laboured, and have diſcovered the fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiſm of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in many inſtances, and ſhewn what horrid Fanaticks the Popes and their followers have been: And becauſe the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts are to my own knowledg ſtill ſuch Fanaticks, and will not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, I have thought it my duty, for the Honour of God, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the good Chriſtian people of this Generation from being any long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er deceived by them, to revive and recover out of oblivion the old obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations and collections of the Servants of Chriſt, which time hath buried in forgetfulneſs; which, together with my own Obſervations, I have tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and cauſed to be publiſhed, that ſo the madneſs and folly in which they perſiſt, may be known to all men: that ſo as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks of his time, <hi>they may proceed no further,</hi> read 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8, 9. And I think it but reaſon, if the diſeaſe be ſtill the ſame, the means of curing ſhould be continued: and of this I am ſure, that they do ſtill cheat the people with their pretended Miracles, and Reliques of pretended Saints; and amongſt the reſt, with the Fanatical pretences of Pardons and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, by going to ſuch a Saints Shrine or Sepulcher, and of being healed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56276:9"/>of diſeaſes by the touch of a Relique of a pretended Saint.</p>
               <p>And becauſe you ſhall ſee that I do not impoſe new fictions of my own brain, but do follow the wiſe example of them, who to undeceive the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and recover them out of the Fanaticiſm of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> did diſcover her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ollies and frauds to all men: I have not only followed their methods, but tranſcribed their very Collections, which I doubt not but will be as uſeful in the preſent recovery of the Engliſh Chriſtians, as in the the days paſt.</p>
               <p>And as the Prophets of old uſed no other means to reduce men, but bringing them back to the Law and Teſtimony, ſhewing them the folly and madneſs of their forefathers, and of them that would, or did miſlead the people in the days in which they propheſied; ſo ought the Servants of God in this day, and I doubt not but the ſame method will have the ſame good effect.</p>
               <p>AT <hi>Rome</hi> in times paſt (as St. <hi>Sylvester</hi> the Pope writeth in his Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle) there were One thouſand five hundred and five Churches, whereof the greater part at this preſent is deſtroyed: But among thoſe that remain, there are Seven principal Churches, which (as they ſay)<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Query,</hi> Who endued theſe Churches? I am ſure not Chriſt, for he beſtows ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Gifts on perſons, not Places.</note> are endued with greater and more ſingular priviledges than the reſt are; yea, and that for the grace, holineſs and dignity which is found in them, paſſing all other Churches<note n="*" place="margin">All are but Stone and Timber, and dead matter, and not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs one more than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note>. In thoſe Seven principal Churches there are many, yea almoſt innumerable Indulgences, Pardons, Priviledges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and Reliques alſo, as they fain. And firſt I will rehearſe the names of all ſuch Reliques as be at <hi>Rome,</hi> not only in thoſe Seven Principal Churches, but in the reſidue alſo; and afterwards rehearſe the Indulgences, Pardons, Priviledges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that appertain unto the ſame. And becauſe no man ſhall think that I invent theſe things of my own head, I here truly and faithfully confeſs, that whatſoever in this Treatiſe is written of <hi>Rome,</hi> is tranſlated out of a Book Printed in Latin at <hi>Rome,</hi> by Mr. <hi>Stephen Plank</hi> of <hi>Patavia,</hi> in the year of our Lord 1489, the 7th. of <hi>November,</hi> the ſixth year of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Eighth. And whatſoever is added, is declared out of what Books they were taken, and the judgment of all theſe things left to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Reader. But firſt of all we will go in hand with ſuch Reliques as be in the Churches at <hi>Rome;</hi> and begin with the Seven Principal Churches, whereof the Church of <hi>Lateran</hi> is the firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Church of <hi>Lateran,</hi> and of the Reliques contained in the ſame.</head>
               <p>THE Church of <hi>Lateran</hi> was dedicated of St. <hi>Sylveſter</hi> the Pope, in honour of St. <hi>Saviour,</hi> St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and St. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Relique-Houſe of this Church there is the Altar of St. <hi>John Baptist</hi> which he had in the Wilderneſs.</p>
               <p>It is a likely matter they ſhould have the Altar of St. <hi>John Baptist,</hi> who had no Altar there, nor had he uſe for one.<note place="margin">A bleſſed company.</note> Why did they not tell us what he offered upon that Altar? And beſides this, the Altar of which they boaſt, is in eight or nine ſeveral places.</p>
               <p>Alſo in a certain Chappel at the end of the ſaid Church,<note place="margin">Ark.</note> there is the Ark of the Lord which <hi>Moſes</hi> made at the Commandment of God in the Deſert, after the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were delivered out of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:56276:9"/>
               <p>They that will believe this ſtory, muſt needs be ignorant, and willing to believe lyes; ſeeing the Prophet <hi>Eſdras,</hi> 2 book ch. 10. v. 22, ſaith it was ſpoiled by the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> which any man will believe ſooner than the Pope. But to put it out of doubt that they do wickedly, read <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.16.</p>
               <p>There is alſo the Table whereupon our Lord Jeſus Chriſt did eat his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per with his Diſciples when he ordained the Sacrament of his Body and Blood.<note place="margin">The Table.</note>
               </p>
               <p>I have ſeen a great part of this Table, ſo called, in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi> and it is of excellent virtue, if we may believe the holy Fathers of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of Jeſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The Rod of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> which being caſt on the ground,<note place="margin">Rod.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Serpent; wherewith alſo many and notable Miracles were wrought by the power of God.</p>
               <p>It is ſtrange to hear that they ſhould have that ſtick or rod of <hi>Moſes</hi> which was 2000 years before Chriſt in the wilderneſs, of which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture makes no mention after <hi>Moſes</hi> ſmote the Rock with it, <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.11. and one of the Jeſuits forgetting that it was ſaid to be at <hi>Rome,</hi> preached this Doctrine, that <hi>Moſes</hi> broke it when he ſmote upon the Rock.</p>
               <p>All theſe things aforeſaid did <hi>Veſpaſtanus</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> bring unto <hi>Rome</hi> from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Padre Antonio de Laudayada</hi> on the Feaſt of St. <hi>Alban,</hi> June 21. 1677.</note> with four Pillars of Braſs, which are ſet up and ſtand about the high Altar of the ſaid Church.</p>
               <p>If we have but folly enough to believe all before ſaid, we may believe this into the bargain; but believe it for all this, becauſe that <hi>Veſpaſianus</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were admirers of thoſe Pillars for the ſanctity that was in them, and certainly did intend them to be for Reliques, and may be as precious as the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi>'s Chamber-pot, which the Fryars of the Order of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> at <hi>Burgos</hi> are ſaid to have, and keep it as a very precious Relique; but if they have the Chamber-pot, I wonder who had her Cloſe-ſtool.</p>
               <p>Upon the ſaid high Altar there ſtand the heads of the holy Apoſtles <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Paul;</hi> and whenſoever thoſe are ſhewed to the people,<note place="margin">
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Peter</hi>'s head.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Paul</hi>'s head.</item>
                     </list>
                  </note> there are ſo many Indulgences and Pardons granted, as there are when the Napkin of the Lord is ſhewed at St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quaery;</hi> Who granted theſe Pardons? Not Chriſt, I am ſure, at either or both the ſhows; but here the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhews her ſelf to be like her Father the Devil, that was a lyar from the beginning.</p>
               <p>The Fryars of <hi>Auguſtine</hi>'s Order in <hi>Bilbao,</hi> ſay they have a great piece of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s skull; and the <hi>Franciſcans</hi> of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Church alſo is the head of St. <hi>Pancras,</hi> out of which head,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pancras</hi> head.</note> when this Church was ſet on fire by a ſort of Hereticks, iſſued and followed out great plenty of blood by the ſpace of three days and three nights. This Head, with divers other Reliques, is ſhewed on <hi>Eaſter-day</hi> after dinner.</p>
               <p>That this is a bloody lye, a weak eye may perceive. It's a wonder they did not ſave ſome of that blood to ſhew amongſt the reſt of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques.</p>
               <p>Under the high Altar of the aforeſaid Church,<note place="margin">Oratory.</note> is that Oratory of St. <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt, where he prayed when he went in and out, and was priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er at <hi>Rome.</hi> This is ſaid alſo to be at <hi>Genoua</hi> now, and alſo at <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſeveral pieces at St. <hi>Diego</hi> in <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:56276:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> In a certain Tabernacle which is upon the Altar of <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> theſe Reliques are hid that follow.</head>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Diadem.</note> THE Imperial Diadem wherewith St. <hi>Sylveſter</hi> the Pope was crowned by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperor.</p>
               <p>Whether or no that ever <hi>Sylveſter</hi> the Pope wore an Imperial Diadem, I will not in this Book contend; but the Diadem the Popes after him chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leng'd, hath been a vexation to many good Princes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The head of St. <hi>Zachary</hi> the Prieſt, Father to St. <hi>John Baptiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zachary</hi> dyed in <hi>Paleſtina,</hi> 2000 miles from <hi>Rome;</hi> and how ſhould his head be ſhown at <hi>Rome</hi> ſo many hundred years after? for it was ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of years after <hi>Zachary</hi>'s death, before the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was ſo fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy as to invent ſuch lyes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Divers Reliques of St. <hi>Mary Magdalen.</hi> Which are called as he that ſhews them pleaſeth.</p>
               <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Shoulder-plate.</note> The ſhoulder-plate of St. <hi>Lawrence</hi> Martyr.</p>
               <p>It is a wonder if they which roaſted him, did not burn his bones; and the wonder is greater, becauſe that his Aſhes and Urn were preſented to the Cathedral Church at <hi>Sevill</hi> in <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">A Tooth.</note> One of the teeth of St. <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">Cup.</note> The cup wherein St. <hi>John</hi> drank the poyſon, and yet it did not hurt him.</p>
               <p>How could that be known ſo many hundred years after, ſeeing that no leſs than four Churches in <hi>Rome</hi> pretend to have this cup, to the certain knowledg of the Publiſher?</p>
               <p n="7">7.<note place="margin">Chain.</note> The chain wherewith St. <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt was bound when he was led from <hi>Epheſus</hi> to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How is it poſſible that the chain ſhould be perceived or known to be the ſame, if it laſted ſo long, 600 years? yea, all the people being dead, and neither Pagan-<hi>Rome</hi> nor Chriſtian <hi>Rome</hi> had got the art of ſhewing thoſe tricks, till <hi>Rome</hi> grew Antichriſtian.</p>
               <p n="8">8.<note place="margin">Petticoat.</note> The Petticoat of St. <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt, (rather of Pope <hi>Joan</hi>) which was laid upon the three dead men, and they ſtraightway roſe up from death to life.</p>
               <p>That St. <hi>John</hi> ſhould wear Petticoats is ſtrange; but that this Petticoat ſhould laſt 800 years, is more ſtrange: but that any body ſhould be ſuch Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks as to believe this, is to be admired!</p>
               <p n="9">9.<note place="margin">Aſhes. Coat.</note> Part of St. <hi>John Baptiſts</hi> Aſhes, and his Coat made of hair, which he did wear in the Wilderneſs.</p>
               <p>There could be no Aſhes of his, for he was not burnt, but his body bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.12. And that he had a Coat is uncertain; but that his Coat ſhould be ſhown ſix or ſeven hundred years after, is incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: and it's a wonder they had not the confidence to ſhow the Taylor that made it.</p>
               <p n="10">10.<note place="margin">Milk.</note> Part of our Ladies Milk, Hair, and Garments.</p>
               <p>Good <hi>Reader</hi> obſerve this Tale well, and compute the time when the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary</hi> gave Milk, and the time when the World were ſuch fools to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and you will find it about 800 year; and that a Womans Milk ſhould laſt till this year 1679, is incredible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Shirt.</note> The Shirt which the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> made with her own hands for Chriſt; which Shirt is of ſuch virtue, that Devils themſelves are driven
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56276:10"/>out (by whole Legions) of perſons poſſeſſed, if you will believe this abominable Harlot and Impoſtor of <hi>Rome:</hi> But I pray then how are Jeſuits in the <hi>East-Indies</hi> poſſeſſors of this Shirt, if it be at <hi>Rome?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Towel.</note> The Towel or Linnen-Cloth wherewith Chriſt wiped his Apoſtles feet.</p>
               <p>This is another lye; for the Publiſher hath ſeen as many pieces of this Towel as will fill an ordinary bag; and half a yard at leaſt was ſhewed him at St. <hi>Barlines Abby</hi> in St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and yet <hi>Rome</hi> challengeth the whole Towel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The Reed wherewith Chriſt was ſtricken.<note place="margin">Reed.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And the hand that ſtruck him. I hope the one is as true as the other, and may prove as good a Relique. It ſeems that the Reed, as the Papiſts ſay, is of ſuch efficacy and force, that ſeveral perſons have been delivered from great pains of body that have kiſſed the ſame. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Jeſuits at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> having alſo the ſaid Reed, ſay ſo, therefore it muſt needs be true.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Garment.</note> The Garment of Purple which was dyed with the drops of blood from Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This is an unworthy and filthy lye; for there are ſo many pieces of this Garment ſaid to be in <hi>Spain, Portugal, Flanders, France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">There is ſcarce a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle in all theſe places but challenge a good piece of this Garment.</note> as is able to make Ten ſuch Garments as Chriſt wore when mocked by the <hi>Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The Vail of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vail.</note> which ſhe put about the privy-Members of Chriſt when he hanged on the Croſs.</p>
               <p>This Veil is ſeen in a dozen places, and works wonderful things in <hi>Spain;</hi> for in one day it begot ſuch a devotion in the people of <hi>Vallidolyd,</hi> that the <hi>Franciſcan</hi>-Fryars got above a Thouſand pieces of Eight, beſides Gold, for the ſight thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The Napkin which was laid upon Chriſts face.<note place="margin">Napkin.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Jeſuits at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> have a good piece in the Engliſh Seminary; And how then can it be all at <hi>Rome?</hi> And in the Reliquary of St. <hi>Ignatius</hi>-Colledg, I have ſeen half a yard of Linnen which the Jeſuits have, and call it a piece of that Napkin that was laid upon Chriſts face; and ſurely we may believe them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> That part of our Lord Jeſus which was cut away when he was cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed.<note place="margin">Skin.</note>
               </p>
               <p>That a little bit of skin cut off a Babes Yard when Eight days old, ſhould laſt and look like ſuch 1500 or 1600 years, none but the Father of lyes, and his Children, can be the countenancers of it. And it is very unlikely it ſhould be at <hi>Rome,</hi> when as the Monks of the Order of St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> near <hi>Vallidolyd</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> pretend to have it alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> That Water and Blood which flowed out of Chriſts ſide when he hanged on the Croſs.</p>
               <p>Note that one drop of this was never ſaved.<note place="margin">A Tun would not hould all, if this blood and water were in one place, it is of ſuch an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</note> And how can it be ſhewn 1600 year after? If it were, Who ſaved it? and who required it to be kept? and to whom was the keeping of it committed? and why do the Fathers of the Engliſh Colledge at <hi>Vallidolyd</hi> challenge a Glaſs full of it, containing at leaſt half a Pint?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> A large piece of Chriſts Croſs, with many other Reliques which are there ſhewed on <hi>Eaſter-day</hi> after Dinner.</p>
               <p>That we are delivered from ſuch intollerable cheats, is a great mercy; but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56276:11"/>to think the people well in their wits that believe ſuch Lyes, were to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate another wonder. But to conclude, the pretenders to theſe things are doubtleſs the greateſt deceivers in the world; which will appear if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the circumſtance of time: And certainly we may expect to find the whole Croſs in time, if the Papiſts will but ſtand to their tackling in this caſe, as they would ſeem to do in other caſes that refer to Reliques.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="church">
               <head>Of the ſecond Principal Church, and of the Reliques contained in the ſame.</head>
               <p>THE ſecond Principal Church is at St. <hi>Peters</hi> in the <hi>Golden-Hill,</hi> in which Church alſo are many Reliques.</p>
               <p>When the Pope, his Whores and Baſtards, (otherwiſe wrapping it in clean linnen, his Nephews and Neeces) are there, then I ſay, there may be a jolly company of Reliques.</p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Half the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </note> The half part of the bodies of the holy Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> reſt in the aforeſaid Church under the high Altar. And the other half lyeth at St. <hi>Pauls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How incredible this is,<note place="margin">If the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhers memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fails him not, he ſee an Arm and a Leg of St. <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Valladolid.</hi>
                  </note> that bodies thus divided, ſhould be ſhown 1600 years after, makes me remember St. <hi>Pauls</hi> words, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, which I pray read. But what have we to do with what St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, ſince St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor ſaith it? Therefore let us not queſtion it, for the Pope is an excellent divider.</p>
               <p>Alſo in the aforeſaid Church reſt the bodies of the Holy Apoſtles <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Jude:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Symon</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi>'s bodies. And <hi>Parnel.</hi>
                  </note> and alſo the body of St. <hi>Parnel</hi> the Virgin, who was the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of St. <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The Head of St. <hi>Andrew</hi> the Apoſtle, which is ſhewed in his Feaſt, and on that day when it was brought and conveyed unto <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Head is ſhewn alſo in no leſs than Nine or Ten places in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Flanders,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A wonderful multiplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> and great ſums of Money are received by the Clergy both Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and Secular, for the ſight thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke.</note> The Head of St. <hi>Luke</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſt.</hi> The Head of St. <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> the Martyr;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>James</hi>'s Head.</note> the Head of St. <hi>James;</hi> the bodies of the Saints <hi>Proceſſus</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinianus,</hi> and many other bodies: with divers Reliques of holy Martyrs, Confeſſors and Virgins.</p>
               <p>How <hi>James</hi>'s Head who was 1600 years before ſlain by <hi>Herod</hi> at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and the bodies of men ſlain ſo many thouſands of Miles off, ſhould after ſo many hundreds of years be lodged in the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> is credible by none but them that are, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, given up to believe Lyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vernicle or Face-cloath this is judged by the ſober Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be a cheat, as the Author of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Eccleſiae,</hi> ſaith.</note> The Vernicle, or the holy Face-cloath of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt remaineth in the aforeſaid Church, and is many times ſhewed in the Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>week, and on Aſcenſion-day, and the next Sunday, both before and after the Feaſt of St. <hi>Anthony</hi> the Abbot. At the ſhewing whereof, the <hi>Romans</hi> that come unto it have 3000 years of pardon. And they that dwell about <hi>Rome,</hi> and come unto it, have 6000 years of pardon. But they that come unto it through Mountains, Vallies and Hills, they have 12000 years of Pardon, and as many Lents, and remiſſion of the third part of all their ſins.</p>
               <p>This of Pardon of ſins by going to ſee ſuch ſights is a damnable Lye, and doth ſhamefully derogate from the merits of Chriſt; and the promoters muſt be ſtark mad, and in a far greater guilt than the fallen Angels: For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it muſt be by faith in his blood, and not by the ſight of the Face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56276:11"/>that men muſt get pardon of ſin; but ſeeing the Pope hath ſaid to the contrary, let <hi>Papists</hi> believe the Pope and not Chriſt, but I muſt believe Chriſt and not the Pope.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> In the aforeſaid Church is the chair in which St. <hi>Peter</hi> did ſit when he was Biſhop at <hi>Antioch;</hi> and gallantly decked and trimmed.<note place="margin">Chair.</note> This chair at every Feaſt that is called <hi>Cathedra Sancti Petri,</hi> is ſet before the Quire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>door with great ſolemnity, where all the people according to their devotion may come and touch it.</p>
               <p>In ſtead of worſhipping God, and honouring him, they worſhip and honour Reliques; and inſtead of truſting in God through Chriſt, they truſt in old rotten rags, and worm-eaten chairs: But ſtay, it is like it was an Iron chair.</p>
               <p>Alſo in the ſame Church there is a pillar,<note place="margin">12. Pillars.</note> upon the which our Lord Jeſus was wont to lean, both when he preached to the people, and when he prayed unto his heavenly Father in the Temple of <hi>Solomon.</hi> This pillar is of ſo great vertue and power, that it driveth out Devils, and maketh them whole that were before vexed with unclean ſpirits; and it worketh daily many mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. This pillar with eleven more were brought from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> out of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> Temple, for the garniſhing and ſetting out of this aforeſaid Church.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Titus Veſpaſian</hi> burnt the Temple, it's unlikely theſe twelve pillars eſcaped, and as unlikely that Devils ſhould be driven out by them: You may ſee that Church is not the <hi>pillar of Truth,</hi> that upholds ſuch lyes and ſuch horrid Fanaticiſms and Impoſtors, Popes, Prieſts, and Papiſts. I am amaz'd at one thing, That the Pope had not the manners to Canonize <hi>Titus</hi> that great Hero for a Saint, ſeeing he procured for holy Church ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil-expelling Reliques; for ſure it is, that no Saint of the Pope's Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ever deſerved more from the Pope than this brave Prince did.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="church">
               <head>Of the third principal Church, and of the Reliques contained in the ſame.</head>
               <p>THE third principal Church is at St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> in the which are theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Arm of St. <hi>Ann,</hi> our Lady's Mother.<note place="margin">Arm of St. <hi>Ann.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. One of the chains wherewith St. <hi>Paul</hi> was bound; and many other more without number.</item>
               </list>
               <p>That our Lady's Mothers name was St. <hi>Ann,</hi> is unknown; but this I know, that all theſe are inventions of them who are his followers, that is, the Father of Lyes; for the good Saint is returned to her duſt long before this Lye was invented. But be it ſo, if they have St. <hi>Pauls</hi> chain, I pray the next time they open ſhop, let us ſee the virtue of the holy Relique.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Half the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi> The Popiſh party are wonderful exact in divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Saints bodies.</note> Under the high Altar is the other half of the bodies of the holy Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul.</hi> Alſo the body of St. <hi>Timothy,</hi> who was St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Diſciple. And infinite number of the Reliques of Saints, whoſe ſouls are merry and joyful in Heaven.</p>
               <p>But the wonder is, where they found the body of St. <hi>Timothy.</hi> But what need that, ſince they have the happy opportunity of having ſo many bodies at one time of him in ſeveral places? and certain it is, that they may turn any body into the body of St. <hi>Timothy,</hi> when they can turn a piece of bread into the body of God.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:56276:12"/>
               <p>In this Church alſo is a devout Image of the Croſs,<note place="margin">That the Croſs ſpake.</note> which ſpake to Saint <hi>Briget,</hi> becauſe ſhe prayed ſo many times, and ſo devoutly before it.</p>
               <p>That a Wooden Croſs ſhould ſpeak, none but a brazen-fac'd Popiſh Prieſt dare affirm; I am certain that the beſt of St. <hi>Brigets</hi> revelations are very ſuſpicious; and never yet is there the leaſt mention of this ſtory. I confeſs in her Liſe the Papiſts take notice of ſuch a paſſage, but never any Church receiv'd it but the Whore of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="church">
               <head>Of the fourth principal Church, and of the Reliques contained in the ſame.</head>
               <p>THE fourth principal Church is at St. <hi>Maries</hi> the greater; in which are theſe Reliques following:</p>
               <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Body of St. <hi>Mathew</hi> and others.</note> The body of St. <hi>Mathew</hi> the Apoſtle lyeth under the high Altar. Alſo the head of the ſaid St. <hi>Mathew</hi> reſteth in the ſaid Church</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The Body of St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> who is one of the Doctors of holy Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The Bodies of St. <hi>Ramula,</hi> and St. <hi>Redempta.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is a crowd of Saints pretended by ſuch a crew of Impoſtors, as are not found amongſt the heathen.</p>
               <p>In the ſame Church is,</p>
               <p n="2">2. A little clout in which <hi>Mary</hi> the Virgin wrapped her Son Chriſt when he lay in the Manger at <hi>Bethlem,</hi> being newly born.</p>
               <p>O horrid and great lye! that a little clout ſhould laſt ſuch a great while as 1600 years, and be brought from <hi>Bethlem</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> which is I believe nigh 2000 miles!</p>
               <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">St. <hi>Jerome</hi>'s Stole.</note> St. <hi>Jerom</hi>'s ſtole. The arm of St. <hi>Mathew</hi> the Apoſtle and Evangeliſt. The arm of St. <hi>Luke</hi> the Evangeliſt. The arm of <hi>Thomas Becket</hi> Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> The hand and arm of St. <hi>Vibian</hi> Virgin and Martyr.</p>
               <p>Certainly theſe Saints had wonderful effects ſhewn upon their bodies af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they were dead; for eight of St. <hi>Mathews</hi> arms are to be ſeen in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Spain,</hi> and <hi>France.</hi> I have ſeen three of St. <hi>Lukes;</hi> but of <hi>Beckets</hi> there is no end.</p>
               <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Manger. The Popiſh Shavelings tell us the virtue of this Manger, and how many of them ye have</note> The Manger wherein Chriſt lay at <hi>Bethlem,</hi> when the ſhepherds came unto him.</p>
               <p>That a Wooden Manger ſhould be brought from <hi>Bethlem</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> which is nigh 2000 miles, and laſt to be ſeen there 1600 years after Chriſts birth, can be credited by none but them that love to make lyes, whoſe doom you may read <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. cap. 21.15.</p>
               <p>Beſides theſe, there are many other Reliques both of he-Saints and ſhe-Saints, whoſe ſouls rejoyce in heaven; and theſe Reliques are ſhewed to the people upon <hi>Eaſter-day</hi> about Even-ſong time.</p>
               <p>That ſo holy a time ſhould be prophaned by ſuch ſhows, ſheweth the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holineſs of Popiſh Prieſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="church">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:56276:12"/>
               <head>Of the Fifth Principal Church, and of the Reliques comained in the ſame.</head>
               <p>THE Fifth Principal Church is at St. <hi>Laurences</hi> without the Walls,<note place="margin">The Stone on which <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> laid.</note> in which, beſides other, is this Relique, <hi>viz.</hi> the Stone upon which bleſſed <hi>Laurence</hi> was laid after that he was roaſted and dead.</p>
               <p>I think it would almoſt make a Stone bleed to hear of the horrid forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> This Stone hath an excellent faculty at caſting out Devils, as Father <hi>Anderton</hi> wrote when he ſent a piece of it to St. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> in a Letter dated <hi>March</hi> 10, 1678. And the Dog at St. <hi>Omers</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not well, this piecee of Stone was hanged about his neck in a Bag to cure him of madneſs, what effects it wrought I cannot tell, but this Stone and a good breakfaſt filled the Curs Belly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="church">
               <head>Of the Sixth Principal Church, and of the Reliques con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſame.</head>
               <p>THE Sixth Principal Church is at St. <hi>Fabian</hi> and St. <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> in the which, beſides other innumerable, are theſe Reliques, that is to ſay, the body of bleſſed <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> the Martyr. The body of <hi>Fabian</hi> Pope and Martyr. The body of bleſſed <hi>Stephen</hi> Pope and Martyr. The body of St. <hi>Lucy</hi> the Virgin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It's a grievous thing that the bodies of the good Saints may not reſt in their Graves, but muſt be dragged out to be made a Market on by a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of covetous Paplings. <hi>But it is Money that makes the Mare to go.</hi> And if we conſider the vaſt treaſures that the Clergy of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have acquired, we ſhall not need much to wonder: But I hope that the Princes of Chriſtendom will be wiſer than to believe them for time to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="church">
               <head>Of the ſeventh principal Church, and of the Reliques contained in the ſame.</head>
               <p>THE ſeventh principal Church is of the Holy Croſs in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in which are theſe Reliques following:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Two Cups, of which, one is full of the blood of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Blood of Chriſt. Milk of <hi>Mary.</hi>
                  </note> and the other is full of the Milk of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>She gives a jolly deal; of that we had a Glaſs full before, and now we have got a Cup full.</p>
               <p>But I pray, how came they by a Cup full of Chriſts blood? Sure the <hi>Jews</hi> ſaved it not, and the Diſciples were all fled, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.56.</p>
               <p>And that this Milk and Blood ſhould not be dryed up all this time, looks like one of their lying wonders.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Sponge, which being full of Vinegar and Gall, the <hi>Jews</hi> reached unto Chriſt hanging on the Croſs a little before his death.</p>
               <p>This is like the reſt, as if the <hi>Jews</hi> had reſerved that Spunge: it is a wonder they do not lye, and ſay they have the Reed alſo.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A good large piece of the Holy-Croſs.</p>
               <p>Some-time they have the whole Croſs, as in the Three principle Churches,<note place="margin">Piece of the Croſs.</note> and then it could ſpeak, and now here is a piece of it: Cannot that ſpeak alſo?</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:56276:13"/>
               <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">Two Thorns.</note> Two Thorns of Chriſts Crown.</p>
               <p>Who ſaved theſe? the Diſciples? How came it at <hi>Rome?</hi> But it's not a Thorn matter how they Romance. But I ſhould be glad to know when they will have an end of their Thorns, for they have at leaſt a Buſhel of them, as divers will juſtifie when it is neceſſary.</p>
               <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">One Nail A noble in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</note> One of the Nails wherewith Chriſt was faſtued to the Croſs.</p>
               <p>There was but Three, have they got one? And the Publiſher hath ſeen four that are ſo called, one at <hi>Burgos,</hi> one at <hi>Vallidolyd,</hi> two in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. A piece of the Croſs of that Thief which did hang on Chriſts right hand, and turned unto Chriſt before his death.</p>
               <p>Is a Thiefs Croſs become a Sacred Rellique? I fear they are Thieves themſelves that made it ſo. Yet why ſhould we fear that, of which the Princes and people of <hi>Europe</hi> have been ſo long convinced.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Reliques that are in other Churches at <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the Church of St. <hi>Chryſogone</hi> are theſe Reliques:<note place="margin">Arm of St. <hi>James.</hi> Shoulderplate of St. <hi>Andrew.</hi>
                  </note> An Arm of St. <hi>James.</hi> The Shoulder plate of St. <hi>Andrew</hi> the Apoſtle. And the Head of the aforeſaid St. <hi>Chyſogone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Abundance of Saints without Heads: I doubt the Prieſts cut them off to make merchandize! More wonders yet; St. <hi>James</hi> put to death in <hi>Pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> by <hi>Heroes</hi> Sword, and yet his Arm at <hi>Rome!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Cecily</hi> theſe Reliques are contained:<note place="margin">Maximianus.</note> The body of St. <hi>Cecily.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The bodies of <hi>Tyburtius,</hi> of <hi>Valerianus,</hi> of <hi>Lucius</hi> the Pope, the firſt of that name; of <hi>Maximianus,</hi> which all lye buried under the high-Altar. There are many other Reliques in the ſaid Church.</p>
               <p>In this Church we cannot find any Reliques worth the noting;<note place="margin">If the Reader doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the meaning of this paſſage, let him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form himſelf at the <hi>Rainbow</hi> Coffee-houſe in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi>
                  </note> and if the Reader will not believe them to be in this Church, let him go to <hi>Rome</hi> to diſprove the Pope: But now I think on't, it is further thither than it is to St. <hi>Albans,</hi> and therefore he had better believe it and ſtay at home.</p>
               <p>In the Church of <hi>Bartholomew,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Body of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew.</hi>
                  </note> there is the body of St. <hi>Bartholomew</hi> the Apoſtle, in a certain Tabernacle which is ſet upon the high Altar. There is alſo the body of St. <hi>Pauline,</hi> of St. <hi>Albert,</hi> of St. <hi>Marcell,</hi> and of St. <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perante.</hi> Beſides, there are many other Reliques, which with thoſe afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, are ſhewed on St. <hi>Bartholomew-day,</hi> and on <hi>Palm-Sunday.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In what proportions theſe bodies appear, I know not; but if in their full proportions, they have very roomly Altars; and that theſe bodies are not rotten ere now, would be a wonder, nay a great one: But that the world hath been taught to believe,<note place="margin">A Power that our Lord Chriſt did not give to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. Rib of St. <hi>Matthew.</hi> Hand of St. <hi>Nicholas.</hi>
                  </note> that Mr. Popes Holyneſs hath an infallible way of ſaving bodies from putrefaction, and hath been ſo kind to the General of the Jeſuits, as that in the year 1668, to give this power to him, and to the Generals of ſome other Orders.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> there is a Rib of St. <hi>Matthew</hi> the Apoſtle and Evangeliſt. There is alſo an Hand of St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> and an arm of St. <hi>Alexius.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:56276:13"/>
               <p>Truly it is to be believed,<note place="margin">What matter is it ſince we get money by it? Our Ladies Milk I believe this poor Church was endowed when our Ladies Wardrobe was plundered: but Clouts rather than nothing.</note> that Thieves and Robbers have had better quarter with Papiſts, for if they do not be-lye themſelves, the bodies of the Saints have had little or no reſt in their graves.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>George</hi> are theſe Reliques; part of our Ladies milk: certain pieces alſo of her Garments. There is alſo the banner, ſpear, and head of St. <hi>George.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That there was ſuch a St. <hi>George,</hi> is as great a queſtion as that of our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Milk is a Lye; but if they have any part of St. <hi>George,</hi> how came it to paſs they did not get part of his horſe, and of the Dragon he killed? they would have made excellent Reliques.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Anaſtaſins</hi> is the pillar whereupon the bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> was beheaded.<note place="margin">The Pillar on which St. <hi>Paul</hi> was beheaded. But alas! there is no Sword to be found that did it: and this is moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ill for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And of this Pillar there are ſo many pieces in the world, inſomuch that if there were a collection made of them, they would make ten pillars. But I pray, have they not the arm of the man, and the ſword that cut off his head? it would do well if they were produced.</p>
               <p>In the Church of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> is the Altar which is called <hi>Scala Coeli:</hi> Upon this Altar all they that ſing Maſs, or cauſe Maſſes to be ſung for the ſouls that are in Purgatory, through the Merits of the ſame bleſſed Virgin,<note place="margin">Scala Coeli.</note> the ſaid ſouls are delivered out of hand from the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pains of Purgatory, and brought unto the everlaſting joys of Heaven. Moreove whatſoever is devoutly asked in that place, it is without all doubt granted. In the ſame Church are hidden alſo the bones of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Martyrs, all which are moſt precious Reliques.</p>
               <p>It's ten thouſand to one if this be not all found falſe; and that it may appear ſo, do but call to mind what St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. with 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. which ſhows the Virgins Mediatorſhip, and her Altars vertue, to be a cheat to bring griſt to the Pope's Mill.</p>
               <p>And it's to be noted, that he that invented Purgatory, contrived the way out of it, that he might bring money into his own pocket.</p>
               <p>In the Church of <hi>St. Gregory</hi> there are, beſides divers other, theſe two principal Reliques:
<list>
                     <item>1. The arm of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Pope.</item>
                     <item>2. The thigh of St. <hi>Panthaleon.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Note how theſe <hi>Cannibals</hi> pull the Saints in pieces that they may not eat their bones, but by ſhowing their bones may eat up the people.</p>
               <p>In the Church which is called <hi>Sancta Maria <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> is the Image of our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> the Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Good imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for an Angel to turn Image carrier</note> which St. <hi>Luke</hi> painted at <hi>Troas</hi> a City, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. This Image an Angel brought into the aforeſaid Church. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> this Image is ſo great, that when all the Church was burnt, yet this Image had no harm<note n="*" place="margin">A very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle. Pieces of Fragments. I ſuppoſe they encreaſe as well as the reſt; but I pray tell me the virtues of theſe reliques.</note>.</p>
               <p>Curſed be the Image and the Image-maker, ſaith the Scripture; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any Angel, it muſt be one of the fallen Angels, who alſo taught the prieſts to put ſuch a Lye upon St. <hi>Luke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover in the aforenamed Church there are kept as Reliques, certain pieces of the fragments which remained of the five barley Loaves and two fiſhes, when Chriſt in the Wilderneſs fed ſo miraculouſly five thouſand peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. There are divers others Reliques which were brought out of the church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard of <hi>St. Calixt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But whether fragments of the bread or of the fiſhes, or both, we will not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56276:14"/>contend; and he that is minded to fiſh for lyes let him caſt his nets into the <hi>Roman</hi> Ocean, which Sea is certainly ſtored with ſuch fiſh. As for the bread of life I am ſure they have none; and as for their nameleſs Reliques I ſuppoſe we may give as much credit to them as to the fragments, and we may look upon them with as much veneration, but any thing good Mr. Pope! to fill our Treaſures, and maintain our pride and tyranny.</p>
               <p>In the Church of the <hi>holy Apoſtles</hi> are theſe Reliques following: The Bodies of <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bodies of St. <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi> St. <hi>Thomas</hi> his Cloak.</note> The Body of <hi>Sabinus</hi> the Martyr. The Cloak of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> the Apoſtle. The Foot of St. <hi>Philip.</hi> The Arm of St. <hi>James.</hi> A Rib of St. <hi>Lawrence.</hi> The Shoulder-plate and the Arm of St. <hi>Blaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have but their bare word for all this; and they which we have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in ſo many lyes already, how ſhall we give them credit in this?<note place="margin">Arm of Saint <hi>Matthew.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Marcellus</hi> is the Arm of St. <hi>Matthew</hi> the Apoſtle and Evangeliſt.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Sylveſter</hi> is the Head of St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Head of St. <hi>John Baptiſt.</hi> Hands and Feet of S. <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</hi>
                  </note> the Hands and Feet of St. <hi>Lawrence,</hi> and a piece of St. <hi>Francis</hi> Cowle, and many other Reliques which are ſhewed on the Feaſts of St. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> and of St. <hi>Sylveſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This looks as like a cheat as all the reſt; for can any wiſe man think that <hi>Herod</hi> preſerved it? and in four days it would ſtink as bad as any dead fleſh: therefore this untruth accuſeth it ſelf; and as for the Cowle of St. <hi>Francis,</hi> he being a notorious thief, is as miraculous as the Croſs of the Thief which they ſay is preſerved.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Lawrence</hi> are theſe Reliques following:<note place="margin">The Blood, the Fat, the Clout, the Gridiron.</note> Two Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons full of the Fat and Blood of St. <hi>Lawrence.</hi> Alſo a Veſſel full of the roaſted fleſh of bleſſed <hi>Lawrence.</hi> The Clout wherewith the Angel did wipe the Body of St. <hi>Lawrence. Item,</hi> the Cridiron whereupon St. <hi>Lawrence</hi> was roaſted.</p>
               <p>That St. <hi>Lawrence</hi> was roaſted is true; but firſt, Saints did not uſe to be very fat. <hi>2ly,</hi> His fat dropt into the fire, ſo did his fleſh. 3. How could they ſeparate his fat from his blood as it dropt through the Gridiron? and that the Tormentors ſhould give the Chriſtians his fleſh, is as uncredible as that they have veſſels full of it; and that the Angel ſtood in need of a clout to wipe his body, is as likely as that they have the Clout or Gridiron.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Julian</hi> there is a certain kind of holy water, whoſe virtue and power is ſo great that it eaſily healeth all them that be diſeaſed of the Ague. It cureth alſo all other infirmities and diſeaſes, ſo that they which will be made whole, take that holy water faſting, and ſay three <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> and as many <hi>Ave Maries</hi> in the honour of Almighty God, and of the glorious Virgin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and alſo of St. <hi>Julian</hi> and St. <hi>Albert,</hi> or elſe cauſe one Maſs to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the honour of the aforenamed Saint <hi>Albert.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I wonder ſo many <hi>Papiſts</hi> die of the Pox, and that the old Prieſt was ſo long in a Doctors hands that kept an Apothecaries ſhop in St. <hi>Giles</hi> Pariſh, if there be ſuch healing vertue in their holy water? But one thing I note, that the Virgin and the Saints have honour, but Chriſt is forgotten; and how the Popes themſelves have not been cured of thoſe foul diſeaſes by which they have periſhed, if they have had ſuch excellent and infallible Remedies!</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Vitus</hi> there is a Marble ſtone ſet about with Iron,<note place="margin">Stone on which a 1000 poor Saints was ſlain.</note> upon which were ſlain more than a thouſand bodies of holy Martyrs. In
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56276:14"/>this Church there is ſo great virtue and grace through the merits of thoſe holy Martyrs <hi>Vitus, Modeſtus,</hi> and <hi>Creſcentia,</hi> that if ſo be any man be bitten with a mad Dog, or of any other beaſt, and take a piece of bread, and dip it in the Oyl of St. <hi>Vitus,</hi> and ſo eat it, he ſhall ſtraightway be made whole.</p>
               <p>All their healing is aſcribed to the Virgin, or to Saints, not to Chriſt. And if they were not all bit with ſome Beaſt or another, they would not ſet Saints of their own coining above the Son of God, Jeſus, whom God hath made to all a means of ſpiritual health and eternal ſalvation. But of this Oyl of St. <hi>Vitus</hi> I find not one word but at <hi>Rome;</hi> and its virtues are not there mentioned.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Braxed</hi> there is a Chappel which is called <hi>Libera nos a penis inferni,</hi> and <hi>Ortus Paradiſi,</hi> in the which is a Pillar whereunto our Lord Jeſus Chriſt was bound in his paſſion.</p>
               <p>But our comfort is, That we are not bound to believe it.</p>
               <p>In the midſt of this Church there is a round ſtone incloſed with Iron; under this ſtone is the blood of many holy Martyrs which bleſſed St. <hi>Brax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> gathered up with a certain Sponge, and put it in a pit, laying that round ſtone upon it.</p>
               <p>They that tell theſe lyes, will be in a pit one day, in which there is no water to cool their tongues, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.24.</p>
               <p>In this Church alſo there is an Altar upon the which Pope <hi>Paſcalis</hi> ſaid five Maſſes for a certain ſoul departed. Which Maſſes being once finiſhed, he ſaw the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> take that ſoul out of Purgatory, and carry it into the boſom of Almighty God, as ye may ſee it plainly painted upon the wall of the ſaid Church. When Pope <hi>Paſcalis</hi> had ſeen this miracle, he granted by his Apoſtolique Authority, That whoſoever did either ſing maſs, or cauſe maſs to be ſung on that Altar, he ſhould deliver for every time ſo doing, one foul out of the bitter pains of Purgatory</p>
               <p>That this looks, as the reſt do, like a piece of Forgery from top to the bottom; for the Virgin never came near any other place but where Gods bleſſed preſence is, ſince ſhe left this World; her ſpirit went to God that gave it, and thence it did never ſtir.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Potentiana,</hi> is the Altar upon which St. <hi>Peter</hi> did ſing his firſt maſs. Alſo a Pit, in which lieth hid the blood of three thouſand martyrs.</p>
               <p>It is as ſcandalous to faſten ſaying maſs upon St. <hi>Peter,</hi> as upon St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who knew that your Maſſing-trick never came into the heart of Chriſt or any of his ſincere followers, if St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf ſay true, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. ver. 20, comp. with ver. 27. and if the Popes Maſſing had been Gods counſel, it would have been <hi>Paul</hi>'s Doctrine.</p>
               <p>In another Church of St. <hi>Laurence</hi> there are theſe Reliques:<note place="margin">A piece of the Gridiron on which they roaſted him. One Arm of St. <hi>Laurence.</hi> Certain of his bones.</note> A piece of St. <hi>Laurence</hi>'s Gridiron upon which he was roaſted. One Arm of St. <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</hi> Alſo in a glaſs of Cryſtal there are certain coals which all men may clearly and plainly ſee, wherewith bleſſed <hi>Laurence</hi> was roaſted. There are alſo certain of his bones.</p>
               <p>What coals are kept in glaſſes, I know not; but of this I am ſure, that the inventors of theſe things are firebrands of hell, and ſuch for which coals hotter than coals of Juniper, is prepared. But let her alone till that day come, as long as the good Angels appear upon the ſight of theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:56276:15"/>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Peter ad Vincula,</hi> there be the bonds of Iron where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with St. <hi>Peter</hi> was bound at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> under King <hi>Herod.</hi> There are alſo the chains wherewith he was bound at <hi>Rome</hi> under <hi>Nero</hi> the Emperor. Theſe chains be of ſo great virtue, that great and wonderful miracles are daily wrought by them, as they ſay.</p>
               <p>In this Church there is ſo great virtue and grace,<note place="margin">Away to <hi>Rome</hi> ye <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> and get your Pardon from the Pope, for you muſt never look to have it from God.</note> that whoſoever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly comes unto it, although never ſo ſinful, he ſhall depart and go his way, delivered and free from all his ſins.</p>
               <p>Many other Reliques there are in the foreſaid Church, as you may ſee in a certain Table that hangeth on the Wall.</p>
               <p>There I perceive a notable trick, that to draw the people where there is not many feigned Reliques, there is high pretences of Pardon and healing, and all to catch money; and I do believe that more money hath been drawn to the Popes Coffers, than tongue can expreſs; and ſure I am, to this day poor <hi>England</hi> is much exhauſted by theſe devilliſh cheats of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Synagogue.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Mary,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">More of <hi>Lukes</hi> Painting! I ſuppoſe this ſcarlet whore hath gotten more money by <hi>Luke's</hi> Painting, than ever he did himſelf.</note> called <hi>Ara Coeli,</hi> is the Sepulcher of St. <hi>Helen</hi> the mother of <hi>Conſtantine.</hi> Alſo an Image of our Lady which St. <hi>Luke</hi> painted even after ſuch form and faſhion as ſhe was in when ſhe ſtood by the croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt weeping and lamenting. This Image is full of virtue, and worketh daily many miracles.</p>
               <p>To detect this Lye, we need no more but to remember, <hi>Luke</hi> was not then converted, nor on the place where Chriſt dyed, and was a Phyſician; yet if the Whore tells truth he did paint; and ſome <hi>Monks</hi> that live in the Engliſh Monaſtry of <hi>Benedictines,</hi> who love painting, have preached this Doctrine that <hi>Luke</hi> was bound Apprentice to a Painter.<note place="margin">Father <hi>How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,</hi> Father <hi>Hitchcock</hi> when in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt. Ladies Hair.</note> But they talked like <hi>Engliſh Monks,</hi> and their credit is not very good with us at this time.</p>
               <p>In the Church of our Lady called <hi>Sancta Maria ſuper Minervam,</hi> are theſe Reliques: The hair of our Lady, and certain pieces of her Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>Item,</hi> Divers parts of the three Patriarchs, <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and alſo of <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet.</p>
               <p>This looks like plain Forgery, and tricking, to deceive the poor people; for all the parts of the Patriarchs were turned to aſhes long before, and ſo was <hi>Daniel,</hi> who dyed in <hi>Babylon</hi> in all likelihood. But becauſe all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches muſt have ſome Reliques, this is content with a little hair, and a few tatters of old clothes.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Euſtache</hi> are theſe Reliques:<note place="margin">More of the Croſs. More of Chriſts blood. A piece of the Crown. Parcels of Chriſts Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel.</note> Part of the holy croſs, a good quantity of Chriſts bloods, a piece of the crown of thorns, parcels of Chriſts apparel, the rib of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> certain of the coals wherewith St. <hi>Laurence</hi> was roaſted.</p>
               <p>I perceive a carnal Church rejoyce in carnal things, as blood, old clouts and bones of men, or any thing to keep the heart off from good, and below Chriſt in its meditation; but the firſt Chriſtians gloried in no ſuch reliques of blood and bones, and coals and clouts; there was then no ſuch cheats.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Martinellus</hi> is part of that garment and coat which our Lady did knit and make with her own hands, and gave it to her Son Jeſus Chriſt, which coat did grow even as he grew.</p>
               <p>That there was knitting in thoſe times, I know not; but I doubt they that invented this ſtory, are ignorant of Chriſt and his mother, and his coat alſo; and if the pretenders were put to prove, they would prove no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but that themſelves are a company of cheats.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:56276:15"/>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Barbara,</hi> are theſe Reliques:<note place="margin">Ladies Kirtle. <hi>Bartholomew</hi>'s Cloak.</note> The head and the vail of St. <hi>Barbara.</hi> Our Ladies Kirtle. St. <hi>Bartholomews</hi> Cloak. The Deacons apparel of St. <hi>Laurence.</hi> The Hair of <hi>Mary Magdalen:</hi> and divers other Reliques of St. <hi>Margaret, Felix Lotitius, Chriſtopher, Sebaſtian, Alexius, Martha,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I confeſs it were worth the while for a Taylor to go to that Church, as they do here in <hi>England,</hi> to ſee what faſhion the Lady's Kirtles, and <hi>Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomew</hi>'s Cloak are of, and if they like the faſhion of our Lady's Kirtle, and his Cloak, to let us have the faſhion that they uſed, for ſure they were a vertuous people; but for the reſt of the Trumpery, I would not go over the Gutter to ſee them.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Laurence</hi> there is a great Bottle of glaſs, of the which on St. <hi>Damaſus</hi> day men uſe to drink in the honour and worſhip of the aforenamed St. <hi>Damaſus.</hi> The virtue of this Bottle is ſo great, that as many as drink of it, believe faithfully they ſhall be delivered from all Agues, and other grievous infirmities.</p>
               <p>They would do well to bring us ſome of thoſe Bottles hither, for I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they are full quarts, and our folk cheat us with pint and a half. But now I remember, it will hinder the trade of our learned Doctors, and nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Apothecaries; and I know when Popery comes in, their Trade will go out, by reaſon of the many Miracles that will be done.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Blaſe de Panneta,</hi> is a large piece of the holy Croſs.<note place="margin">A large piece of the Croſs. More Croſs ſtill!</note> There are alſo certain pieces of the Garments of our Lady of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> St. <hi>Blaſe,</hi> St. <hi>Doria, Creiſant,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This was ſome poor Church that could get nought but a good log of the Croſs, and a few ſhreds of our Lady's old Petticoat,<note place="margin">I am very ſorry this Church could not get one ſmall piece of <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalens Noli me tangere;</hi> it would have been an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to her.</note> and ſome rags of the other Saints which had no virtue that we hear of. I fear therefore, that this Church was as one born out of due time; therefore being the leaſt of all the Churches, was content with the rags: But the miſchief on't is, the poor Rag merchants have been abominably put to it, to loſe ſo good a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Rags; but St. <hi>Blaſe</hi> Church hath them, and ſo much good may do her with them: I ſuppoſe that ſome little two-penny miracles have been wrought with them</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Mary Tranſpontin</hi> there are this day the two Pillars whereunto the holy Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> were bound, and ſo afterward whipped and ſcourged; the which Pillar all men according to their devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may daily come unto and touch.</p>
               <p>Did God ever appoint, or did it ever come into his heart to appoint ſuch Devotion? He may well ſay, Who required theſe things at your hands, to go in devotion to Wooden Pillars?</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>James</hi> is the ſtone of that Altar upon which Chriſt was offered in the Temple, when <hi>Simeon</hi> took him in his arms,<note place="margin">The Stone on which Chriſt was offered.</note> embraced him, and ſaid, <hi>Now letteſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace according to thy word,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Titus Veſpaſian</hi> had burnt the Temple many hundred years before;<note place="margin">Note.</note> and how could the Prieſts when they began to ſhew ſuch tricks, find ſuch ſtone or ſtones? and <hi>Rome</hi> being 2000 miles off, how got they the ſtone? and if they had it, what good can be expected from it, but to ſet fools a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing?</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Katharine</hi> is part of the Oyl which flowed out of the Sepulcher of the aforenamed St. <hi>Katharine.</hi> There is alſo of the Milk,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Catharine</hi> Milk and Blood.</note>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:56276:16"/>which inſtead of Blood, flowed out of her holy body when ſhe was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed.</p>
               <p>How credible this is, I will leave the Reader to judg; but muſt boldly ſay, that the tricks the Prieſts of <hi>Rome</hi> have to get money, are both many and ſtrange.</p>
               <p>In the Church of the Holy Ghoſt is the Arm of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Andrews <hi>Arm.</hi> Kates <hi>Finger.</hi>
                  </note> the Finger of St. <hi>Katharine,</hi> and many other Reliques.</p>
               <p>I perceive the Holy Ghoſt is in no great credit with them; for his church is but poorly endowed, that is, only furniſhed with an Arm and a Finger. As for the many Reliques oft-times named, I perceive they are of no great value.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Regiſter of ſuch Reliques as I have found in reading Chronicles and Hiſtories.</head>
               <p>POPE <hi>Leo</hi> the third bearing rule, there were given to <hi>Carolus Magnus,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> for the good ſervice he did to Mother holy Church, theſe Reliques following:<note place="margin">A Crown of Thorns. A Nail. A large piece of the Croſs The Napkin he wiped his face with The Lady's Smock. The Swadling Clouts. <hi>Simeons</hi> Arm.</note> Firſt of all, the crown of thorns wherewith Chriſt was crowned. 2. One of the Nails wherewith Chriſt was faſtned to the croſs. 3. A large piece of the Tree whereon Chriſt was hanged when he ſuffered his Paſſion. 4. Chriſts Napkin wherewith he uſed commonly to wipe his face. 5. The Smock of our bleſſed Lady, which ſhe had on when ſhe brought forth Chriſt. 6. The Swadling-clouts wherein Chriſt was wrapped when he lay in the Manger. 7. Old <hi>Simeons</hi> Arm wherewith he embraced Chriſt in the Temple of <hi>Solomon,</hi> when he broke out into theſe words, <hi>Nunc dimittis,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>One may ſee by this Paragraph, the fountain of all the Popiſh cheats, is the Pope himſelf; and that he endoweth perſons and places with what of thoſe Reliques he pleaſeth; and if he ſay, This is the Ladies Smock, it is believed to be ſo; and truly, it may by ſome be thought rational, becauſe that Mr. Pope is a very honeſt Gentleman, and never told a lye in plain downright Engliſh in all his life.</p>
               <p>The Head of St. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> is affirmed of ſome to be in a certain Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtry which King <hi>Pipinus</hi> built in <hi>France.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Head of St. <hi>John Baptiſt.</hi>
                  </note> Some ſay it is at <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> ſome hold that it is <hi>apud Caſtrum Nogenti;</hi> ſome maintain that it is at <hi>Rome</hi> in the church of <hi>Sylveſter;</hi> but I believe it is conſumed to duſt according to Gods Ordinance upon all fleſh.</p>
               <p>This his head St. <hi>John</hi> himſelf did reveal to tvvo Monks vvhich came to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> on Pilgrimage.</p>
               <p>That St. <hi>John Baptist</hi> had more heads than one;<note place="margin">Note.</note> for in the church of St. <hi>Sylveſter,</hi> as before, you find his head. But it ſeemeth by this Paragraph, they cannot agree where it is; by which you may ſee the folly of theſe men and their followers, who are ſo fond of deviſed fables, that they will believe contradictions.</p>
               <p>Yet by the way we are to conſider, that the Pope can turn what he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth into <hi>John Baptiſts</hi> Head; and can ſay to his Reliques, Encreaſe and multiply.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:56276:16"/>
               <p>Pope <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the ſecond bearing rule, St. <hi>Andrew</hi> appeared to a Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,<note place="margin">The Spear that pierced Chriſt.</note> which at that preſent was one of the Army which went to conquer the Holy Land, and to win Chriſts Sepulcher out of the Infidels hands, and ſaid unto him, <hi>Come, I will ſhew thee where the ſpear is that pierced Chriſts heart when he hanged on the croſs;</hi> for it lay hid in the ground,<note place="margin">The Tale of the Spear. His apparel was not hurt, becauſe he had none on; but his body was ſo ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched that it coſt him his life.</note> being buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church at <hi>Antioch.</hi> This Soldier, at the commandment of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> went unto the place appointed, and digged out the Spear, which was ſo virtuous, noble, and precious a Relique, and of ſo great power, that a certain man called <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> cauſed a great fire to be made of thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen foot in length; and he having the Spear in his hand, went through the fire, and was not hurt, neither in himſelf, nor in his apparel.</p>
               <p>Moreover, through the virtue of this Spear,<note place="margin">I wonder they would ſtay ſo long from vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals till almoſt ſtarv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when they had ſuch a miraculous Spear about them. I would wiſh the <hi>Saracens</hi> to have a care of this Spearl</note> when the Army of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were ſo pined away with hunger, that they were almoſt compelled one to eat another, this Famine ceaſed, and plenty of all things was mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred unto them; yea, through the virtue of this Spear, they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came their Enemies, and had moſt glorious victories. By the virtue al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo of this Spear, a certain man called <hi>Boemundus,</hi> flew in one battel an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand <hi>Saracens;</hi> and beſides many other notable ſpoils, he got Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen thouſand Camels, wherewith the Chriſtians were greatly comforted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſo great labours taken for the recovery of the Holy Land, and of Chriſts Sepulcher.</p>
               <p>It would pierce any Chriſtians heart to hear ſuch invented lyes impoſed on the pretenders to Chriſtianity: But what is it that the Father of lyes, and Mother of abominations cannot invent? I will be bold to ſay, that in the Kingdom of <hi>Spain</hi> this Spear is to be ſeen in forty places; nay, they have pretended to have obtained great Victories againſt the <hi>Moors:</hi> nay, they have attributed much of their expelling the Moors out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Spain,</hi> to theſe Spears; and every one of them is the very Spear that pierced the ſide of our Lord Chriſt when upon the croſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Balduinus,</hi> Emperor of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> gave unto <hi>Lewis</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Crown of Thorns. More great pieces of the Croſs! The Spunge that the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar was given in.</note> for moſt precious Reliques, and things of incomparable virtue, the Crown of thorns that Chriſt did wear upon his head, and a great part of the croſs whereon Chriſt dyed, with the Spunge wherewith they gave Chriſt vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar and gall to drink, and the iron of the ſpear wherewith Chriſt was thruſt to the heart on the croſs.</p>
               <p>O the Frauds of <hi>Rome!</hi> we had the ſpear given before by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban,</hi> and the great Wonders it did without its head; What would it have done if the head had been on it? We have before found a piece of the crown, and the whole crown, and behold it's here again! ſure they that can make a Wafer Chriſt, can make Chriſt many crowns.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt, being Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> Chriſts coat which had no ſeam, was found (as they ſay), and brought unto <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and laid up by the croſs of Chriſt as a moſt precious and healthful Relique.</p>
               <p>Thus they aſcribed the power of healing to the old coat which they pretend to have found, which they would not have done if they had not loſt the right faith of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Sibel,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Fuleo</hi> King of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and Wife to <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doricus,</hi> by whom ſhe had many goodly children, afterward by the conſent of her Husband, returned unto <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and became a Religious wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, where ſhe found (as they write) a good quantity of Chriſts blood, which <hi>Nicodemus</hi> and <hi>Joſeph of Arimathea</hi> got out of the wounds of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56276:17"/>Chriſt when they waſhed his body, and ſhe ſent it to her Husband. Which blood (as they ſay) is at this day kept at <hi>Bruges,</hi> and is ſhewed every year to the people on the third day of the Month of <hi>May.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe men are gone from the virtue of Chriſts blood to the matter;<note place="margin">Note.</note> and that Chriſts blood can be ſaved 1600 years, is incredible! but that the people ſhould make a piece of Pageantry of it, ſet it out to ſhew for money on ſuch a day in the year, is prophaneſs.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Euſebius</hi> the firſt,<note place="margin">The Croſs again!</note> being Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> the croſs whereupon Chriſt died, was found at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by <hi>Helena,</hi> Mother to <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and kept for a noble and precious Relique.</p>
               <p>Of this Croſs there have been cut out for Reliques ſo many pieces ſince that time, that if they were gathered together, they would come to a greater quantity than five of the greateſt Oaks in <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to encreaſe the honour of this croſs, the aforeſaid Pope <hi>Euſebius</hi> ordained the Feaſt of the <hi>Invention of the croſs,</hi> and commanded it to be kept holy for ever after.</p>
               <p>The uſe of the croſs is an invention of fooliſh men.<note place="margin">Note.</note> This is not the croſs St. <hi>Paul</hi> gloried in, as the Papiſts do.</p>
               <p>The aforeſaid <hi>Helena</hi> found at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the three Nails wherewith Chriſt was faſtened to the croſs, and brought them with her to <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> with great reverence and honour, and gave them unto her Son <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> who took one of them, and put it upon his bridle, which he uſed always when he went to the Wars, and at no other time, that by virtue thereof he might have good ſucceſs againſt his Enemies. This Nail is at this day kept at <hi>Mediolanum,</hi> and had there in great reverence.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Nail he put upon his Helmet, which he uſed in the time of Wars, that by virtue thereof he might the ſooner get the victory over his Adverſaries.</p>
               <p>The third Nail he threvv into the Sea, called <hi>Mare Adriaticum,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, mitigate, appeaſe, and aſſvvage the cruel ſtorms and nerce compeſts of that cruel and raging Sea.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee the three Nails diſpoſed of;<note place="margin">Note.</note> and theſe lying Prieſts do feign to have them as Monuments in other churches in <hi>Rome,</hi> as you heard before.</p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Helena</hi> brought vvith her alſo a good part of the holy croſs from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Here is now a good part of the Croſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</note> vvhich ſhe cauſed to be ſumptuouſly garniſhed, and gallantly trimmed, vvith a caſe of ſilver and precrous ſtones.</p>
               <p>And this part of the croſs thus decked and adorned, ſhe brought after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard to <hi>Rome</hi> vvith great reverence, vvorſhip, and honour, and placed it in that church vvhich is novv called <hi>The church of St. Croſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus theſe men that have forgot to reverence Chriſt,<note place="margin">Note.</note> do adore and adorn the croſs.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt reigning,<note place="margin">Here is the Coat again.</note> Chriſts coat that vvas vvithout ſeam, vvhich the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> made vvith her ovvn hands for him, vvas found not far from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in a Tovvn called <hi>Saphat,</hi> of theſe three Biſhops, <hi>Gregory</hi> of <hi>Antioch, Thomas</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Conſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This coat vvas laid up in a fair Marble cheſt, and vvas found very fair, vvithout breach, and uncorrupt.</p>
               <p>The three aforeſaid Biſhops taking this coat of Chriſt out of the cheſt,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56276:17"/>brought it unto <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and laid it up very devoutly in a cheſt of <hi>Ivory,</hi> and with great honour as a moſt precious Relique. This is that coat for which the Soldiers did caſt lots when Chriſt hanged on the croſs.</p>
               <p>And yet theſe lyars pretend to have it as a Relique in other places. Lyars had need have good memories. It's a like matter the <hi>Roman</hi> Soldiers ſhould part with a coat, that wanted cloathes, as moſt Soldiers do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Egelvotus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> found at <hi>Papia</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> one of St. <hi>Austins</hi> arms, and gave for it an hundred Talents of ſilver, and one of gold, and brought it with him into <hi>England</hi> with great reverence, and placed it as a moſt precious Relique in the City of <hi>Venturia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may ſee that they will be at great charge to maintain their ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:<note place="margin">Note.</note> But how can they ſay this was his Arm? one mans Arm may be like another.</p>
               <p>The Diſh which was ſet before Chriſt with the Paſchal Lamb that night wherein he inſtituted the Sacrament of his body and blood, was afterward found by the <hi>Genoueſes</hi> at <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> and brought home into their own City with great joy, and is now there kept as a moſt precious Relique.</p>
               <p>As the fool thinks, ſo the bell clinks. How came Chriſts diſh at <hi>Caeſarea?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note> And how, 1500 years after, could they know that from another diſh?</p>
               <p>The aforeſaid <hi>Genoueſes</hi> have alſo the aſhes of <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> which they brought with them from <hi>Mirea</hi> unto their own City, and keep them as moſt precious and bleſſed Reliques, as by whoſe virtue they have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten moſt triumphant victories, and moſt victorious triumphs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> was not burnt, but buried by his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.12.<note place="margin">Note.</note> which was a 1000 years before the <hi>Genoneſes</hi> were a people.</p>
               <p>The Head of St. <hi>George</hi> is kept of the <hi>Venetians</hi> even at this day as a moſt precious Relique.</p>
               <p>This is a Fiction like the ſtory of his killing the Dragon.</p>
               <p>The Head of St. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula</hi> was tranſlated from <hi>Cales</hi> unto <hi>Bergomo</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note> where it is now kept in the Monaſtry of the <hi>Auſtin-Friers,</hi> as a moſt holy Relique, and had in great reverence of the people.</p>
               <p>Her Body, with the Bodies of the other 11000 Virgins which ſuffered with her, lye buried in <hi>Colon</hi> a City of <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You may ſee every place will pretend ſome holy Relique to invite peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to gaze.<note place="margin">Note.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Body of St. <hi>Mark</hi> the Evangeliſt, was brought by a certain Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant from <hi>Alexandria</hi> unto <hi>Venice,</hi> where it know kept and had in great reverence; the <hi>Venetians</hi> taking St. <hi>Mark</hi> for their chief Patron.</p>
               <p>When men turn Papiſts, they go from God to creatures, and inſtead of Gods protection, put themſelves under the Patronage of dead creatures,<note place="margin">Note.</note> inſtead of the living God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Paleologus,</hi> graciouſly eſcaping out of the hands of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Emperor, brought with him out of <hi>Achaia,</hi> the head of St. <hi>Andrew</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle unto <hi>Rome,</hi> and with great humility gave it unto Pope <hi>Pius,</hi> who garniſhing it moſt ſumptuouſly, placed it with great honour and high rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the Church of St. <hi>Peter</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> as we have heretofore heard.</p>
               <p>How the Heads and Members of their Saints are halled about to make a ſhow of!<note place="margin">Note.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Black Friers gave to King <hi>Henery</hi> the third for a moſt precious Relique, a white Marble-ſtone wherein was the print of a mans foot, making the King believe that it was that ſtone whereupon Chriſt ſtood, when he leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56276:18"/>this world, aſcended into the Kingdom of his Father; and that it was the print, length, and breadth of Chriſts foot; left here in the earth for a worthy remembrance of his wonderful aſcenſion.</p>
               <p>The Gray Friers gave to the aforeſaid King the blood of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The White Monks preſented unto him our Ladies Milk, with moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſupplications unto his Grace that he would be good and gracious, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable and liberal to his poor Beads-men and daily Orators.</p>
               <p>The great quantities of Chriſts Blood,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and our Ladies Milk, ſhow the cheat, as well as the length of time that they pretend to have kept it.</p>
               <p>But I confeſs, they that can turn Wine into the Blood of Chriſt, may find great ſtore.</p>
               <p>The Bones of <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet were tranſlated from <hi>Rome</hi> unto <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> and there placed as Reliques of great virtue.</p>
               <p>To confute this Lye,<note place="margin">Note.</note> take notice, <hi>Samuel</hi> was turned to his duſt hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of years before the Papiſts began to ſhow theſe tricks; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is feigned any man may ſee.</p>
               <p>There hath been an old and long contention between the <hi>French</hi> men and <hi>Italians</hi> concerning the Bodies of St. <hi>Benet</hi> the Monk, and of St. <hi>Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtica</hi> his Siſter. The <hi>French</hi> men ſay plainly, that without all fail they have thoſe bodies, and that they were tranſlated from Mount <hi>Caſſine</hi> unto the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtry <hi>Floriacens,</hi> and there they are kept and honoured as moſt precious Reliques. The <hi>Italians</hi> ſtoutly deny this matter, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that their bodies remain ſtill in Mount <hi>Caſſine;</hi> ſo that whoſoever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> worſhip them, they muſt come thither, and there make their oblation.</p>
               <p>When theſe Fops agree,<note place="margin">Note.</note> I ſhall begin to enquire into this matter, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall believe it.</p>
               <p>The Body of St. <hi>Dioniſe</hi> is ſo holy and precious, that, as it is reported, <hi>Clodoveus</hi> King of <hi>France</hi> became mad and utterly out of his wits, becauſe he unreverently diſcovered the foreſaid body, broke off one of his arms, and privily carried it away with him.</p>
               <p>And ſure no man that is in his wits will believe this ſtory.<note place="margin">Note.</note>
               </p>
               <p>When the Body of <hi>Boniface</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> was brought unto <hi>Fuldes</hi> Monaſtry to be buried, all the Bells in the Countrey rung in moſt goodly and comely order, yea, and that without any help of mans hand, only by the power of God, to teſtifie what a noble and precious Relique was brought unto them.</p>
               <p>O the blaſphemy of theſe people,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that will intitle the Holy and Wiſe God to be a countenance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Follies and Fanaticiſms!</p>
               <p>At <hi>Aquiſgranum</hi> there was ſo great a company of Reliques brought thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>France</hi> that there was a very ſolemn Pilgrimage ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed unto them, which endured the ſpace of ſeven years.</p>
               <p>Among all theſe Reliques the Crown of thorns was,<note place="margin">Here is the Crown of thorns again!</note> which was put on Chriſts head; this they ſay had ſo great virtue in it, that the King holding it in his hand, it flouriſhed and gave out leaves.</p>
               <p>The aforeſaid King brought it from <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> unto <hi>Paris,</hi> and there placed it among the other Reliques.</p>
               <p>I cannot but pity theſe people,<note place="margin">Note.</note> where the King joins with the Clergy to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce or miſlead them; for woful exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ce ſhows, that people for the moſt part will follow the Religion and Manners of their Kings. All the Idolatry that the <hi>Jews</hi> were guilty of, they were led into it by their Kings and Prieſts: what they believe and do, people think it is right.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:56276:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aaron</hi> King of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> ſent to <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>France</hi> the bodies of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Spiratus,</hi> with the head of St. <hi>Panthaleon,</hi> for moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reliques.</p>
               <p>What the Pagan Prince ſent,<note place="margin">Note.</note> might have been refuſed by the pretender to Chriſtianity, if he had not been as great a fool as the other. It's not the name, but the power of Chriſtianity, or Spirit of it, that makes men wiſe.</p>
               <p>The head of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Pope, and the arm of St. <hi>Leo,</hi> were tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Pope <hi>John</hi> unto the Church <hi>Sinonſe,</hi> and there placed as holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques.</p>
               <p>Reliques they might be, but not holy, if the Limbs of Popes.<note place="margin">Note.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The body of St. <hi>Martin</hi> was ſo holy a Relique, that after it was tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (as they write) it cleanſed the Leper of his Leproſie, it healed a man diſeaſed of the Palſie, and reſtored a blind man to his ſight, and made all the Trees in the Countrey to bring forth ſuch leaves, as far paſſed the courſe of nature.</p>
               <p>If it had ever ſuch a power, when did it leave or loſe it?<note place="margin">Note.</note> it's a wonder it do not ſo ſtill; but it may be a Lye, for all it flouriſhed ſo with leaves. The Popiſh Miracles are but tricks of art, and tales to pleaſe fools.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Bruno</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Colen,</hi> brought with him from <hi>Rome</hi> St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſtaff, and placed it at the City of <hi>Colen</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> as in holy and precious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique.</p>
               <p>If the Papiſts did own St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s golden doctrine,<note place="margin">Note.</note> they would not much admire his wooden ſtick: but any thing will ſerve wooden Chriſtians!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rainoldus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Colen,</hi> tranſlated the bodies of the three Kings that came to worſhip Chriſt, from <hi>Maediolanum</hi> unto <hi>Colen.</hi> Theſe bodies were before taken away by <hi>Helen, Conſtantine's</hi> Mother, out of <hi>India,</hi> and brought unto <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> Afterward they were tranſlated by Biſhop <hi>Euſtorgius</hi> from thence unto <hi>Mediolanum,</hi> and ſo from that place unto <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> where they now remain as moſt worthy Reliques, and work great Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, as they ſay.</p>
               <p>Is it not a ſhame that Chriſtians ſhould be ſo bewitched,<note place="margin">Note.</note> as to think that the dead bodies of three Pagan Kings, which doubtleſs were hundreds of years before turned to duſt, ſhould be ſet up as Reliques of Saints! And could <hi>Helen</hi> fetch them from the remote parts of <hi>India,</hi> where ſhe never was? But I ſee every place muſt have ſome foppery or other to invite fools, and to inrich Prieſts.</p>
               <p>The holy and religious Monk St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> after that he was canonized and made a Saint by Pope <hi>Alexander,</hi> did ſo abound in working Miracles in the place where his body lay, by reaſon thereof great confluence of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple reſorted to the Abby, that the Abbot of the place forbad him to work any more miracles. And bleſſed St. <hi>Bernard</hi> meekly and reverently obeyed Father Abbots commandment, and ſo for ever he took his eaſe, and wrought no more miracles.</p>
               <p>This obedience was ſhewed, St. <hi>Bernard</hi> being dead.</p>
               <p>A man would ſtand amazed at the confidence theſe people have in telling of lyes, yea, contradictions; but if true and conſiſtent,<note place="margin">Note.</note> then doubtleſs the Abbot was an ill-natur'd fellow, that he would hinder the good that coſt him nothing. And had St. <hi>Bernard</hi> been ſet at work by the liberal God, he would not have been ſubject to a covetous Abbot, that had ſo much of his meat and drink devoured by poor people. But this ſounds like the reſt.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:56276:19"/>
               <p>In a certain Monaſtery of St. <hi>Gabriel</hi> is a great ſtone that fell down from Heaven, having in it the ſign of the holy Croſs, and a very lively Image of Chriſt, and written upon it with Golden Letters theſe words, <hi>Jeſus Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarenus Rex Judeorum.</hi> This great ſtone, as they ſay, is a great precious Relique, and worketh great Miracles in the great Monaſtry of great Saint <hi>Gabriel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We may ſee what takes people off from holy Scripture,<note place="margin">Note.</note> from God, from Chriſt; they have laden all people, and filled all places with ſuch lyes, cheats, and <hi>hocus-pocus</hi> tricks, that they have no room left in their hearts for truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hugo</hi> the Monk at the deſire of Monk <hi>William,</hi> Abbot of <hi>Hirſangia,</hi> ſent unto him the hair of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> which was received with great reverence, and placed in the aforeſaid Abby as a true precious Relique, not without great honour daily done unto it.</p>
               <p>They honour any thing but Chriſt and God.<note place="margin">Note.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Norbertus</hi> came unto <hi>Toline</hi> to ſeek Saints Reliques; and after that he and his Company had given themſelves to faſting and prayer certain days, one of the number of the nine thouſand Virgins appeared unto him, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him her name and the place where ſhe lay. The next day after, the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Norbertus</hi> with his Company took her up with great reverence and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity, and placed her very devoutly, with many other Reliques, in the Monaſtry <hi>Premonſtratenſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus people when they have forſaken the living God,<note place="margin">Note.</note> ſeek dead ſtinking Carcaſes to adore and worſhip; and ſure if <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſtank in four days, this Woman could not be ſweet after many years; but to make it a Miracle they muſt pretend a Viſion.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Norfolk</hi> there was a certain Monaſtry called <hi>Bromholm</hi>-Abbey, in the which was an holy Croſs brought thither by a certain Prieſt. This Croſs was ſo precious a Relique and of ſo great virtue, that it raiſed up unto life thirty-nine dead perſons, reſtored to their ſight nineteen blind men, and wrought many other notable Miracles.</p>
               <p>The people in <hi>Norfolk</hi> uſe to be more ingenuous than to be ſo cheated;<note place="margin">Note.</note> but when Prieſts have once made men blind, they may lead them whither they liſt, out of one error into another.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Winfarthing,</hi> a little Village in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> there was a certain Sword called the Sword of <hi>Winfarthing.</hi> This Sword was counted ſo precious a Relique, and of ſo great virtue, that there was a ſolemn Pilgrimage uſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, with large gifts and offerings, with Vow-makings, Crouchings and Kiſſings. This Sword was viſited and ſought far and near for many and ſundry purpoſes, but ſpecially for things that were loſt, and for Horſes ſtollen or run aſtray. It helped alſo greatly to ſhorten a married mans life, if the Wife weary of her Husband would ſet a Candle before that Sword every Sunday, for the ſpace of one whole year, no Sunday excepted, for then all was in vain, whatſoever was done before.</p>
               <p>I have many times heard when I was a child, of divers ancient men and women, That this Sword was the Sword of a certain Thief which took Sanctuary in that Church-yard, and afterward through the negligence of the Watchmen eſcaped and left his Sword behind him, which being found and laid up in a certain old Cheſt, was afterward through the ſubtilty of the Parſon and the Clerk of the ſame Pariſh, made a precious Relique full of virtue, able to do much, but eſpecially to enrich the Box, and to make fat the Parſons pouch.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:56276:19"/>
               <p>I ſhall leave the Reader to weigh this Story,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and by putting both ends together, he may ſee there is no end of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> cheats, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples folly.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Thetford,</hi> a Town in <hi>Norfolk,</hi> there was a Pariſh-Church, which is now deſtroyed, called St. <hi>Audrice:</hi> In this Church, among other Reliques was the Smock of St. <hi>Audrice,</hi> which was there kept as a great jewel, and precious Relique. The virtue of this Smock was mighty and manifold, but eſpecially in putting away the Tooth-ach, and the ſwelling of the Throat; ſo that the Patient were firſt of all ſhriven, and heard Maſs, and did ſuch Oblations as the Prieſt of the Church enjoyned.</p>
               <p>All was governed by the Prieſt, and the Prieſt by his covetouſneſs,<note place="margin">Note.</note> of which there is no end.</p>
               <p>In the Monaſtry of St. <hi>Edmundsbury,</hi> beſides many other almoſt innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Reliques; there was one, a modeſt, ſingular, and precious Relique, called St. <hi>Edmunds</hi> Girdle: The virtue of this Relique was, That if any woman being with Child, came devoutly on Pilgrimage to ſweet St. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund,</hi> and were girded about with that holy Relique by ſome Monk, and ſo kneeling down before St. <hi>Edmund's</hi> ſhrine, ſaid certain <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> certain <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> and a Creed in the Worſhip of God, and of our Lady, and ſweet St. <hi>Edmund,</hi> and paid the accuſtomed offering, ſhe ſhould not periſh of that Child, but have good and lucky deliverance.</p>
               <p>This was an eaſie medicine, but like all the reſt, chargeable:<note place="margin">Note.</note> They wrought all their Miracles for money, by which it appears they were none of Chriſts Diſciples, who as they received freely, gave freely, but Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts merchandize was always of more coſt than value.</p>
               <p>In the ſame Monaſtry there was alſo another holy Relique, which was called the <hi>pardon bowl;</hi> whoſoever drunk of this Bowl in the Worſhip of God, and St. <hi>Edmund,</hi> he had 500 days of pardon, <hi>toties quoties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How ſome for cure, ſome for pardon,<note place="margin">Note.</note> all were made to bring Griſt to the Popes Mill.</p>
               <p>The Coat of St. <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt was ſo holy a Relique, and of ſo great virtue, that by touching thereof, ſuch as were diſeaſed, were cured; the ſick were made whole, the blind were reſtored to their ſight, the Lepers were cleanſed, and Devils were caſt out of men.</p>
               <p>Theſe are ſuch incredible Stories, that they need nothing to confute them,<note place="margin">Note.</note> but the ſerious reading and weighing them.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Geneva</hi> was a certain Relique, called St. <hi>Peters</hi> Brain, and was eſteemed for a precious treaſure among all the people of the Countrey, and had in great worſhip. But after that it pleaſed God to reveal the truth of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Word to the Inhabitants of the City, and the crafty juggling of the Papiſts began to be eſpied, and ſearch made, it was found to be not St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> Brain, but a Marble-ſtone.</p>
               <p>When people came to exerciſe their own brains,<note place="margin">Note.</note> they ſoon found the cheat, and ſo may men now.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Piſe,</hi> at <hi>Ravenna,</hi> at <hi>Clugny,</hi> at <hi>Angers,</hi> at St. <hi>Saeviours</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note. Theſe Pots are found in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers places, and none but they that are drunk with the Popes Wine, will believe it.</note> &amp;c. are the Cruſes or Water-pots which they call <hi>Hidries,</hi> wherein the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was that Jeſus Chriſt changed into Wine at the marriage of <hi>Cana</hi> in <hi>Galilee,</hi> and are taken for great Reliques.</p>
               <p>And as in the aforeſaid places they have the Cruſes, or Water-pots; ſo they of <hi>Orleans</hi> affirm and ſay, That they have among them at this preſent, part of the Wine which Chriſt miraculouſly turned from Water unto
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56276:20"/>Wine at the aforeſaid marriage, and kept it among them devoutly as an holy and worthy Relique. This cuſtom alſo have they among them: Once a year, ſo many as will religiouſly and devoutly come on Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage unto the aforeſaid Relique, and offer ſomething for the relief of our Mother-holy-Church, they ſhall not only ſee it, but alſo taſte of it, by licking the end of a Spoon, which is dipped into it. And they make the ſimple people believe, that it is part of the ſame Wine which Chriſt at the marriage of <hi>Cana</hi> in <hi>Galilee</hi> turned from Water into Wine. They add moreover, that the taſting of the Wine is not only profitable to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel all ſorrows and cares, and to make them the more merry and joyful all the year after, but alſo very medicinable againſt divers and ſundry diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes. And the virtue thereof is ſo great and marvellous, that although never ſo many taſte of it, yet the quantity thereof abideth always one, and diminiſheth nothing at all. Is not this a marvellous Relique!</p>
               <p>This is a thing which requireth great ſtore of Ignorance to make it go down;<note place="margin">Note.</note> and I hope the people of <hi>England</hi> will never be ſo drunk with the Wine of the Cup that the Whore of <hi>Rome</hi> fills out, as to believe any of the Wine Chriſt made by a Miracle, is to be licked in <hi>Spain</hi> from the end of a Spoon.</p>
               <p>The Knife wherewith the Paſchal Lamb was cut up at the Supper which Chriſt made with his Diſciples the night before he was crucified, is, as they ſay, at <hi>Trier,</hi> and there kept for a precious Jewel, with no ſmall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion and reverence.</p>
               <p>At how ſmall rates theſe <hi>Papiſts</hi> deceive the people!<note place="margin">Note.</note> here is a Knife for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth had in great reverence, becauſe the Lord uſed it at the Paſchal Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; but that the Good-man of the houſe where they eat, did not call for his Knives and other things, but that his Diſh and Knife was carried away by the Diſciples, is to make them thieves like Popiſh Prieſts in <hi>Spain:</hi> this is like the reſt of their lyes, and I hope will cut them to the heart.</p>
               <p>Part alſo of the Bread which was at that Supper, is to be ſeen at St. <hi>Sae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi>'s in <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is Bread of Sixteen hundred years old,<note place="margin">Note.</note> if they ſay true; but they are ſuch old lyers that there is no wiſe man will believe them.</p>
               <p>The Platter alſo wherein the Paſchal Lamb was put,<note place="margin">The Platter.</note> is found to be in divers places, as at <hi>Rome,</hi> at <hi>Geves,</hi> at <hi>Earles, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Platter it ſeemeth is in many places,<note place="margin">Note.</note> ſo that a wiſe man will judg it is not at all, except they can multiply Platter as they can do bodies of Chriſt, which they ſay may be in many places at the ſame time; much alike.</p>
               <p>The Cup wherein Chriſt gave the Sacrament of his blood to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to drink, is ſhewed at our Lady of the Iſle near to <hi>Lyons,</hi> and alſo at <hi>Allegeios</hi> in a certain Covent of <hi>Austin</hi>-Friers, and in both places kept as a moſt precious Relique. How this may be (good Reader) make no inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, except thou wilt repay unto them that lately have brought in the Doctrine of the Ubiquity of Chriſts body. But if they can perſwade thee that one and the ſame Cup, being a dead thing, may be in divers places at once, then maiſt thou the ſooner be brought to believe the ſtrange Doctrine of the Ubiquity of Chriſts body.</p>
               <p>That what is ſaid to the former Paragraph ſerves to undeceive the Reader in both.<note place="margin">Note.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Towel, Napkin or Cloth, wherewith Chriſt wiped his Apoſtles feet after that he had waſhed them, is not only at <hi>Rome</hi> in the <hi>Lateran</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:56276:20"/>Church, but alſo at <hi>Aix,</hi> and at St. <hi>Cornelius,</hi> with the ſign of <hi>Judas</hi> foot.</p>
               <p>The Traytor <hi>Judas</hi> betrayed Chriſt but once;<note place="margin">Note.</note> theſe Popiſh Prieſts make a Trade daily to betray Chriſt in his Perſon and Members into all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt imaginable, by their frauds and falſhoods.</p>
               <p>The very ſame bough that Jeſus held in his hand when he entred into <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> on <hi>Palm ſunday,</hi> is (as they ſay) at St. <hi>Saviours</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> and is taken for a great Relique.</p>
               <p>It is doubtful whether Chriſt had a bough or not,<note place="margin">Note.</note> for the holy Text is ſilent. But that this is a falſhood, is out of all doubt.</p>
               <p>The common opinion is, That Chriſt was faſtned to the Croſs only with three Nails, which Nails, how they were beſtowed, we have heretofore heard. Notwithſtanding it is found that there is one of thoſe Nails at <hi>Rome</hi> in St. <hi>Helens</hi> Church, another in the Church of the holy Croſs, another at <hi>Milan,</hi> another at <hi>Carpentras,</hi> another at <hi>Venice,</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> two, at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lein</hi> one at the <hi>three Maries,</hi> another at <hi>Triers,</hi> one in <hi>France</hi> at the holy Chappel of <hi>Paris,</hi> another at the <hi>Carmes,</hi> one alſo at St. <hi>Denis</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> one at <hi>Bruges,</hi> one at <hi>Tenail,</hi> one at <hi>Draquigne, &amp;c.</hi> And every one of theſe places perſwade themſelves to have one of thoſe three Nails where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Chriſt was faſtned to the Croſs, and count it for a precious Relique. But how this may be true, let the indifferent Reader judg. But who knoweth not that the Kingdom of the Papiſts is crowned, confirmed, and maintained with lyes and tyrannies?</p>
               <p>The Spear-head wherewith Chriſt was thruſt to the heart, is not only at <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo (as they report) at the holy Chappel of <hi>Paris,</hi> at the Abbey of <hi>Tenail,</hi> at St. <hi>Euge,</hi> at <hi>Selne,</hi> &amp;c. And in all theſe places it is counted to be a precious Relique: Alſo the very ſame Spear wherewith Chriſt was pierced unto the heart.</p>
               <p>That divers Thorns of Chriſts thorny Crown be at <hi>Rome,</hi> we have like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe before heard: But beſides thoſe there are other, yea and thoſe not few, at <hi>Venice</hi> one, at <hi>Bruges</hi> five, at <hi>Beſanſon</hi> in St. <hi>Johns</hi> Church three, at St. <hi>Saviours</hi> in <hi>Spain</hi> I cannot tell how many; at St. <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Galicia</hi> two, at <hi>Alby</hi> three, at <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> at <hi>Maſcove,</hi> at <hi>Charoure</hi> in <hi>Poictiers,</hi> at <hi>Clere,</hi> at St. <hi>Floure,</hi> at St. <hi>Maximine</hi> in <hi>Province,</hi> in the Abbey of <hi>Salle,</hi> in the Pariſh-Church of St. <hi>Martin</hi> at <hi>Noyon;</hi> in every one of theſe places there is at the leaſt one, and in many other places.</p>
               <p>The Purple Robe wherewith <hi>Pilate</hi> cloathed Chriſt in deriſion, for as much as he called himſelf a King, is at <hi>Rome,</hi> as we have heard. But as touching the Garment that was Woven from top to toe, without ſeam, whereon lots were caſt, it is found to be in divers places, one at <hi>Argentine,</hi> near <hi>Paris,</hi> another at <hi>Trier,</hi> &amp;c. And the <hi>Turk</hi> mocking the folly of the Chriſtians, ſaith plainly, That he hath this Garment in his hands.</p>
               <p>Reader, conſider well the five former Paragraphs,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and thou wilt ſee the Trade of cheating by the Prieſts, and how well content the people are to have it ſo, like them in the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah's</hi> time, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.31. and thou wilt ſee cauſe to thank God thou art delivered from the Error of the wicked Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Soldiers that crucified Chriſt plaid, as they ſay, at Dice for the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Coat of Chriſt, which Dice were three in number, and yet remain as precious Reliques: One of them, they ſay, is at <hi>Trier,</hi> and the other two at St. <hi>Saviours</hi> in <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:56276:21"/>
               <p>That they caſt Lots, the holy Text ſaith; but that they plaid at Dice, is one of their Fables: but what if it ſhall appear there was no Dice in thoſe days, will not they appear great lyars? But if perchance there was amongſt the Pagan Soldiers, muſt the Devils bones (as people call Dice) now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come holy Reliques? O horrid Impiety!</p>
               <p>The Cloth which was put upon Chriſts head when he was laid in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, is kept as an holy Relique at the <hi>Auguſtines</hi> of <hi>Carcoſſone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It's ſtrange this old Clout is not waſhed to rags in 1600 years,<note place="margin">Note.</note> or elſe it's but a foul one by this time: but where was this ſmall piece of Cloth kept before the Whore of <hi>Rome</hi> began to ſhow her tricks, which ſhe thought not of, or was aſhamed to do, till within theſe ſix or ſeven hundred years?</p>
               <p>Chriſts Winding-ſheet wherein he was wrapped, and laid in his grave, is found perfect and whole, (as they ſay) in divers places, as at <hi>Nice,</hi> at <hi>Aix,</hi> at <hi>Traicte,</hi> at <hi>Beſancon,</hi> at <hi>Eadoe</hi> in <hi>Limoſin,</hi> &amp;c. And in all theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces it is kept as a moſt precious Relique. But how one ſheet can be in ſo many places at once, muſt be learned of thoſe Maſters who teach the Ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of Chriſts natural body.</p>
               <p>If it were poſſible by their art of Tranſubſtantiation to make Chriſts perſon in many places,<note place="margin">Note.</note> yet this old ſheet ſure is not a fit ſubject of that Art.</p>
               <p>The Aſſes tail whereon Chriſt rode on <hi>Palm-ſunday,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note> is to be ſeen at <hi>Genes,</hi> and is there held for an holy Relique.</p>
               <p>What Aſſes are the poor people that have given up their ſenſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to their lying Prieſts, and are made to believe an Aſſes tail to be a holy Relique! and why muſt his tail be cut off? could they not as well have kept the Aſſe, as have been ſuch Aſſes themſelves as to think a man in his wits will believe ſuch a fiction?</p>
               <p>There is alſo in a certain Monaſtry kept for a Relique, a morſel of that broil'd fiſh which Chriſt preſented, and gave to St. <hi>Peter</hi> when he appeared unto him on the Sea-ſhore after his Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>How incredible things do theſe men fain!<note place="margin">Note.</note> but what good-luck have they, that they can keep fiſh ſo long after it's broiled? It's a wonder the Mice had not eat it in 1600 years time! it's ſtrange the <hi>Jews</hi> had not eat it in the time of the Siege of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when old ſhooes were good meat, if <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus</hi> ſpoke true!</p>
               <p>At <hi>Reines</hi> in <hi>Campania</hi> there is a Stone behind the high Altar, wherein (as they ſay) is the form of Chriſts Hips: This is taken for a great Relique al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and full devoutly kiſſed of many devout people. And they ſay this was done at ſuch time as our Lord became a Maſon to build their Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porch.</p>
               <p>This is ſuch a weak and ſenſeleſs Fiction,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that I can note in it nothing, but that the Inventors were notorious fools.</p>
               <p>Our Ladies Smock, beſides divers other places, is to be found (as they ſay) at <hi>Aix.</hi> And this is the order when it is ſhewed. One holdeth it out upon the end of a pole, as it were a long white Surplice of a Prieſt. This Smock is ſo long and large, that if <hi>Mary</hi> had been a Giant, yet could ſhe ſcarcely have worn ſuch a monſtrous Smock. And for to make a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhew thereof, one doth carry ſtraightway after a Hoſe of St. <hi>Joſeph</hi> her Husband, yea and that ſo little, and ſo ſlender a Hoſe, that it may ſeem little enough fora Dwarf to wear, and ſuch a one as they ſay <hi>Tom Thumb</hi> was.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:56276:21"/>
               <p>The ſtories of <hi>Thomas Thumb</hi> and <hi>Don Quixot</hi> ſure would be Canonical with the people which believe ſuch things as theſe,<note place="margin">Note.</note> if the Popes Holineſs would declare them ſo.</p>
               <p>Of our Ladies Kerchers, two yet remain and are preſerved as moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Reliques: one at <hi>Trier</hi> in St. <hi>Maximins</hi> Abby; another at <hi>Lilio</hi> in <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That a woman of ſo great vertue, and worthy of ſo much honour,<note place="margin">Note.</note> ſhould be ſo diſgraced as to have her Smock and other parts of her old Napery thus expoſed when Sixteen hundred years old, is certainly a great ſhame.</p>
               <p>The Girdle of our Lady is at <hi>Prat,</hi> and kept as a holy Relique.</p>
               <p>One of our Ladies Slippers is at St. <hi>Jaqueries,</hi> and one of her Shooes at St. <hi>Floures,</hi> and are taken for great and ſolemn Reliques.</p>
               <p>That ſhe might wear a Girdle, is credible; but that ſhe wore Shooes,<note place="margin">Note.</note> I doubt, becauſe there was none but Sandals worn in that Country; but I am glad ſhe was ſo well furniſhed to have Shooes and Slippers both; but how ridiculous ſuch ſtories are I leave you Reader to judg.</p>
               <p>Two of our Ladies Wedding-ring is alſo kept as a precious Relique and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Jewel at <hi>Peruſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Divers of our Ladies Gowns are to be found in divers places, as at <hi>Rome</hi> in St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Lateran.</hi> In St. <hi>Barbara</hi>'s Church. In St. <hi>Maries</hi> upon <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerve.</hi> In St. <hi>Blaſes</hi> Church. At St. <hi>Saviours</hi> in <hi>Spain.</hi> At the leaſt they ſay they have certain pieces of her Gowns, and keep them devoutly as holy Reliques.</p>
               <p>The Slippers of St. <hi>Joſeph</hi> our Ladies Husband are in St. <hi>Simons</hi> Abby of <hi>Trier,</hi> and are had in great reverence and honour. Of his Hoſe we have heretofore heard.</p>
               <p>Reader,<note place="margin">Note.</note> conſider what vain people theſe are which always keep minds exerciſed about ſuch toys and old rags as theſe: as for a Wedding-ring ſhe never had any, nor was it the cuſtom in thoſe days to have Wedding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Carcaſſone</hi> the Papiſts boaſt to have certain Reliques of St. <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel, and likewiſe at St. <hi>Julians</hi> of <hi>Toures.</hi> They do ſhew at great St. <hi>Michaels</hi> (which is ſo well haunted of Pilgrims) his Sword which is like a Childs Dagger, and his Buckler likewiſe which is as it were the boſs of a Horſe-bit.</p>
               <p>That Angels ſhould have Swords and Shields, is ſo vain,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that all the wit the Pope and Clergy of <hi>Rome</hi> have, can never defend themſelves from the imputation of being moſt horrid Impoſtors in aſſerting; but that the Sword ſhould be like a Childs Dagger, and the Shield or Buckler like the boſs of a horſe-bit, none but knaves will ſay, and none but fools will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it.</p>
               <p>Although we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> before that the head of St. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> is in divers places, yet they <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Amiens</hi> boaſt to have the viſage of St. <hi>John.</hi> And in the Mask which they ſhew, there is the ſign of the cut of a kniſe over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwart the eye, which they ſay <hi>Herodias</hi> gave him. But they of St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Angel</hi> deny it, and ſhew the like part. As concerning the reſt of the Head from the crown to the forehead, it was at <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and is now at <hi>Malta,</hi> as it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56276:22"/>is thought; at the leaſt they have made men believe that the <hi>Turk</hi> did render it them. The hinder part is at St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Nemoures.</hi> The Brain is at <hi>Noyon.</hi> Beſides all this, they of St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Morein</hi> do not want ſome certain part of the Head. His Jawes are ſeen at <hi>Beſanſon</hi> at St. <hi>John</hi> the great. There is another part at St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Latians</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> and at St. <hi>Floura</hi> in <hi>Auvergne.</hi> They keep his Hair at St. <hi>Saviours</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> the Brow and ſome of the Hair. There is alſo a little thereof at <hi>Noyon,</hi> which is ſhewn very authentickly. There is alſo ſome part (I know not of what place) at St. <hi>Lukes.</hi> As for St. <hi>John Baptiſts</hi> Arm, they of <hi>Sene</hi> boaſt to have it, which is repugnant to all ancient Hiſtories. Now as touching that finger wherewith St. <hi>John</hi> did point and ſhew our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>Ecce Agnus ille Dei,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Behold that Lamb of God that taketh away the ſin of the world,</hi> it is found to be in many and divers places. There is one at <hi>Beſanſon</hi> in the Church of St. <hi>John</hi> the great, another at <hi>Lions,</hi> another at <hi>Bruges,</hi> another at <hi>Florence,</hi> another at St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Adventures</hi> near to <hi>Maſcone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One of St. <hi>John</hi>'s Shoos is at the Charter-houſe of <hi>Pa is.</hi> His Jacket is at <hi>Rome</hi> in the Church of St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Lateran;</hi> where alſo, as they ſay, is the Altar whereon he prayed in the deſert: As if in thoſe days they uſed to make Altars for every purpoſe, and in every place! It is a marvel that they make not the people believe alſo that he ſung Maſs!</p>
               <p>In <hi>Avignon</hi> is the Sword wherewith he was beheaded. At <hi>Aix</hi> is the Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Cloth that was ſpread under him when he was beheaded.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Poicters</hi> they have the Jaw-bone and beard of St. <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At <hi>Trier</hi> there are divers bones both of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At <hi>Argenton</hi> in <hi>Bury,</hi> one of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Shoulders.</p>
               <p>At St. <hi>Saviours</hi> in <hi>Spain</hi> one of St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Slippers: They of <hi>Poicters</hi> alſo brag that they have St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Slippers, but thoſe are wonderful trim and brave, made of Satin, and broidered with Gold, as though he had been like to our Popiſh Biſhops when they are dreſſed and decked like Puppets in their Pontificalibus. When it is well known that <hi>Peter</hi> lived a very poor man, as it evidently appeareth by theſe words which he ſpake to a certain man that was lame from his mothers womb, <hi>Silver and gold</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>have I none, ſuch as I have I give thee; in the name of Jeſus Chriſt of Nazareth riſe up and walk.</hi> And are not theſe the words of St. <hi>James, Hath not God choſen the poor of this world?</hi> Saith not St. <hi>Paul</hi> of himſelf and of his fellow Apoſtles in this wiſe, <hi>Even unto this time we hunger and thirst, and are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and are buffeted with fiſts, and have no certain dwelling place, and labour, working with our own hands?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Paragraph ſhews that their Reliques are of their own invention by the gayneſs of them,<note place="margin">Note.</note> which agrees not at all with the poor eſtate of the holy men they talk of.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Pontifical Chair with his Cope wherein he ſaid Maſs (as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> fain) are at <hi>Rome,</hi> and kept as precious Reliques.</p>
               <p>About the Altar whereon he ſaid Maſs, there is great contention; they of <hi>Rome</hi> affirm that they have it, and they of <hi>Piſe</hi> likewiſe ſay they have it. But how the lying <hi>Papists</hi> ſtrive among themſelves for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ye, who knoweth not? ſeeing that neither that monſter the Maſs, nor ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>tars were receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Church of Chriſt many years after the death of St. <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this they pretend to juſtifie their own fooliſh Gayeties,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and therein be-lye the Primitive modeſty and plainneſs of the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               <p>The Sword alſo wherewith St. <hi>Peter</hi> cut off <hi>Malchus</hi> his ear, is reſerved
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56276:22"/>and reverenced of the <hi>Papists</hi> in divers and ſundry places.</p>
               <p>The having one Sword in ſo many places,<note place="margin">Note.</note> is a reaſonable ground to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude they have it no where.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Peter</hi>'s Croſier is ſhewed at St. <hi>Stephens</hi> of <hi>Grees</hi> at <hi>Paris:</hi> But they of <hi>Collen</hi> plainly affirm that they have it: So likewiſe ſay they of <hi>Trier.</hi> But it is truly to be thought that none of them all have it; for in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s time there were no ſuch baubles as the Popiſh Biſhops uſe now-a-days, neither Miter nor Croſier, Cope nor Veſtment, Altar nor Altar-cloth.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Bartholomew</hi>'s skin is at <hi>Piſa,</hi> and there kept for an holy and precious Relique, notwithſtanding in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> they plainly affirm that they have the whole Body of St. <hi>Bartholomew</hi> with skin and all. And in St. <hi>Bartholomew</hi>'s Church at <hi>Rome</hi> they ſtoutly maintain that he is there both body and skin, and in no other place.</p>
               <p>Poor St. <hi>Bartholomew</hi> is at <hi>Piſa,</hi> and at <hi>Rome</hi> too; what place next? an Arm with the <hi>Walloon</hi> Jeſuits at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and five Ribs at <hi>Leige</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> and a Leg at <hi>Burgos,</hi> and an Head at <hi>Villa Garſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Mathias</hi> hath one Body at <hi>Padua,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note, here is a bleſſed in creaſe of St. <hi>Mathias.</hi>
                  </note> another at <hi>Rome</hi> in the Church of St. <hi>Mary</hi> the greater, and a third Body at <hi>Trier.</hi> Beſides this, he hath a Head and an Arm at <hi>Rome,</hi> and another Body at <hi>Salamanca</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> and another at the Cathedral at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> and another where Mr. <hi>Pope</hi> pleaſeth: Nay he hath any thing but Truth and true Religion; but theſe have left <hi>Rome</hi> long ſince.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Ortone</hi> the Body of Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> the Apoſtle is kept and taken for an holy Relique, notwithſtanding they of <hi>Trier</hi> ſay they have cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of his Bones, and at <hi>Rome</hi> they boaſt to have his Arm and Head.</p>
               <p>The Chalice out of which St. <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt drank the Poyſon, being condemned by <hi>Domitian</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperour, is found in two places, and taken for a great Relique: One is at <hi>Rome</hi> in the Church of St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Lateran,</hi> and the other at <hi>Bullen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At our Lady of the Iſle near <hi>Lions</hi> are kept for precious Reliques the twelve Combs of the twelve Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Anne</hi> Mother of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> hath one of her Bodies at <hi>Apte</hi> in <hi>Provence,</hi> the other at our Lady of the Iſle, at <hi>Lyons.</hi> Beſides this, ſhe hath one Head at <hi>Trier,</hi> the other at <hi>Turen,</hi> another at <hi>Turinge</hi> a Town named after her name. I omit the pieces of her Body which are in more than a hundred places, as an arm in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church at <hi>Rome, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:56276:23"/>
               <p>When they are agreed amongſt themſelves,<note place="margin">Note.</note> it will be time enough to believe them, of the ſtory of the twelve Combs and Cups, Bodies and bones, they talk of in theſe four laſt Paragraphs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lazarus</hi> the Brother of <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> hath three Bodies, one at <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> the other at <hi>Authum,</hi> the third at <hi>Avalon.</hi> Every one of theſe places boaſt that they have the true Body of <hi>Lazarus.</hi> But how this may be, no man may demand, except he will be taken for a <hi>Lutheran.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> is known to have two Bodies,<note place="margin">Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen<hi>'s</hi> Noli me tangere, <hi>hath great Veneration in the</hi> Romiſh <hi>Church.</hi>
                  </note> one at <hi>Veſelnere Auſerre;</hi> the other, which is of greater renown, at St. <hi>Maximius</hi> in <hi>Provence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, ſhe hath divers parts of her Body in divers places, as her head, with her <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> her bones, her hair, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With what face can theſe people look men in the face,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and boaſt of unity of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when they cannot agree about a few bones and old invented Reliques, about which they prove themſelves lyars, and under the curſe of believing lyes? But as for the <hi>Noli me tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere</hi> of <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> I ſuppoſe the Prieſts have a great devotion, and the people kiſs it with as much.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Longus</hi> the Knight who pierced the ſide of our Lord Jeſus on the Croſs with a Spear, hath two Bodies in two ſundry places, the one is at <hi>Mantone,</hi> the other at our Lady of the Iſle, near <hi>Lyons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truly I ſhould be as well contented if he had had two and twenty.</p>
               <p>The Bodies of the three Kings which came to worſhip the new-born Saviour of the World, whom the <hi>Papists</hi> have baptiſed with theſe names, <hi>Balthaſar, Melchior,</hi> and <hi>Gaſpar,</hi> are conſtantly affirmed of many to be at <hi>Colen;</hi> but they of <hi>Millain</hi> ſay plainly that they have theſe Bodies of the three Kings; ſo that whoſoever will worſhip them, they muſt come unto <hi>Millain</hi> and offer there unto them, or elſe all their labour is loſt. About this matter there hath been great contention in times paſt, inſomuch that it was brought before the Apoſtolique See to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</p>
               <p>And could not the Pope by his art perſwade the fools they are in both places?<note place="margin">Note.</note> and if I am not miſinformed, they are in the great Church in <hi>Portugal</hi> alſo. And they pretend to have the Bodies of one of thoſe three Kings at <hi>Palencia,</hi> and another at <hi>Toledo</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Denis,</hi> whom ſome take to be one of the Apoſtles Diſciples, and the firſt Preacher of the Goſpel in <hi>France,</hi> hath two Bodies in two ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56276:23"/>places: one is at St. <hi>Denis</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> the other at <hi>Regensburg</hi> in <hi>Germany.</hi> About this matter alſo there hath been no ſmall ado who have the true body of St. <hi>Denis,</hi> inſomuch that the Apoſtolique See was fain to give judgment therein. And yet both of them perſiſt in their fancy.</p>
               <p>And well they may perſiſt, for it is but a fancy,<note place="margin">Note.</note> like all the trinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets we have heard of in this whole Inventory of their Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize.</p>
               <p>The Body of St. <hi>Stephen</hi> is reported to be whole in his Church at <hi>Rome.</hi> Notwithſtanding his Head is affirmed to be in <hi>Arles;</hi> and his Bones are in more than 200 places.</p>
               <p>Thus do theſe fools prove themſelves Knaves and Lyers;<note place="margin">Note.</note> and would not <hi>England</hi> be bleſt to entertain ſuch a ſort of Religion and Religious men?</p>
               <p>The Stones alſo wherewith St. <hi>Stephen</hi> is reported to be ſtoned to death, are kept as Reliques at <hi>Florence;</hi> again in <hi>Arles</hi> at the <hi>Auguſtines,</hi> and at <hi>Vigan</hi> in <hi>Languedock.</hi> There is alſo at <hi>Poictiers</hi> one of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Stones, which, as they ſay, if it be aptly applied to a certain part of a Woman that is big with Child, is very profitable unto the ſafe deliverance of the Child, to the haſty expedition of the Birth, and eaſing of pain.</p>
               <p>Would it not be well to find out who gathered theſe ſtones toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and kept them till the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> began to ſhow ſuch tricks, and invent this Trade, cheating her followers.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> hath four whole bodies, in four ſundry places, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one is at <hi>Rome</hi> in St. <hi>Laurences</hi> Church, the other at <hi>Soiſon,</hi> the third at <hi>Pilligne,</hi> near <hi>Nantes,</hi> the fourth near <hi>Narbon,</hi> in the place where he was born; beſides this, he hath two heads, the one at St. <hi>Peters</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> the other at the <hi>Jacobins</hi> of <hi>Tholouſe.</hi> But all theſe are but empty skulls, if it be true what is reported; for the <hi>Gray-friers</hi> of <hi>Angers</hi> affirm, that whoſoever have St. <hi>Sebaſtians</hi> head, they have all his brains, which they keep for holy and precious Reliques. <hi>Item,</hi> the <hi>Jacobins</hi> of <hi>Angiers</hi> have an Arm of his, and they of St. <hi>Servine</hi> of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> have another. Another alſo of his Arms (if one man may have ſo many Arms) is at <hi>Avergne,</hi> and another at <hi>Mombriſon</hi> in the foreſt, beſides the ſmall little pieces that are in many other Churches.</p>
               <p>This Story, if well obſerved, doth ſo fully confute it ſelf,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that one half blind may perceive it. And what is the reaſon that they at <hi>Lisbon,</hi> who do one day every year go down to the Water-ſide to look for him, do not rather go to theſe places to meet him?</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:56276:24"/>
               <p>The Arrows alſo wherewith St. <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> was ſhot, are preſerved and kept for Reliques; whereof one is at <hi>Lambeſt</hi> in <hi>Provence,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other at <hi>Poictiers</hi> at the <hi>Auguſtines,</hi> and the reſt are here and there.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>David Rivers,</hi> when he kept a Cooks Shop in <hi>Nortonfall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Plow,</hi> there lodged two <hi>French</hi>-men at his houſe, which were (as they ſaid) <hi>Pilgrims,</hi> and had been at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Among ſeveral other diſcourſes, ſaid Mr. <hi>Rivers,</hi> you could not chuſe but be expoſed to great want, in ſo long a Journey.</p>
               <p>No, ſaid one of the Pilgrims (the other ſtanding by) we did ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom want long, for by one means or other we were ſoon ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied.</p>
               <p>But we were once in a very great ſtrait, night coming on, and we having neither food, nor money, but only a few odd things that might yield ſome ſmall matter; So we entred into an houſe, required Lodging; which being granted, we demanded of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, if ſhe had any thing to eat? No indeed, replyed the Woman, I have nothing in the houſe but Bread, that is fit for this day (it being then a Fiſh-day); but had it happened on another day, I could have furniſhed you with a good Rib of Bacon: bring us that, ſaid we, we are holy Men, and can make it Fiſh. It being brought, we prayed over it; and then pronounced it was no more Fleſh, but Fiſh. And after it was boyled, and we well ſupped thereon, we ſoon found an invention for to make profit of the Bone, to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount the price of our Meat and Lodging. So to work went we with our Knives; and after two hours we had ſcraped it ſo exactly, that it appeared to have lain long in the ground.</p>
               <p>We gave the Woman the Bone, with great charge to lay it up very ſafe, which ſhe did: In the morning we demanded the Bone, and gave her the things which we had brought with us, to lay up until we went a little way, and we would ſoon return. So walking about three or four Miles, we came to an Abbey, and having found the Abbot, we told him our buſineſs; how that we were Pilgrims, and had been to viſit the holy Land; and in our Pilgrimage, in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre of our bleſſed St. <hi>Anthony</hi> we had found a wonderful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique of his, even one of his Ribs. And having ſpecial love and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to that Abbey, more than to any other, were willing to beſtow it upon the ſame.</p>
               <p>The which was received with great joy and thankfulneſs, and we honourably treated. And he forthwith ſummoned all the people in the adjacent parts, to the Abbey; where being met, and the aforeſaid Bone being ſet on the Table, in a Silver Charger, the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56276:24"/>ſaid, Here lyeth the Bone of our bleſſed St. <hi>Anthony;</hi> therefore let no Adulterer, Thief, Drunkard, or other profane perſon, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to come within ſix foot of the Table, to offer their offering; and the very woman that ſold them the Bacon, did offer among the reſt.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> whom the Papiſts feign to be a cholerick and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Saint, burning whomſoever he is angry with, is found to have two bodies; one at <hi>Arles,</hi> the other at <hi>Venice</hi> among the <hi>Antheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> There is a Knee of him alſo at the <hi>Auguſtines</hi> of <hi>Albi.</hi> There are alſo at <hi>Burge,</hi> at <hi>Maſcon,</hi> at <hi>Dion,</hi> at <hi>Chalouſe,</hi> at <hi>Ourour,</hi> at <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſancon,</hi> &amp;c. divers Reliques of divers Members of St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> to ſay nothing of that Baggage which Pardoners carry about them from Countrey to Countrey to deceive the people withal, which is no ſmall quantity.</p>
               <p>Here I cannot omit to affix a Story which I received from an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man,<note place="margin">Note.</note> whom I dare credit, and is alive to atteſt the Truth of it as he heard it.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Patronel,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Parnel,</hi> the Daughter of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> hath alſo two bodies, one at <hi>Rome</hi> in her Fathers Church, and another at <hi>Mans</hi> in the <hi>Jacobin Covent.</hi> This latter body is had in great Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and is ſought far and near of all ſuch as are diſeaſed of Agues. Beſides theſe two bodies, there are found in other places many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of hers, which are full Religiouſly kept, and taken for things of great virtue.</p>
               <p>Are not the words of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.9, 10, 11. <hi>verſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note> fulfilled in theſe Merchants of <hi>Rome?</hi> And are not their followers given up to believe lyes, with whom ſuch cheats are in credit?</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Suſan</hi> likewiſe hath two bodies, one at <hi>Rome,</hi> and another at <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſe;</hi> and both are affirmed to be her true body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod, whereof we ſpoke before,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Arons</hi> Rod gain the thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> time.</note> is found to be not only at <hi>Rome</hi> in the <hi>Lateran</hi> Church, with the Ark of the Covenant, but alſo at the holy Chappel of <hi>Paris.</hi> And they of St. <hi>Saviours</hi> in <hi>Spain</hi> affirm, That they alſo have a certain piece of the Rod. Moreover, they of <hi>Burdeaux</hi> ſay, That the Rod which is ſhewn there in St. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verines</hi> Church, is the very ſelf-ſame Rod that <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> had in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and was turned into a Serpent.</p>
               <p>Sure theſe men are taught by the old Serpent that deceived <hi>Eve,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note> and are in love with all forbidden fruit.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Moor</hi> writeth, that while <hi>Rhodes</hi> was in the hands of the Chriſtians, which is now in the poſſeſſion of the <hi>Turk,</hi> there was in that City a great and precious Relique, which was one of the Thorns
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56276:25"/>in Chriſts Crown. This Thorn, ſaith he, upon <hi>Good-friday</hi> every year for theſe two hundred years, hath been ſeen in the ſervice-time to bud and bring forth flowers.</p>
               <p>Though we have had a good burden of theſe Thorns already,<note place="margin">Note.</note> yet none like this which brought forth flowers, which when the <hi>Turk</hi> ſays it, we may think it worth the while to go ſee it. But though he be a misbeliever, he is not ſuch a lyar as theſe Popiſh Prieſts, and therefore till he ſay it, we may ſuſpend our Journey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in his Colloquies ſaith, That when he was at <hi>Canterbury</hi> he ſaw in the Church dedicated to <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> a certain Altar dedicate to our Lady, where the ſaid <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaid his laſt Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night to her when he ſhould depart hence. In that Altar, ſaith he, is the point of the Sword that ſtirred about the brains of this bleſſed Martyr, and there lye his Brains ſhed upon the earth, whereby ye may well know that he was never dead.</p>
               <p>Not far from thence, ſaith he, we ſaw the Brain-pan of that holy Martyr, which was thruſt quite through, all the other was cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſilver, except the upper part, which was bare to be kiſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There hang alſo the ſhirt of hair and his girdle, with his hairy breeches wherewith the noble Champion chaſtened his body.</p>
               <p>From thence we returned into the Quire, on the North-ſide where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were the Reliques.</p>
               <p>A wondrous thing it was to ſee what a ſort of bones were brought forth, Skulls, Jaws, Teeth, Hands, Fingers, whole Arms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was alſo brought forth an Arm which had yet the red fleſh upon it.</p>
               <p>Alſo a Napkin full of ſweat, and bloody, wherewith St. <hi>Thomas</hi> wiped both his noſe and face.</p>
               <p>From thence (ſaith he) we were led to greater things. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the high Altar we aſcended as it were into another new Church; there was ſhewed us in a Chappel the face of that bleſſed man gilded over, and garniſhed with many precious ſtones.</p>
               <p>At laſt we were brought back again into the Veſtry, where was taken out a Coffer covered with black leather, which being ſet down upon the Table and opened, every body kneeled down and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped. In this Coffer were certain rags of linnen Cloth, many ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving yet remaining in them the token of the filth of the holy mans
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56276:25"/>noſe. With theſe, as they, ſay St. <hi>Thomas</hi> did wipe away the ſweat of his face and neck, the filth of his noſe, or other filthineſs wherewith mans body doth abound.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Herbert-Down</hi> there was an old ſhooe of <hi>Thomas Becket</hi> bound about with an Iron-hoop, wherein was a glaſs like a precious ſtone. This ſhooe the poor Brothers of the ſame Houſe were wont to offer to be kiſſed by ſuch as came that way, as a moſt holy and precious Relique.</p>
               <p>At St. <hi>John</hi>'s in <hi>Canterbury, Becket</hi>'s Comb was kept, kiſſed and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped as an holy and honourable Relique.</p>
               <p>And have not we cauſe to love and praiſe God that we are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from ſuch frauds?<note place="margin">Note.</note> Would it not be a dreadful judgment upon this Nation that it ſhould again be given up to ſuch blindneſs, and have ſuch Villains to lead us, as theſe Popiſh Prieſts are? the Lord Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty deliver Prince and People from them, and make their folly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to all men.</p>
               <p>At St. <hi>Stephens,</hi> a mile from <hi>Canterbury,</hi> was the Boot of St. <hi>Stephen</hi> kept for a precious Relique.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:56276:26"/>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:56276:26"/>
               <head>The Reliques that follow are taken out of an old written Book yet remaining in the Cathedral Church of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> This Book is called, <hi>Memorale multorum Henrici Prioris.</hi> And it may appear by the account to be <hi>262</hi> years ſince it was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and left for a perpetual remembrance of ſuch things as at that time appertained unto the Monaſtery commonly called, <hi>Chriſt's Church,</hi> being then a place of <hi>Monks,</hi> now, through the beneſit and liberality of the moſt noble King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, a moſt worthy Cathedral Church, and Place of Godly and Learned Prebendaries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Firſt the Body of <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> Biſhop of the ſaid Church, which was firſt buried in the Undercraſt, and afterward tranſlated into the upper part of the Church on the Eaſt ſide, and there lay in a Coffin of pure Gold, as a moſt holy and precious Relique.</p>
               <l>The Body of St. <hi>Alphege</hi> which was put into a Coffin of Silver, and gilt.</l>
               <l>The Body of St. <hi>Dunſtan</hi> in a Coffin of Copper and gilt.</l>
               <l>The Body of St. <hi>Odo</hi> in a Cheſt of Wood gilded.</l>
               <l>The Body of St. <hi>Wilfrid</hi> in a Coffin of Copper gilded.</l>
               <l>The Body of St. <hi>Anſelme</hi> in a Coffin of Wood gilded.</l>
               <l>The Body of St. <hi>Elphrick</hi> in a Coffin of Wood gilded.</l>
               <l>The Body of St. <hi>Blaſe</hi> in a Cheſt of Wood gilded.</l>
               <l>The Body of St. <hi>Andoen</hi> in a Coffin of Silver and gilt.</l>
               <l>The Body of St. <hi>Salvin</hi> in a Coffin of Wood gilded.</l>
               <l>The Bodies of St. <hi>Wulgan</hi> and St. <hi>Swithune.</hi>
               </l>
               <p>The Head of St. <hi>Blaſe:</hi> The Head of St. <hi>Furſey:</hi> The Head of St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrobert;</hi> theſe were framed of Caſes made of Silver, and gilt enamell'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> two Arms of old St. <hi>Simeon</hi> wherewith he embraced Chriſt in the <hi>Temple,</hi> as we read in the Goſpel of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>Nune dimittis ſervum tuum domine,</hi> &amp;c. We have heard before that one of his Arms was given to <hi>Carolus Magnus,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> for the good ſervice he did to Mother Holy Church: Whether that Arm were one of theſe two Arms that were at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or whether the third Arm was begotten ſince that time or not, I know not; for, in the Art of Multiplying, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> for lucres ſake are very wiſe and expert.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> the Arms of St. <hi>Blaſe,</hi> St. <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> St. <hi>George</hi> St. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, St. <hi>Richard,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> of St. <hi>Roman, Gregory</hi> the Pope, St. <hi>Hugh,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> St. <hi>Mildrith</hi> the Virgin, and of St. <hi>Edburg:</hi> All theſe, as Holy Reliques, were covered over with Caſes of Silver, and gilt ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell'd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> a Piece of Chriſt's Croſs:<note place="margin">More of the Croſs ſtill.</note> A Fragment of the Cradle wherein Chriſt was rocked: A Parcel of the Maunger wherein Chriſt was laid after he was born: A Piece of the Sepulchre wherein Chriſt was buried: A Remnant of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Rod which was turned into a Serpent: Chriſt's uſual Napkin wherewith he wiped his Face.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:56276:27"/>
               <p>To ſay no more of the Croſs,<note place="margin">Note.</note> which hath afforded a good Cart-load all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, let us obſerve their Foolery about his Cradle, and Maunger, and Sepulchre, which was of Stone, all which it ſeemeth lay dormant till An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt did awake to deceive the Nations, which was not till 800 years, and is it not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they should tell us who kept all the ſo bits of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, before we believe the reallity there of.</p>
               <p>In a great Croſs of Gold given by <hi>Stephen</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> with a Ruby on the top, and two Emeralds on the ſides, were theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques contained.</p>
               <p>In the midſt of the Croſs there was a piece of the Croſs that Chriſt dyed on;<note place="margin">More of the Croſs yet.</note> a Bone of St. <hi>Benigne,</hi> a Tooth of St. <hi>Bleſe,</hi> a Bone of St. <hi>Julian,</hi> a piece of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Staff, certain Reliques of St. <hi>Quintin,</hi> St. <hi>Mark,</hi> and <hi>Marcellian; Item,</hi> a Bone of the man of God; alſo a Bone of St. <hi>Stephen</hi> the Pope.</p>
               <p>How were thoſe poor people pulled in pleces by theſe Popiſh Villains,<note place="margin">Note.</note> if what they ſay were true; but the things are ſo groſs, yea ſo impoſſible, that we will rather put them down for Lyars, than ſuppoſe the people were thus born Limb from Limb by the Primitive Profeſſors of the Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
               <p>In the Croſs of St. <hi>Andrea,</hi> being of silver, and gilt, ſet with divers goodly and precious Stones, were theſe two Reliques: Firſt, a piece of St. <hi>Andrent</hi>'s Croſs: Secondly one of his Bones.</p>
               <p>In a Croſs of Silver, and gilt, ſet with divers goodly and precions ſtones, was this one Relique, <hi>viz.</hi> a piece of the Holy Croſs.</p>
               <p>In the Croſs of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> which was of Silver and gilt, was this one Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, that is to ſay, a piece of the Croſs that St. <hi>Peter</hi> dyed on.</p>
               <p>In a Croſs of Silver, gilt on the one ſide and not on the other, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained theſe Reliques following.</p>
               <p>Firſt, a piece of the Holy Croſs; a good gobbet of Chriſt's Sepulchre; certain Bones of St. <hi>James;</hi> of St. <hi>Oſuha;</hi> of St. <hi>Andrem,</hi> of St. <hi>Paneras;</hi> of St. <hi>Brigide;</hi> and of St. <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a little Croſs of Silver, and gilt, without any precious ſtones, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Image of a Lamb on the back-ſide, was this one Relique, <hi>viz.</hi> a piece of Chriſt's Croſs.</p>
               <p>What Fictions are here about the Croſs, and what abundance do we meet with,<note place="margin">Note.</note> is worth noteing.</p>
               <p>In a Glaſs of Chryſtal was this one Relique contained,<note place="margin">The Thorns of Chriſt's Crown ſure were many. <hi>Aron</hi>'s Rod again.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> one of the Thorns of Chriſt's Crown.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> In a great Aumbry or Cupboard were theſe Reliques found; <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Rod; a piece of the Coffin that our Lady was buried in; the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altare of St. <hi>Elphege; Item,</hi> a Chalice of St. <hi>Elphege,</hi> made of Cryſtal, gilt and enar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>led, with a paten of Mother Pearl.</p>
               <p>The people have no other ground to believe theſe things to be ſuch,<note place="margin">Note.</note> but that the falſe Prieſt tells them ſo.</p>
               <p>In a certain great Cheſt of Cryſtal, ſet in ſilver, and gilt and garniſhed with many goodly precious ſtones, were theſe two Reliques; firſt our Ladies Hair; ſecondly a piece of hee Vail.</p>
               <p>It's impoſſible that a little Hair,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and a piece of her Vail, ſhould laft, and not be rotten, or loſt, in thoſe 1000 years that paſſed before the <hi>Papiſts</hi> began to make ſuch ſhow.</p>
               <p>In a Coffer of Copper, and gilt, was the Blood of St. <hi>Edmund,</hi> King and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56276:27"/>Martyr, a piece of his Shirt, a remnant of his Breeches, and a fragment of his Cuſhion.</p>
               <p>The ground of their Faith in theſe things is the bare word of their Prieſts;<note place="margin">Note.</note> why may not theſe bits be old Clouts gathered off a Dunghill, and the Blood might be the Blood of a ſheep as well as of St. <hi>Edmund,</hi> but they are bound to believe what the Prieſts ſay, right or wrong.</p>
               <p>In a Cheſt of ſilver, and gilt, with a round Cryſtal, and a Vine graven thereon, were theſe Reliques contained; the bones of St. <hi>Laurence,</hi> and a piece of his Gridiron whereon he was broyled.</p>
               <p>In another Cheſt of ſilver, and gilt, and adorned with precious ſtones, was the Hair and the Girdle of St. <hi>Laurence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſome places they have St. <hi>Laurence</hi>'s whole body, here is but a piece, and a piece of his Gridiron: I have ſeen a whole one, in ſeveral places: The Hair of St. <hi>Laurence</hi> was roſted; but that may be, for, if the Whore lies not, there was an Angel that held his Head whileſt he was roaſting, and ſo did preſerve his Hair.</p>
               <p>In a Cheſt of ſilver, and gilt, ſet with precious ſtones and a long Cryſtal, were contained a Tooth and a Bone of St. <hi>Bennet</hi> the <hi>Monk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>St. Bennet</hi>'s Tooth an excellent Relique, and a Bone which is as good as the other; I pray how many Devils have theſe rotten Reliques caſt out?</p>
               <p>In a Coffin of ſilver, and gilt, garniſhed with divers, precious ſtones, were a Tooth and a Finger of <hi>St. Stephen;</hi> alſo divers of his Bones; <hi>Item,</hi> certain of the ſtones where with he was ſtoned unto death: alſo part of his Blood.</p>
               <p>I have ſeen as many of <hi>St. Stephen</hi>'s Teeth as would fill a Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k,<note place="margin">St. <hi>Stephen</hi> I believe was never trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with the Tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach, for he ſaved all his Teeth for Reliques.</note> and as great a quantity of his blood; I ſuppoſe ſong Angel ſaved that: Theſe are admirable Reliques, but the Vertue of the ſtones I cannot as yet learn.</p>
               <p>In a Cheſt of Copper, gilt, without precious ſtones, with a long round Cryſtal were theſe Reliques contained; part of <hi>St. John</hi> Baptiſt's head, and one of his bones; <hi>Item,</hi> a bone of <hi>St. Blaſe,</hi> a bone of <hi>St. Pantaleon,</hi> and a bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap> of St. <hi>Menna</hi> the Martyr.</p>
               <p>We found a whole head in one Church, and now poor St. <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt hath but a piece of one here; but it is all one, Neighbour Pope, thy <hi>ipſe dixit</hi> will rather paſs than be proved, unleſs one of thy graving Angels will bring this Church to us.</p>
               <p>In a Coffer of ſilver, and gilt, having a great round Cryſtal at the foot thereof, were contained certain of the bones of thoſe Innocents whom <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> ſlew.</p>
               <p>Really the Pope hath a great advantage of us Hereticles, there is not many of us that can ſay any thing againſt this Relique, but a little proof for the confirmation of our Faith would have done no hurt.</p>
               <p>In a little Cheſt of ſilver, and gilt, ſet with precious ſtones, having in it a little long Cryſtal, were part of the bones of St. <hi>Nicholas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Nicholas</hi>'s bones are very efficacious to cure the Itch; therefore if any be troubled there with let them repair to <hi>Rome,</hi> and it ſhall coſt them nothing but their Charges.</p>
               <p>In a Cheſt of Silver and gilt, having in it a long Cryſtal; were contained divers parts of our Ladies Cloaths.</p>
               <p>Certainly the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> had the beſt Wordrobe of any in her time,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56276:28"/>for in <hi>Spain, France,</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> I have ſeen as many of her Cloaths as a good handſom Cart would contain.</p>
               <p>In divers other Cheſts of silver, whereof ſome were gilt and enamell'd, and ſome ungilt; ſome ſet with Precious Stones, ſome without Precious stones, theſe Reliques following were contained.</p>
               <p>Part of <hi>Thom is Becket</hi>'s Fleſh reſolved: a piece of the Fleſh of St. <hi>Nicholas:</hi> a Finger and a Tooth of St. <hi>Alban.</hi> Part of the Hair of St. <hi>Edmund</hi> the Confeſſor, and part of his Garments, and one of his Teeth. A Tooth of <hi>S. Mildred</hi> the Virgin. Alſo of the Rib of St. <hi>John Baptiſt.</hi> The Shirt of <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> and his Sandals. Part of the Blood of St. <hi>Edmund</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, with his Hoſe, Shirt, and Pillow. A Bone of St. <hi>Mildred.</hi> A Bone of St. <hi>Edburg.</hi> The Powl of <hi>Thomas Becket:</hi> The Duſt of his Body. The Arm of St. <hi>Jerome.</hi> The Bones of St. <hi>Corduba</hi> one of the eleven thouſand Virgins. A bone of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> with a piece of his Cloak or Mantle. The Oyl of Saint <hi>Demetris.</hi> Part of the Fleſh and Skin of <hi>Thomas Becket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Thomas Beckets</hi> Fleſh certainly is a precious Relique; and will appear ſo, if we conſider the Qualifications of the man; and beſides I have ſeen as many pieces of his Skull as an ordinary man can carry: and I have ſeen no leſs than four or five Arms of St. <hi>Jerome:</hi> but the Papiſts may make as many Arms as they pleaſe.</p>
               <p>In an Ivory Cheſt were theſe Reliques contained.</p>
               <p>The Cheek-bones of <hi>Coſmas</hi> and <hi>Damian</hi> with nine Teeth. The Bones of St. <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle. St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Beard, and part of his Croſs. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain pieces of our Ladies Garments. Part of St. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi>'s Hairy Coat. Of the Duſt of St. <hi>Furſeus</hi> Head. Certain Bones of St. <hi>Hipolytus</hi> the Martyr. The Blood of St. <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle: Certain Reliques of <hi>S. Stephen:</hi> Part of Chriſts Crib: Part of our Ladies Bed: Certain Bones of St.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ore of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>roſs.</note> 
                  <hi>Agnes,</hi> of St. <hi>Julian,</hi> of St. <hi>Praxed,</hi> of St. <hi>Wandregeſile,</hi> and a large piece of the holy Croſs.</p>
               <p>Theſe coſtly Cheſts in which theſe pretended Reliques were kept, as theſe Lyars ſay,<note place="margin">Note.</note> might amaze the ignorant beholders; but to ſee their pretended Saints thus pulled in pieces to be ſhown, ſheweth planny the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of theſe Merchants of <hi>Rome;</hi> and that St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Beard was pulled off to be ſhewn, if it were true, was Inhumane: but where were all theſe Trinkets kept the 800 years before they thus ſet them out to view?</p>
               <p>In a little round Cheſt of Ivory was contained the ſtone upon which <hi>St. Stephen</hi> ſtood when he was ſtoned unto death: Alſo a Bone of Saint <hi>James</hi> the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p>How does it appear Saint <hi>Stephen</hi> ſtood upon one ſtone? or upon any ſtone at all?<note place="margin">Note.</note> And there are ſo many of theſe ſtones, that a ſober <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> wiſhed that Relique were taken out of the way, it appearing ſo ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous.</p>
               <p>In a great Coffer of Ivory, with a round head, and barred about with Copper and gilt, were theſe Reliques. <hi>Thomas Becket</hi>'s Mitre made of white silk, with the Tunicle wherein he was buried: Another Mitre of his made of white Sattin, which he uſed to wear on ſingle Feaſts: Alſo his Gloves which he uſed in Divine Service, with three goodly Ouches up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them: Alſo his Sandals embroidered moſt coſtly, with Roſes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Flowers of Gold: <hi>Item,</hi> his Breeches of Hair: Part of his Bed and of his Girdle: The Duſt of his Body: His Cap, and other Veſtures: His
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56276:28"/>Coul: The Lace or band wherewith his hairy Breeches were tyed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: Part of his Fleſh and Blood reſolved: His Girdle, his Hair, his Pillow, his Coat, his light Cap of ſilk which he wore under his Mitre: His Stamine, his Hood: A Tunicle of white ſilk to wear over an <hi>Albe:</hi> A Cloth dyed in his blood: In fine, a Whip wherewith he uſed to ſcourge himſelf when he felt <hi>Carnis inſurrectionem,</hi> that by this means he might obtain <hi>Vitam aeternam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hem! hem! hem! very witty:<note place="margin">Note.</note> All theſe Reliques are pretended to be his, to countenance the uſe of ſuch Formalities,<note place="margin">Every Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent would do well to get this Whip and theſe Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> and to bring Whipping in the more credit. But this St. <hi>Thomas Becket</hi>'s Whip and Veſtments I know are excellent Reliques, for they have cured <hi>Watton</hi> College of an extraordinary Diſtemper, <hi>viz. Poverty,</hi> for if Father <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liams</hi> did ſpeak the truth, an old Lady gave the College 20000 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr> Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> or elſe for ought I know, ſaid the Father <hi>Williams,</hi> we might have ſtarved.</p>
               <p>In the firſt ſtanding Table made of Wood, with two doors, covered over with ſilver, and gilt, and adorned with divers precious Stones, were theſe Reliques following contained.</p>
               <p>A Tooth of <hi>St. Laurence</hi> the Martyr, with divers of his bones.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Beckets</hi> low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy Breeches were ſweet Reliques. A bleſſed Crop of Reliques.</note> Alſo a Rag of the hairy Breeches of <hi>Thomas Becket.</hi> Certain bones of Saint <hi>Urban,</hi> Pope and Martyr; of St. <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> Martyr: of St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop: of St. <hi>Eugenius,</hi> Pope: Of S. <hi>Clement,</hi> Pope and Martyr: Of S. <hi>Felix,</hi> Pope: of St. <hi>George,</hi> Martyr: of St. <hi>Bennet,</hi> and alſo of the Innocents whom <hi>Herod</hi> ſlew.</p>
               <p>How they came a thouſand years after by the bones of the Babes that <hi>Herod</hi> ſlew, makes them that underſtand themſelves wonder.<note place="margin">Note.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſecond Table was a bone of St. <hi>George,</hi> a bone of St. <hi>Stephen</hi> the Pope, a bone of St. <hi>Salvius,</hi> and a bone of St. <hi>Mildrid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What the Vertues of theſe bones are, theſe Popiſh Doctors are able to give an account to the people; but the moſt ſober men of their party look on them as abominable Cheats.</p>
               <p>In the third Table was a piece of Chriſt's Croſs, a piece of his Nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin,<note place="margin">More of the Croſs.</note> and a piece of that Table whereon he made his Supper with his Twelve Apoſtles, when he ordained the <hi>Sacrament of his Bodywand Blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> A bone of St. <hi>Philip</hi> the Apoſtle; a bone of <hi>S. James</hi> the Apoſtle, and a bone of <hi>S. Thomas</hi> the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> A bone of <hi>S. Stephen</hi> the Martyr, a bone of <hi>Mary Madalen,</hi> the Hair of <hi>S. Cecily,</hi> a bone of <hi>S. Margaret,</hi> and the blood of <hi>Thomas Becket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>More blood of this<note n="†" place="margin">cket.</note> blood Saint ſtill, good God! when ſhall we have an end of it? Certainly the blood of Traytors hath greater veneration amongſt Papiſts, than the blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>In a long Cryſtal, with a Foot of ſilver, and gilt, and a round Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſet with four precious Stones, were theſe Reliques contained.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:56276:29"/>
               <p>The Oyl of S. <hi>Katherine</hi> the Virgin, part of the body of S. <hi>Oſith,</hi> Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin: Alſo a good lump of the ſtone whereon Chriſt ſtood when he aſcended into the Kingdom of his Father.</p>
               <p>Theſe Papiſts are excellent Chymiſts, they have extracted more Oyl out of poor S. <hi>Katherine</hi> (who before ſhe ſuffered was almoſt ſtarved) than out of any Saint I can read of; I have ſeen at leaſt a Quart my ſelf in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt Cheſt of Ivory were the Napkin of our Lady, the Arm of S. <hi>Pauline</hi> the Biſhop, a bone of S. <hi>Ciriack,</hi> and of S. <hi>Modevine</hi> the Virgin.</p>
               <p>Certainly our Lady was an excellent Houſe-wiſe, and provided good ſtore of Napkins, or elſe how would this poor Whore of <hi>Rome</hi> have had Napkins enough (called our Ladies Napkins) to have beſtowed on Churches.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond Cheſt of Ivory were part of Chriſts Sepulchre, part of our Ladies Coffin, with part of her Hair. Alſo a bone of S. <hi>Stephen</hi> the firſt Martyr, a bone of S. <hi>George,</hi> the Duſt of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> Martyr: A piece of the Croſs that the good Thief, called <hi>Diſmas,</hi> did hang on: A Rib of bleſſed S. <hi>Edburg,</hi> Virgin: Alſo certain bones of <hi>S. Theodore</hi> the Martyr.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> A bone of one of the Innocents, with divers bones of <hi>S. VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> Confeſſor.</p>
               <p>Here is a jolly Crop of Reliques: Certainly if our learned Jeſuites in <hi>England</hi> could but get a luſty Fardel of them, they would ſtore a bonny company of ſhops with them.</p>
               <p>In the third Cheſt of Ivory were contained theſe Reliques following, certain of the bones of <hi>S. Damian,</hi> Martyr: a bone of <hi>S. Nereus,</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr: certain bones of <hi>S. Innocentius,</hi> Martyr; of <hi>S. Sebaſtian,</hi> Martyr; of <hi>S. Theodorus,</hi> Martyr; of <hi>S. Demetrius,</hi> Martyr; of <hi>S. Griſand,</hi> and <hi>S. Dariss.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> A bone of the head of bleſſed <hi>S. Amphibalus,</hi> Martyr: alſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Reliques of the man of God, which were found with the body of <hi>S. Sebaſtian,</hi> Martyr.</p>
               <p>Again, The bones of <hi>S. Pentaleon,</hi> Martyr; of <hi>S. Julian,</hi> Biſhop and Confeſſor: A Tooth of <hi>S. Francis,</hi> alſo part of his Hair: Alſo the bones of <hi>S. Fortunate,</hi> Biſhop and Confeſſor. A piece of the Sepulchre of <hi>S. Lazarus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The bones of <hi>S. Aguſs,</hi> Virgin. Alſo the Reliques of <hi>S. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina,</hi> Virgin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The Spunge of <hi>S. Praxed,</hi> Virgin, which was dipped in the blood of many Martyrs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> A Penny that was bored through with the Spear of <hi>S. Cyriack,</hi> Martyr.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> A Penny that was bored through with the Spear of <hi>S. Maurice,</hi> Martyr. Moreover the bones of <hi>S. Euſtathius,</hi> Martyr; of <hi>S. Vitale,</hi> Martyr; of <hi>S. Cyriack,</hi> Martyr; of <hi>S. Agapit,</hi> Martyr; of <hi>S. Roniface,</hi> Martyr; of <hi>S. Algar,</hi> Martyr; of <hi>S. Sylveſter,</hi> Pope and Confeſſor;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:56276:29"/>of <hi>S. John Chryſoſtom,</hi> of <hi>S. Nicander,</hi> of <hi>S. Secundius,</hi> Virgin; and finally, a piece of the Sepulchre of S. <hi>Seba.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note>
               </p>
               <p>How theſe people are fooled and cheated with a multitude of idle things, under the notion of holy Reliques! But that a Penny ſhould be a Relique, becauſe it had a hole bored in with the ſpear of a pretended Saint, is ſuch a Foppery, as none but men and women bewitched by their jugling lying Prieſts would ſet any value upon.</p>
               <p>In the fourth Cheſt of Ivory were contained theſe Reliques follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>The Bones of the holy Martyrs which were put to Martyrdom with bleſſed St. <hi>Priſcus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> certain bones of St. <hi>Ireneus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lyons,</hi> and Martyr, and of his Fellows. Alſo bones of St. <hi>Flavian</hi> Martyr, of <hi>Potentian</hi> Martyr, of St. <hi>Darius</hi> Martyr.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> the Oyl of St. <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Gardmey,</hi> which flowed out of the Breafts and Paps of the Image of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> certain bones of St. <hi>Nictarius,</hi> of St. <hi>Liberius,</hi> of St. <hi>Serenus,</hi> of St. <hi>Marian,</hi> of St. <hi>Julit,</hi> of St. <hi>Cyrick,</hi> of the 11000. Virgins, and part of the Head and Hair of St. <hi>Trocia</hi> Virgin.</p>
               <p>As one may ſtand amazed at the great multitude of their Bones,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and Hair, and Clouts that are mentioned in the eight laſt Paragraphs; ſo may they wonder at the horrid lye in this laſt, that when they have made the Image of a Woman of Clouts, or Wood, or Stone; Oyl ſhould flow out of it.</p>
               <p>In the fifth Cheſt of Ivory theſe Reliques were contained.</p>
               <p>A piece of the Table whereon Chriſt did eat his Supper with his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples when he ordained the Sacrament of his Body and Blood. <hi>Et de quadragena Chriſti.</hi> Some of the Fleſh and Blood and many other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of <hi>Tho. Becket.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> a Tooth of worſhipful <hi>Odo,</hi> Abbot of <hi>Battell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They take great care to ſet up <hi>Tom.</hi> of <hi>Becket,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note> who was a great Chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and horrible Traytor, and yet one of the Popes Saints.</p>
               <p>In the Sixth Cheſt of Ivory were theſe Reliques contained.</p>
               <p>The Bones of St. <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, of St. <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle, of St. <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> Pope and Martyr, of St. <hi>Urbian</hi> Pope and Martyr, of St. <hi>Facun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine</hi> Martyr, of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> Martyr, of St. <hi>Maurus</hi> Biſhop and Confeſſor, of St. <hi>Macharius</hi> Confeſſor, of St. <hi>Juſtin</hi> Virgin and Martyr, of St. <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> the Apoſtle, of St. <hi>Chremes</hi> Martyr, of St. <hi>Tiburtius</hi> Martyr, of St. <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> Pope and Martyr, of St. <hi>Adrian</hi> Martyr, of St. <hi>Maurus</hi> Abbot and Confeſſor. Alſo of the dry Blood and Veſtures of St. <hi>Eufemia</hi> Virgin and Martyr.</p>
               <p>We find the Bodies of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the Churches in <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Note.</note>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:56276:30"/>and that their bones ſhould be in this Cheſt, looks like the reſt of their Frauds, and proveth them Forgers of Lyes in the ſight of all rational men.</p>
               <p>In a Cupboard of Ivory with a Crucifix upon it were theſe Reliques contained.</p>
               <p>The bones of <hi>Coſino</hi> and <hi>Damiane;</hi> the bones of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> Biſhop and Confeſſor, and a great Doctor; a bone of St. <hi>Leo</hi> Pope and Confeſſor; the duſt of St. <hi>Diſciple;</hi> the bones of St. <hi>Machutus, Vulfrannus</hi> and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinianus.</hi> The bones of St. <hi>Anaſtatius,</hi> Martyr; of St. <hi>Agnes,</hi> Virgin and Martyr; of St. <hi>Amalburg</hi> Virgin; of St. <hi>Keinburg</hi> Virgin; the hair of St. <hi>Barbara</hi> Virgin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> three fingers and two teeth with other bones of St. <hi>Alban,</hi> the firſt Martyr of <hi>England;</hi> the bones of St. <hi>Cyriack</hi> Levite and Martyr, with three of his teeth. Alſo the bones of St. <hi>Gervaſius</hi> and <hi>Prothaſius,</hi> Martyrs; the bones of St. <hi>Wandregeſile</hi> Abbot and Confeſſor; of St. <hi>Samſon</hi> Biſhop, with one of his teeth; of St. <hi>Albine</hi> Confeſſor; of St. <hi>Remigius</hi> and <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manns</hi> Biſhops; of St. <hi>Margaret</hi> Virgin; of St. <hi>Oportune</hi> Virgin; of St. <hi>Batilde</hi> Queen; the hair of St. <hi>Alburg</hi> Virgin; the Veſtures of St. <hi>Alde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gund</hi> Virgin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The duſt of St. <hi>Pancras</hi> Martyr; the bones of St. <hi>Adrian</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr; of St. <hi>Chriſto,</hi> Martyr; the duſt of St. <hi>Criſpian</hi> and <hi>Criſpine,</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs; the bones of St. <hi>Pantaleon</hi> Martyr; of St. <hi>Sixtus</hi> Pope; of St. <hi>Apelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> Martyr; of St. <hi>Stephen</hi> Pope.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The duſt of St. <hi>Medard</hi> Confeſſor, alſo a rib of St. <hi>Apolliner</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, with one of his teeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The bones of St. <hi>Firmine</hi> Martyr and Biſhop; and of St. <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> Martyr; a piece of Chriſts Sepulchre; a lump of the Pillar where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto our Lord was bound when he was ſcourged of the wicked Jews; a piece of the ſtone whereupon the Angel ſtood when the Women came to anoint the Body of Chriſt. Alſo a good big lump of the ſtone where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Chriſt ſtood when he aſcended into heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">More of <hi>Moſes</hi> Rod. Sure there was abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live</hi> bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, we find of them ſo many in this ſtory.</note> A piece of <hi>Moſes</hi> rod that was turned into a Serpent. Alſo a parcel of that ſtone whereupon the Lord ſtood in <hi>Galilee;</hi> alſo the Palm and Olive branch which Chriſt bare in his hand on <hi>Palm-Sunday,</hi> as he was riding towards <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> Part of the Table whereat Chriſt ſate at his ſupper when he waſhed his Diſciples feet; a piece of the Garment which our Lady made for our Lord; a piece of the priſon out of the which the Lord delivered bleſſed <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle; a piece of the cloth which was laid upon Chriſts ſepulchre; part of the hair and garments of St. <hi>Anne</hi> our Ladies Mother; alſo of the garments of St. <hi>Helias,</hi> of the two ſiſters <hi>Mary</hi> and <hi>Martha;</hi> and alſo of St. <hi>Sophy</hi> the Virgin; again, part of the wooll which our Lady did ſpin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The duſt of St. <hi>Benet</hi> the Virgin: the bones of St. <hi>Chryſtopher</hi> Martyr; of St. <hi>Lambert,</hi> with his duſt and part of his garments; a piece of the beard and Veſtures of St. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> Biſhop and Confeſſor; the bones of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Pope, with one of his teeth; the bones of S. <hi>Wingunalock</hi> Abbot and Confeſſor; of St. <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> Martyr; of St.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:56276:30"/>
                  <hi>Quintin</hi> Martyr; In fine, a piece of the Manger wherein Chriſt lay.</p>
               <p>That all theſe Reliques ſhould be ſhown were more than a days work to produce, and thus they buſied the minds of the poor people, to fetch in money to them that made the ſhow; but that ſome of the Wool that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> ſpun ſhould be kept to <hi>Tom.</hi> of <hi>Becket</hi>'s time, which was nine hundred or a thouſand years, none but Cheaters would pretend, and none but deluded souls believe: how happy was <hi>England</hi> when all theſe Frauds were detected, and how is the reſt of the world abuſed by Papal Pettifoggers.</p>
               <p>In the firſt Coffer made of Copper, are contained theſe Reliques:</p>
               <p>The bones of St. <hi>Vulſtane</hi> Biſhop and Confeſſor; and of St. <hi>Priſca</hi> Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The hair of St. <hi>Anſelme</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Certainly, <hi>Anſelme</hi>'s hair muſt needs have much virtue in it, becauſe our bleſſed Lady uſed to comb it once or twice in a week; and becauſe that he was very devout to her Ladyſhip, ſhe did aſſume the Popes power, and gave Indulgences her ſelf to this hair; witneſs a Sermon Father <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers</hi> the Jeſuit preacht.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond Copper Coffer were theſe Reliques contained.</p>
               <p>The Reliques of St. <hi>James</hi> the Apoſtle: the bones of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> the Apoſtle: the bones of St. <hi>Thaddeus</hi> the Apoſtle: and alſo of St. <hi>Matthew</hi> the Apoſtle and Evangeliſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The Staffe of St. <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle: the bones of St. <hi>Luke</hi> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt. In fine, the bones of St. <hi>Philip</hi> the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p>It's a wonder they had not ſome of Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s Needles and Thread he made his Tents with, as well as his Staff:<note place="margin">Note.</note> but that the good Servants of Chriſt ſhould have their Bodies torn in preces, to have their bones thus ſhown, is a ſign of great inhumanity.</p>
               <p>In the third Copper Coffer were theſe Reliques contained.</p>
               <p>A piece of the holy Croſs: certain Reliques of St. <hi>Andrew:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">More of the Croſs yet.</note> the blood of St. <hi>Gervaſe:</hi> Reliques alſo of St. <hi>Griſant</hi> and <hi>Darias:</hi> of <hi>Joſeph</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimathea,</hi> of the Prophets <hi>Elizeas</hi> and <hi>Abdias:</hi> of St. <hi>Pancras:</hi> St. <hi>James:</hi> St. <hi>Faith:</hi> St. <hi>Brigide:</hi> St. <hi>Maurice</hi> and his Companions; and of St. <hi>Bertine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> Certain bones of St. <hi>John Baptiſt;</hi> the Reliques of the Saints <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Paul:</hi> A bone of S. <hi>Euſtathius,</hi> Martyr.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> was buried by his Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.12.<note place="margin">Note.</note> and then how came they by his bones that was buried a thouſand years before?</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:56276:31"/>
               <p>In the fourth Copper Coffer were theſe Reliques.</p>
               <p>Part of the Duſt of Saint <hi>John Baptist</hi>'s Body which was burnt: Two little pieces of the Holy Croſs:<note place="margin">More pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Croſs.</note> A certain bone of Saint <hi>James,</hi> the Brother of Saint <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt: Part of that ſtone whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord did eat after that he called his Diſciples out of the Ships.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> A piece of that Oak upon which <hi>Abraham</hi> did climb to ſee the Lord: A portion of our Ladies Coffin: A large piece of that ſtone whereupon Chriſt ſtood when he was transfigured: A piece of our Lords Sepulchre: A piece of that Earth whereof God formed <hi>Adam:</hi> Certain Reliques of the elven thouſand Virgins which lye at <hi>Collen:</hi> Alſo a bone of Saint <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> was not burnt but buried,<note place="margin">Note.</note> as above; ſo that the fraud in this, as in all other caſes, is plain. But that they may have of the Earth of which <hi>Adam</hi> was made is no wonder, but a cheat in them that would make it ſeem a wonder, for it was of the common duſt.</p>
               <p>In a white great Box. made of Wood, were theſe Reliques contained.</p>
               <p>Part of Chriſt's Sepulchre: Part of that place where he prayed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Father: A piece of that Table whereat Chriſt our Lord ſupped: A piece of that Earth where Chriſt's Croſs was put down when he was Crucified: A piece of Chriſt's Cradle: A piece of our Ladies Bed: Part of the Seat whereon the Mother of our Lord ſate in the day of her Purification.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> A bone of S. <hi>Jerome,</hi> Prieſt and Confeſſor, with part of his Stole and of his other Garments: Alſo bones of the Innocents: Bones of S. <hi>Bartholomew</hi> the Apoſtle, of S. <hi>Blaſe,</hi> Biſhop and Martyr; of S. <hi>Clement,</hi> Pope and Martyr; of S. <hi>Vincent,</hi> Martyr; of S. <hi>George,</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr; of S. <hi>Maurice,</hi> Martyr; and of his Fellows. A piece of the Leg of S. <hi>Damian,</hi> Martyr: The hones of S. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> Martyr; of S. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the Pope, and of S. <hi>Bennet</hi> the Abbot together. The Duſt of S. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and part of his Hairy Coat, and of his other Garments. The Hair of S. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the Wife of <hi>Zachary</hi> the Prieſt, and Mother of S. <hi>John Baptiſt.</hi> A piece of the Gridiron whereon S. <hi>Laurence</hi> was roaſted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">More of the Croſs yet.</note> A great piece of the Holy Croſs: Part of S. <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle's Beard, and alſo of his Table: The bones of S. <hi>Hipolytus,</hi> Martyr; of S. <hi>Roman,</hi> Martyr; of S. <hi>Martyn,</hi> with a piece of his Cloak. The bones of S. <hi>Silveſter,</hi> Biſhop and Confeſſor: The Beard of S. <hi>Anthony:</hi> A bone of S. <hi>Paul</hi> the firſt Hermite: Part of S. <hi>Julian</hi>'s Head, with a piece of his Coat.</p>
               <p>Theſe things are ſo ridiculous,<note place="margin">Note.</note> that none that is honeſt will pretend to have them, and none that is wiſe will regard them.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:56276:31"/>
               <p>In a great Horn of Ivory, hanging under the Beam beyond the High Altar, were theſe Reliques following contained.</p>
               <p>The bones of S. <hi>Blaſe,</hi> of S. <hi>Stephen</hi> the firſt Martyr, of S. <hi>Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew,</hi> of S. <hi>Patrick,</hi> of S. <hi>Martyn,</hi> of S. <hi>Thomas</hi> the Apoſtle, of Saint <hi>Andrew</hi> the Apoſtle, of S. <hi>Giles,</hi> of S. <hi>Serene,</hi> of S. <hi>Done,</hi> of S. <hi>Edburg,</hi> of S. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> of S. <hi>Katherine,</hi> of S. <hi>Agnes,</hi> of S. <hi>Juſtus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The Hairs of S. <hi>Agaſſe,</hi> and of S. <hi>Cecile:</hi> A piece of the Rock whereupon the Croſs of our Lord ſtood: A piece of the Rock of <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotha:</hi> And a piece of our Lady's Sepulchre.</p>
               <p>A little before the Croſs ſtood in Earth, and now it was upon a Rock;<note place="margin">Note.</note> but how can they have the bones of. S. <hi>Stephen?</hi> when the holy Text tells us, <hi>Acts</hi> the 8. and <hi>ver.</hi> 2. that <hi>devout men carried Stephen and buried him,</hi> which was 900 years before poplings began their Pagean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and doubtleſs turned to duſt.</p>
               <p>In a great Croſs made of Wood at the Altar of S. Croſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> covered over with Silver, and gilt, and ſet with divers precious ſtones, with a Croſs in the midſt, were theſe Reliques following.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, A Croſs of Silver, and gilt, garniſhed with precious ſtones, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the midſt of it a piece of the Holy Croſs,<note place="margin">More of the Croſs yet.</note> with certain Reliques of <hi>Thomas Becket.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, A Finger of S. <hi>Andrew</hi> the Apoſtle.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, A Bone of S. <hi>Stephen.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fourthly, A piece of S. <hi>Vulſtan</hi>'s Fleſh.</item>
               </list>
               <p>To pull the Saints thus in pieces, to ſhow ſo many pieces of their fleſh, is to be more like <hi>Cannibals</hi> than Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and would make a tender-hearted Chriſtian weep to think of ſuch horrid Cruelties.</p>
               <p>In the firſt Coffin, over the Beam, were theſe Reliques.</p>
               <p>The Arm of S. <hi>Vulfade,</hi> Martyr: The Arm of S. <hi>Ruſſinian,</hi> Martyr; and another great bone of his back.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> A bone of the Head of S. <hi>Chad,</hi> Biſhop and Confeſſor, with part of his Clothes.</p>
               <p>They tore the very back bones of them they call Saints in pieces,<note place="margin">Note.</note> to make a ſhow of to get money.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond Coffin were contained,</p>
               <p>A piece of Chriſts Croſs, of his Crib and Sepulchre.<note place="margin">More of the Croſs yet.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> The bones of S. <hi>Calix,</hi> Pope and Martyr: The bones of Saint
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:56276:32"/>
                  <hi>James</hi> the Apoſtle, who is called the Brother of the Lord: The bones of S. <hi>Catharine,</hi> Virgin and Martyr.</p>
               <p>Lord,<note place="margin">Note.</note> how many poor people did they pull Limb from Limb to get money by?</p>
               <p>In the third Coffin were contained,</p>
               <p>The Banner of Chriſt: A piece of Chriſt's Sepulchre: Certain Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of our Latly: The bones of S. <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, with the bones of S. <hi>Martyn,</hi> Biſhop and Confeſſor.</p>
               <p>In how many places have they pretended to have the bones of Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> But that they ſhould have a piece of Chriſt's Sepulchre, which <hi>S. Matthew</hi> tells us was hewn out of a Rock, <hi>c.</hi> 27. <hi>v.</hi> 60. is very unlike, but as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>the ſimple,</hi> meaning ignorant and fooliſh people, <hi>believe every word, Prov.</hi> 14.15. and ſuch are they which go after Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prieſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:56276:32"/>
               <head>Of the famed, or rather, infamous <hi>Indulgences, Pardons,</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FRom the beginning of the world unto the time that <hi>Rome</hi> was firſtmade, were 3212 years. And from thence to the Nativity of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, were 750 years. And in this City of <hi>Rome</hi> there are 400 Churches, in which Maſs is daily done: but there be ſeven of the ſame priviledged above all other with great holineſs and pardon, as is hereafter ſhewed.<note place="margin">And ſomthing elſe, or <hi>Rome</hi> is fearfully bely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, even by her own Votaries; and therefore not too much Holineſs good Father Pope.</note> The firſt is St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church, ſcituate on the foot of an Hill, ſo that men aſcend thereunto by a ſtair of 29 ſteps. And as oft as a man goeth up and down that ſtair, he is releaſed of the <hi>7th</hi> part of penance enjoined. This was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Pope <hi>Alexander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> as ye come before the Church a Well ſpringeth, and above the door is an Image of our Lord, between whoſe Feet is one of the pence that God was ſold for: and as oft as ye look upon that peny,<note place="margin">The peny re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique that God was ſold for.</note> ye have 1400 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>Certainly, men that are in their wits would ſcarce give two pence for ſo much pardon as the ſight of this peny would or could produce; but I ſee they prefer a peny before the blood of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> in the ſame Church, on the right ſide, is a Pillar that was ſometime of <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple,<note place="margin">Our Lords lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pillar and excellent cure for mad peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam hath been more effectual</note> at which Pillar our Lord was wont to reſt him when he preached to the people: At which Pillar, if there be any mad, or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with ſpirits, they be delivered and made whole. And in that Church be 11 Altars, and at every Altar is 48 years of pardon and as many Lents or Kerries: And ſeven of the Altars are priviledged with great grace and pardon.</p>
               <p>At the firſt Altar is the viſage of our Lord: who looketh upon that, hath 700 years of pardon: Alſo the Spear that Chriſt was pierced with, brought from <hi>Conſtautinople,</hi> ſent from the great Turk to Pope Innocent the Eighth.</p>
               <p>When I have nothing elſe to do I will viſit theſe Altars, yet I think a man may do as well to ſtay at home.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Altar is of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> there ye have 500 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>The third Altar is of St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> there ye have 400 year of pardon.</p>
               <p>The <hi>4th</hi> Altar is of our Lady, there is 700 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>The <hi>5th</hi> Altar is of St. <hi>Leo,</hi> there he received the abſolution in his Maſs from Heaven: and there is 700 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>The <hi>6th</hi> Altar is of <hi>All-Souls:</hi> and there is 500 years of pardon, and every high Feaſt a Soul out of Purgatory.</p>
               <p>The <hi>7th</hi> Altar is of <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Jude:</hi> there is 600 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>And before the door ſtand two iron Croſſes; who kiſſeth thoſe Croſſes hath 500 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>Had not Chriſt propoſed in his Goſpel the way and method that God uſed in pardoning the ſins of mankind, the Pope would have deſerved well at mens hands, yet theſe pardons require ſo tedious a Journey, that it would ruine a poor Papiſt to perform it: therefore my advice is, That he ſtay at home, and make but uſe of Gods means for obtaining pardon, and I aſſure him he may have it an eaſier rate; for God offers it without mony, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out price, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:56276:33"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> upon our <hi>Lady-day</hi> in Lent, hangeth afore the Quire a Cloth that our Lady made her ſelf, and it hangeth ſtill till our <hi>Lady-day</hi> Aſſumption. And as many times as a man beholdeth that Cloth, he hath 400 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>Our Lady was admirably well imployed, and ſo very many good works have been done by her, that the Papiſts need do none themſelves.</p>
               <p>Alſo as many times as a man goeth through the Crouds at St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church, he hath 400 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>Here the Pope of his great liberality, (we thank his Holineſs for it,) crouds a great deal of pardon upon his Votaries.</p>
               <p>And as oft as a man followeth the Sacrament to the ſick bodies, he hath 1400 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>I do not wonder now why Rogues and Whores were ſo Zealous to follow the Sacrament, for here is a Jolly crop of pardon beſtowed on them by good Mr. Pope.</p>
               <p>Alſo Pope <hi>Sylvester</hi> granted to all them that daily go to the Church of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> the third part of all his ſins releaſed, and all his Vows and Promiſes releaſed, and all his ſins forgotten, releaſed and forgiven, except laying vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent hand upon Father or Mother. And above this is granted 2800 years of pardon, and the merits of as many Lents or Karins. (What a Karin is, ye ſhall find in the end of this book.)</p>
               <p>And in the Feaſt of St. <hi>Peter</hi> 1000 years of pardon, and as many Karins, and the third part of penance enjoyned, releaſed. And from the Aſcenſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day of our Lord, unto the Aſſumption of our Lady, ye have 1400 years of pardon, and as many Karins, and forgiveneſs of the third part of all ſins.</p>
               <p>Who would converſe with ſuch Vermin, or ſtand bound to take their words; for here is at the firſt daſh a bonny releaſe from all vows and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Certainly men are not ſafe in ſuch Converſation as may be ruin'd for ſuch a proiniſe-makers going to ſee a Church. Nay, it is the Opinion of the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, if a man hath but a Friend at <hi>Rome</hi> that will do it for him, it is all one: therefore there can be no credit given either to their Promiſes or Vows.</p>
               <p>And upon the one ſide of St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church lieth a Church-yard,<note place="margin">But they muſt part with the mony that they have begged in their Journey.</note> and that is called Gods field, where none but poor pilgrims are buried, and it is the Land that was bought with the 30 pence for which our Lord was ſold. As oft as a man goeth upon that ground, he hath 15 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>This, if the Pope lieth not, would be an excellent motive to draw Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims and other perſons to <hi>Rome;</hi> but lazie Proteſtants had rather ſtay at home.</p>
               <p>In the old Latin Book we read concerning the Church of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> that there are granted every day in the year to ſo many as devoutly come unto it, 48 years of pardon, and as many Lents, with the forgiveneſs of the third part of all ſins.</p>
               <p>Well, it is but the forgiveneſs of the third part of your ſins; but the Pope hath an excellent Church, where all your ſins ſhall be pardoned: go thither, and let this alone till you are aſſured of your bargain, for before you get home it will coſt you dear.</p>
               <p>Note alſo, That whenſoever the Feaſt of St. <hi>Peter</hi> comes, or the Feaſt of the aforeſaid Altars, or the Feaſt of the Nativity of our Lord, or of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> or the Feaſt of <hi>All-Saints,</hi> or any other double Feaſt, than all the aforeſaid Indulgences and Pardons are doubled. Alſo in the Feaſt of the Annuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of bleſſed <hi>Mary</hi> the Virgin, there are 1000 years of pardon. Again,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:56276:33"/>from the above-named Feaſt unto the Kalends of <hi>Auguſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Come, here's your man Sir, no leſs than 12000 years of pardon toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with a <hi>3d</hi> part better and better yet, give me this Church for my mony.</note> there are 12000 years of pardon, and as many Lents, and the forgiveneſs of the third part of all the ſins.</p>
               <p>Poor St. <hi>Peter,</hi> how hath this abominable Harlot dreſs'd thee up, I am ſure thou didſt teach the world other Doctrine; but this Pardon-monger hath not told us the price: I believe, if we go round the Church, we ſhall find the reckoning dear before we come out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> whoſoever aſcendeth or goeth up the ſtairs of St. <hi>Peter</hi> devoutly, to him are granted for every ſtep ſeven years of pardon by Pope <hi>Alexander.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſteps being well trod, and the example of his Maſter our Lord Chriſt, will produce a better than Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> could ever give: but as for the Stone ſteps in St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church what pardon they procure, let Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> inform you; but unleſs he gives better evidence than his own words, we will give him leave to lie, and our ſelves the liberty of not giving credit to what he ſaith.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Paul</hi> without the walls, ye have 47000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>Here is more pardon than many an honeſt man can tell what to do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, or at leaſt, more than he will have occaſion for.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> in the day of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> Converſion, ye have a 100 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> on <hi>Childermas</hi> day 4000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tas</hi> of St. <hi>Martin,</hi> when the Church was hallowed, 14000 years of pardon, and as many Karins, and the third part of all ſins releaſed.</p>
               <p>Moreover, he that viſiteth the Church of St. <hi>Paul</hi> two Sundays, doth as much as though he went on pilgrimage to St. <hi>James,</hi> and come again.</p>
               <p>In this Church alſo on the right hand of the Quire, is a devout Image of the Croſs, which ſpake to St. <hi>Bridget,</hi> becauſe ſhe uſed to pray before it.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Laurence</hi> without the walls, lie the bodies of Saint <hi>Laurence,</hi> and of St. <hi>Stephen:</hi> and at the high Altar ye have 18000 years of pardon, and as many Karins. And whoſo viſiteth the other Altars, hath at each Altar 7000 years of pardon, and as many Karins. Alſo Pope <hi>Pelagius</hi> granted there at four Feaſts of the year, at each Feaſt 700 years of pardon, and as many Karins. And he that goeth thither every <hi>Wedneſday</hi> in the year, delivereth a Soul out of Purgatory, and is himſelf quit of all his ſins. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the holy Father Pope <hi>Calixt</hi> the third hath granted to all men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that devoutly viſit the aforeſaid Church, full remiſſion of all their ſins. Alſo if any man enter into the aforeſaid Church by the door that is on the South-ſide, and ſo goeth from one Croſs to another, devoutly praying, he ſhall have clean remiſſion of all his ſins <hi>toties quoties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Croſſe,</hi> there is a Chamber or Chappel which Pope <hi>Sylveſter</hi> named <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in which Chappel is that Bond wherewith Chriſt was led to his Crucifying. Alſo two Sawcers, the one full of Jeſus's blood, and the other is full of our Ladies milk. Alſo the Spunge wherein was min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled Vinegar and Gall. <hi>Item,</hi> one of the Nails wherewith Jeſus was nailed to the Croſs. <hi>Item,</hi> a part of the block upon which St. <hi>John</hi>'s head was ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten off. <hi>Item,</hi> two Arms, the one of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> the other of St. <hi>Paul. Item,</hi> there ſtandeth a Chair in which Pope <hi>Anicetus</hi> was martyr'd: And to all them that ſit in the Church, they gave an hundred thouſand years of pardon, and as many Karins; and every <hi>Sunday</hi> a Soul out of Purgatory, and the third part of all ſins releaſed.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:56276:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> in the ſame Church is a great part of one of the Croſſes that one of the Thieves was put on that was crucified with Chriſt.</p>
               <p>I believe this Croſs grows in <hi>Spain,</hi> for there is a Jolly company of them; for I have ſeen at leaſt 40 or 50 of the Thieves Croſſes, and all to be the Croſſes of the good or bad Thief, beſides pritty gobbets of this Croſs in their little Pigeon-houſes, or Hovels where Maſs is ſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> In the ſame Church is the title of Chriſt, which <hi>Pilate</hi> wrote in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, Hebrew and Greek, which title was found in the time of Pope Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, the Eighth of that name, in the <hi>7th</hi> year of his Reign: To which title the ſame Pope hath granted great pardon to be received of all them that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther look upon the title devoutly, or with reverence either hear it read, or elſe read it themſelves.</p>
               <p>This Pope was very happy in this Find-all, I ſuppoſe it was one of his Image-graving Angels that contributed this Worthy Relique to this Church.</p>
               <p>And it is to be noted, that into that Chappel which is called <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> women do not enter, but only one in the year, that is to ſay, on the Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation day of that Chappel, which is on the even of St. <hi>Bennett</hi> the Abbot, in the month of <hi>March.</hi> At which time there is full remiſſion of all ſins, none excepted.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Mary Major</hi> there ſtandeth on the high Altar, the head of St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> and there ye have 14000 years of pardon, and as many Karins. And on the other Altar on the right hand, there is the Cradle that Jeſus lay in, part of our Ladies milk, and a great part of the holy Croſs, and many bodies of many holy Saints. And there ye have 19000 years of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and as many Karins. And Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> the <hi>4th,</hi> and St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> each of them granted thereto 10000 years of pardon, and as many Karins. And from the aſcenſion of our Lord unto <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> ye have there daily 14000 years of pardon, and as many Karins, and the <hi>3d.</hi> part of all ſins releaſed.</p>
               <p>Well, for my part I do believe a man may go to all the Cathedrals in <hi>England,</hi> yea, and Pariſh-Churches, and not find ſo much pardon as the Pope is pleaſed to confer on thoſe that go to St. <hi>Mary Major.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> That on the even of the Aſcenſion of our Lord, in which the Feaſt of the tranſlation of St. <hi>Jeroms</hi> body is celebrated, whoſe body reſteth there; Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond hath granted to ſo many as devoutly viſit in that Church the Altar of St. <hi>Jerom,</hi> clean remiſſion of all their ſins <hi>toties quoties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> On all the Feaſts of bleſſed <hi>Mary</hi> the Virgin, there are 1000 years. Alſo on the Feaſt of the Aſſumption of <hi>Mary</hi> the Virgin, to the Feaſt of her Nativity, there are 12000 years of pardon, beſides the daily Indulgences aforenamed.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Schaſtian</hi> without the Town, is a place that Pope <hi>Calixt</hi> named <hi>Talundas,</hi> where an Angel appeared and ſpake to St. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Pope. In that place is forgiveneſs of all ſins, and of all penance. At the high Altar is granted 2800 years of pardon, and as many Karins. And he that cometh to the firſt Altar that ſtandeth in the Church, hath 2400 years of pardon. And there is a Cellar or Vault wherein lyeth buried 49 Popes that died all martyrs. Whoſo cometh firſt into that place, delivereth eight Souls out of Purgatory, of ſuch as he moſt deſireth, and as much pardon thereto, as all the world cannot number nor reckon: and every <hi>Sunday</hi> deliver a Soul out of Purgatory. And in that Cellar ſtandeth a Well or Fountain, where the bodies of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> lay hid fot the ſpace of 250 years, ſo that no man wiſt where they were become: And whoſo putteth his head into that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:56276:34"/>Pit, Well, or Fountain, is clean of all ſins. Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> Pope <hi>Sylvester,</hi> Pope <hi>Nicholas,</hi> Pope <hi>Pelagius</hi> and <hi>Honorius,</hi> each of them granted to the ſame place, 1000 years of Pardon, and as many Karins. And alſo there lie the bodies of divers holy perſons, which were too long to write of. And ſo the grace that is at St. <hi>Sebaſtians,</hi> is ſo ſurely grounded, that it cannot be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away.</p>
               <p>Here is all in all; what need we have any more than all our ſins paſt, preſent, and to come, forgiven us; ay, and Souls out of Purgatory too? here is not only a bit for our ſelves, but our Friend may come in for a ſnack, we heartily thank his Holineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> In this Church of St. <hi>Mary Major,</hi> before the Quire, is the Image of our Lady, which St. <hi>Luke</hi> did paint: which Image St. <hi>Gregory</hi> did bear from St. <hi>Mary Major</hi> to St. <hi>Peters</hi> the Apoſtle, and ſo coming before the Caſtle of St. <hi>Angell,</hi> he ſaw an Angel in the top of the Caſtle, having in his hands a mighty flame of fire, and with him a great multitude of Angels, which ſung afore that image, <hi>Regina caeli laetare, &amp;c.</hi> And St. <hi>Gregory</hi> anſwered, <hi>Ora pro nobis Deum. Allelujah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am not yet ſatisfied about St. <hi>Lukes</hi> Painting; for he did not come to the Faith till ſhe was aged, as will appear, if we conſider the account the Scripture gives of him, though ſmall; and this Image that he is ſaid to paint, repreſents the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> not to be above 12 years of age, and then I am confident, that St. <hi>Luke</hi> never knew her: but his Holineſs hath ſaid it, therefore it ſhall paſs, rather than I will foul my fingers to diſprove it.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Lateran</hi> Church, Pope <hi>Sylvester</hi> gave thereto as many years of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don as it rained drops of water on the day that he hallowed the ſame Church. And at that time it rained ſo ſore, that no man had ſeen a greater rain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that day. and when he had granted this pardon, he thought in himſelf whether he had ſo much power or not; And a voice came from Heaven and ſaid, Pope <hi>Sylveſter, Thou haſt power enough to give that pardon:</hi> And God hath granted alſo thus much thereto, that if a man had made a vow to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and could not do his pilgrimage, if he go from St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church to the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran</hi> Church, he ſhall be diſcharged, and have Abſolution of that promiſe.</p>
               <p>And any time that a man cometh to the <hi>Lateran</hi> Church, he is quit of all ſins and of all penance, ſo that he be penitent for his ſins. O bleſſed is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that beareth the Child that heareth Maſs on <hi>Saturdaies</hi> at St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran,</hi> for he ſhall deliver all them that he deſireth out of Purgatory, to the number of 77 Souls.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> Upon the Tower of the Church ſtandeth a double Croſs made of the Sword wherewith St. <hi>John</hi> was beheaded: And every time that a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth that Croſs, he hath 13000 years of pardon, and as many Karins of all penance, and innumerable pardon more than he needeth for himſelf. Moreover, there is the grave where St. <hi>John</hi> laid himſelf in when he ſaid maſs, and then came there a great light over the grave, and when that light was gone, nothing was found there but heavenly bread. Out of the grave cometh every good <hi>Friday</hi> in the night, holy Cream and Oyle. And he that putteth his head in that grave, hath 100000 years of pardon, and as many Karins. <hi>Item,</hi> Behind the high Altar ſtandeth a Chair wherein God himſelf fate, whoſo ſitteth therein, hath the third part of all his ſins releaſed. And he that viſiteth all the other Altars, hath at each Altar 4400 years of pardon, and as many Karins. And on one ſide of the Church is a ſacrifice at St. <hi>John Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi>'s Altar. There is the Table that our Lord did eat at upon <hi>Maunday-Thurſday;</hi> alſo the Tables of Stone, with the ten Commandments that our
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:56276:35"/>Lord gave to <hi>Moſes</hi> upon <hi>Mount Sinai;</hi> and many other Reliques that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to our Lord of Heaven. There is alſo of the five Barley Loaves, and two Fiſhes, wherewith Chriſt fed the people in the Wilderneſs. Alſo certain of our Ladies Kerchiefes. <hi>Item,</hi> the heavenly Bread that was found in Saint <hi>Johns</hi> grave: In that offering you have releaſe of all ſins and penance. <hi>Item,</hi> in the ſame Church on the high Altar, be the heads of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> the Prophet, Father of St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> with divers other Reliques.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> In the ſame Church-yard ſtandeth a Chappel that is called <hi>Sancta Sanctorum,</hi> there is the face of our Lord. There may ye have 14000 years of pardon, and as many Karins. When the Emperor <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> was Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, he ſpake to Pope <hi>Sylveſter,</hi> ſaying, <hi>In that I have given my houſe to the Worſhip of God, grant you meekly his Grace to all that willingly come to this Town.</hi> To whom Pope <hi>Sylveſter</hi> anſwered, <hi>Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that by his great mercy hath purged you of your great Lazary, purge all their penance.</hi> He that will not believe this, may go to <hi>Rome,</hi> unto the <hi>Lateran</hi> Church, and there before the Quire door may he ſee graven in a Marble-ſtone, all that is written here. From St. <hi>Johns</hi> day unto <hi>Shrovetide</hi> all this pardon is doubled; and from <hi>shrovetide</hi> unto <hi>Eaſter</hi> the pardon is threefold doubled: and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is he that may deſerve to have this pardon.</p>
               <p>But this we muſt note by the way, that the Chappel aboveſaid is of ſo great Grace and Holineſs, that no woman may come therein. <hi>Item,</hi> above the Chappel on the left ſide, are ſteps which ſometimes were at <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Whoſo goeth up the ſteps on his knees, delivereth one Soul out of Purgatory.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Sylveſter</hi> and Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> who both conſecrated and hallowed that Church, have given and granted to all them that devoutly viſit the <hi>Lateran</hi> Church; ſuch and ſo great, yea, and ſo many Indulgences and Pardons, as no man is able to number them, but God alone, as bleſſed St. <hi>Boniface</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, ſaying, <hi>If men did know the Indulgences and Pardons of the</hi> Lateran <hi>Church, they were ſo many and ſo great, that they ſhould have no need to go to</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem <hi>to viſit Chriſts Sepulchre, nor yet unto St.</hi> James. That ſame Pope ſaith again, <hi>If any man cometh unto our See of</hi> Lateran <hi>for devotion ſake, or for pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or on pilgrimage, he is abſolved and delivered from all his ſins.</hi> And further ſaith, <hi>If any man come unto the aforeſaid See on the day of St.</hi> Saviour, <hi>he is out of hand diſpatched of all his ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Feaſt of St. <hi>Saviour,</hi> whoſe Image appeared viſibly to all the people of <hi>Rome</hi> when Pope <hi>Sylveſter</hi> hallowed the aforeſaid Church, where the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Rome</hi> were gathered together, there is remiſſion of all ſins. This Image of St. <hi>Saviour</hi> which at that time appeared viſibly to all the people of the City, remaineth yet at <hi>Rome</hi> in a certain wall, and it may duly be ſeen, and is of ſo great virtue and power that it could not be burnt, although the Church in times paſt have been twice burnt. <hi>Item,</hi> in the Chappel of St. <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> into which women may not enter under pain of Excommunication, is full remiſſion of all ſins. <hi>Item,</hi> in the Chappel of St. <hi>Laurence,</hi> into which alſo women may not enter under the like pain, (which Chappel is called <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta Sanctorum</hi>) there is alſo clean remiſſion of all ſins. And in the ſame Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is an Image of Chriſt when he was 12 years old, and it is very nobly and cunningly made and ſet forth. And about the ſame there are certain Stairs, upon which our Lord Jeſus Chriſt fell, even unto the ſhedding of his blood, and the ſign, token or mark, now evidently appeareth where the blood fell; which Stairs ſtood before <hi>Pilates</hi> houſe in <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> And whoſo goeth up theſe Stairs, he ſhall have for every Stair nine years of pardon, and as many Lents, and forgiveneſs of the third part of all his ſins.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:56276:35"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> in the Church of St. <hi>Euſtace</hi> ye may have releaſe and pardon of all ſin. And he that is ſhriven, and repenteth of his ſin, hath a 1000 years of pardon, and as many Karins.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Here followeth the knowledge of what a Karin is.</head>
               <p>A Karin is to go Wolward and barefoot ſeven year, and to faſt with bread and water that <hi>Friday,</hi> ſeven year. <hi>Item,</hi> In ſeven years not to ſleep one night where he ſleepeth another. <hi>Item,</hi> In 7 years not to come under no cover'd place, except it be to hear Maſs in the Church-door or Porch. <hi>Item,</hi> In 7 years not to eat or drink out of any Veſſel, but in the ſame that he made his avow in.</p>
               <p>He that fulfilleth all theſe points ſeven years ſucceſſively, doth and winneth a Karin or Lenton.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus may a man have at</hi> Rome <hi>great pardon and Soul-health. Bleſſed be thoſe people, and in good time are they born, that receive theſe Graces and well keep them. Of which pardon and grace, our Lord Jeſus grant to every good Chriſtian man.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Here followeth the Indulgences granted to other lower Churches in <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN <hi>Rome</hi> there is a Church of St. <hi>Peter ad vincula,</hi> which Pope <hi>Pelagius</hi> did Conſecrate and Hallow. To this Church the aforeſaid Pope <hi>Pelagius</hi> gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to remiſſion of all ſins the firſt day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> by the prayer of the Son of <hi>Theodorus</hi> the Emperor, who brought the Chain from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> wherewith <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle was bound.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Vitus, Modeſtus, Creſcentia, Marcellus,</hi> and others, to the number of 5000 martyrs, whoſe bodies were ſlain in the ſame place in the time of <hi>Antoninus</hi> the Emperor, is granted 100 years of pardon, and as many Karins, and forgiveneſs of the <hi>4th</hi> part of all ſins. In this Church alſo is a Vault, wherein lyeth the body of <hi>Sylveſter</hi> the Pope, to which is granted 800 years of pardon, and as many Karins, and remiſſion of the third part of all ſins.</p>
               <p>The old Latin Book ſaith, that the Indulgences and Pardons that belong to this aforeſaid Church, are 7000 years, and as many Lents. And that in that Church there is ſuch grace through the merits of the holy Martyrs <hi>Vitus</hi> and <hi>Modeſtus,</hi> &amp;c. that whoſoever is hurt of any mad dog, &amp;c. or of any other noiſom beaſt, and dippeth his bread in the Oyle of St. <hi>Vitus,</hi> and eateth it, he is preſently made whole.</p>
               <p>In the Church of all the Apoſtles, is every day a year of pardon; and every Feaſt of one of the Apoſtles, 300 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church entituled, <hi>Quatuor Coronatorum,</hi> is 40 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Julian,</hi> is a 100 years of pardon. In this Church is a certain kind of holy water, very medicinable, and eaſily cureth all kind of Diſeaſes, but eſpecially Agues, be they never ſo fervent, ſharp, and hot: Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided always, that they which are diſeaſed, and come to take this bleſſed and holy water, be faſting, and ſay three <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> and as many <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> in the Worſhip of Almighty God, and of the glorious Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and of the ſweet Saints <hi>Julian</hi> and <hi>Albert:</hi> Or elſe, either ſay Maſs, or cauſe it to be ſaid, in the honour of the aforenamed St. <hi>Albert.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Foelix</hi> is 1000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Viſy</hi> is 100 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Marcellin</hi> is 1000 years of pardon. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:56276:36"/>Pope <hi>Alexander,</hi> who conſecrated and hallowed this Church, granted unto it from the day of the Conſecration unto the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tas</hi> every year, 3 years of pardon, and as many Lents. And after that, he removed the ſaid pardon from that time, unto the <hi>Monday</hi> after the ſecond <hi>Sunday</hi> of Lent, and added the pardon of one year, and forty days.</p>
               <p>In the Church of <hi>Marcell</hi> is 1000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Cire</hi> and <hi>Joannes,</hi> is the remiſſion of the fourth part of all ſins.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>John</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> is 1000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Euſtace,</hi> where his own and his Wifes body lieth, with their two Sons, is 1000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> where his body lieth, and the body of St. <hi>Pauline,</hi> is 1000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Gregory</hi> is 300 years of pardon; and in the ſame Church whoſoever be buried, he ſhall never be damned. This Church, which before was dedicated (ſaith the old Latin book,) to St. <hi>Andrew</hi> the Apoſtle, St. <hi>Gregory</hi> did hallow, and endowed the ſame with great and ſingular priviledges. And after he had finiſhed the Conſecration of the ſaid Temple, he kneeled down, and moſt humbly proſtrated himſelf before the Majeſty of God, and prayed on this manner, ſaying, <hi>O Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Son of the living God, which ſaidſt to thine Apoſtles, and by thine Apoſtles, to all faithful Chriſtians,</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ye ſhall ask the Father in my name, he ſhall give it you: <hi>I deſire of the Omnipotency and Almightineſs of thy Majeſty, that whoſoever for ever after ſhall chooſe his burial in this Church, or Church-yard, ſo that he hold the Chriſtian faith, may never be adjudged to the pains of Everlaſting damnation, but be exalted to the joys of Everlasting life.</hi> When he had thus prayed, the Angel of the Lord appeared unto him, ſaying, <hi>O</hi> Gregory, <hi>thy prayer</hi> is heard.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> is 1000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In this Church is the chiefeſt Image of our Lord that ever St. <hi>Luke</hi> painted; which Image he always carried with him whitherſoever he went. And it was found in the Grave of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> about his head. And this Image is called, <hi>Sancta Maria Virgo Virginum, &amp; mater omnium;</hi> that is, Saint <hi>Mary</hi> Virgin of Virgins, and Mother of all. This Image, throughout all the City of <hi>Rome</hi> did excel; and was very famous in working of Miracles in the time of Pope <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the <hi>8th,</hi> in the year of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, 1485.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Jerom</hi> is 1000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Alexius,</hi> where his body lieth, is 2000 years of pardon. In this Church, ſaith the old Latin Book, are every day in the year 100 years of pardon, and as many Lents. In this Church alſo is a worthy Image of our Lady, which ſometime was in a Church of the aforeſaid Lady, at a certain City called <hi>Edeſia,</hi> where bleſſed <hi>Alevius</hi> being a Pilgrim, was, and greatly deſired to come and pray before it, and he could not be ſuffered. In conſideration whereof, the moſt bleſſed Image miraculouſly ſpake twice to the Keeper of the Church, and ſaid, <hi>Let</hi> Alexius <hi>the man of God come in, who ſitteth without at the door; and is worthy of the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Church of <hi>Salvator</hi> is 1100 years of pardon, and 40 days.</p>
               <p>In the Chappel of 3 <hi>Wells,</hi> where St. <hi>Paul</hi> was beheaded, is 1000 years of pardon, and as many Karins, and the third part of all ſins releaſed.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Salvator,</hi> in the way to St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> is an hundred years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Sylveſter</hi> is 1000 years of pardon; and there is the head of St. <hi>John Baptist.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:56276:36"/>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Jacob</hi> is 1000 years of pardon, and the third part of all ſins releaſed: and there's the head of St. <hi>James</hi> the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> is 100 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> is 100 year of pardon, and as many Lents.</p>
               <p>In the Hoſpital of St. <hi>Spirit</hi> is 700 years of pardon, and the ſeventh part of all ſins releaſed. Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth granted to all and ſingular perſons that enter into the ſaid Hoſpital of St. <hi>Spirit,</hi> and become a Brother or Siſter of the ſame Fraternity, that they may chooſe where they will a meet Confeſſor, or Ghoſtly Father, to abſolve them from all their ſins, yea, and alſo once in their life-time, and again at the hour of death, to Abſolve them from the Caſes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to the Apoſtolick See; as it is moſt fully contained in a certain Bull made upon the ſame matter. In this Hoſpital is the Arm of St. <hi>Andrew,</hi> and the Finger of St. <hi>Katherin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Michaelis</hi> is 1000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Matthew</hi> is 200 years of pardon: and there is his Arm, and the Arm of St. <hi>Chriſtopher.</hi> The old Latin book ſaith, that there is in this Church 1000 years of pardon, and as many Lents, and the forgiveneſs of the ſeventh part of all ſins, given, granted, and confirmed by Pope <hi>Honorius,</hi> Pope <hi>Alexander,</hi> and Pope <hi>Innocentius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Celore</hi> is 100 years of pardon: and there is the finger of St. <hi>Nicholas</hi> the Biſhop, and the foot of <hi>Mary Magdalen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Simplician</hi> and <hi>Fauſtinus</hi> is 5000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> in the way to St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> is 1000 years of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. In this Church is the Pillar whereupon bleſſed St. <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle was beheaded.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Thomas</hi> is 1000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>John Portlatin</hi> is one Soul delivered out of Purgatory; with many Indulgences and Pardons.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> is 100 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Apollinaris</hi> is 100 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Bennet</hi> is 100 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Andrew</hi> is a 1000 years of pardon: And in this Church there are very many Reliques which were found in the ground, and lay hid there in a Baſon and Glaſs more than 200 years, as it appeareth by the writing that was found with the Reliques.</p>
               <p>In the Church of <hi>Coſine</hi> and <hi>Damiane</hi> is 1000 years of pardon: Whoſoever viſiteth this Church, hath 1000 years of pardon granted by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt, <hi>toties quoties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Simon</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> is 1000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Chappel that is called <hi>Domine quo vadis,</hi> be the ſteps of the Feet of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and there is 1000 years of pardon. In this place, when the Angel of God delivered <hi>Peter</hi> from the hand of <hi>Nero,</hi> our Saviour Chriſt met with him, to whom <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, Lord whither goeſt thou? and he anſwer'd, I go to <hi>Rome</hi> to be crucified again.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>John</hi> is 1000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>James</hi> the Apoſtle is 2000 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>And Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Eighth hath granted full remiſſion of all ſins to all and ſingular perſons that devoutly viſit the aforeſaid Church, in the Feaſt of the aforenamed Apoſtle, with this Proviſo, That they hear Mattens, Maſſes, and Even-ſong, in the aforeſaid Church.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Bernard</hi> is 300 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Luke</hi> is 1000 years of pardon.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:56276:37"/>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Mark</hi> is 1000 years of pardon. This Church Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the ſecond endowed with many priviledges, and very great Indulgences, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that all and ſingular perſons that viſit the ſame Church in the Octaves of the moſt holy body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, or at the Feaſt of the Epiphany of Chriſt, or elſe give ſomewhat to the beautifying and enriching of the ſaid Church, ſhall have manifold indulgence and pardon, with full remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Panthaleon</hi> is 48 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Pancras</hi> is 100 years of pardon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of certain Churches in <hi>Rome</hi> dedicated to our Lady.</head>
               <p>IN the Church of our Lady called <hi>Rotunda,</hi> is every <hi>Friday</hi> in the year, and in the Feaſt of <hi>All-hollows,</hi> clean and perfect remiſſion of all ſins. This Church was edified by one called <hi>Agrippa,</hi> in the Worſhip of <hi>Sibilla, Venus,</hi> and <hi>Neptunus,</hi> and of all other Gods and Goddeſſes, and was called <hi>Pantheon:</hi> But afterward at the deſire of the Pope <hi>Boniface,</hi> it was granted by the Emperor to be made a Temple of the Chriſtians, ſo that the aſoreſaid Pope, with a great multitude of the <hi>Romans,</hi> did dedicate the ſame the firſt of the Kalends of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> in the Worſhip of our Lady, and of all Saints. He hath alſo made there an Altar, and ſaid Maſs there himſelf, and miniſtred the Sacrament to the people, and on the morrow after, he ſaid Maſs in the ſame place for all Souls paſt. He granted alſo great Indulgence and Pardon to all that devoutly viſit this Church, and meekly, kneeling upon their knees, ſay a <hi>Pater Noſter,</hi> and an <hi>Ave,</hi> in the Worſhip of our Lady, and all Saints.</p>
               <p>In the Church of our Lady <hi>Trans Tiberim,</hi> where a Well of Oyle plentifully flowed by the ſpace of one whole day, and one whole night, when Chriſt was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> is 700 years of pardon in the Feaſt of the Nativity of our Lady, granted by Pope <hi>Calixt;</hi> and in Lent 400 years of pardon, gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the third.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item,</hi> In the ſame Church are the ſteps of <hi>Odraphin,</hi> printed in Stone, which was found upon the Caſtle of St. <hi>Angel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſame Church alſo is one of the five Images of our Lady, which St. <hi>Luke</hi> did paint.</p>
               <p>In the Church of our Lady, called <hi>Ara Coeli,</hi> is 3000 years of pardon, and as many Lents. This Church was ſometime the Palace of <hi>Octavianus</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, who ſaw in his Viſion, a fair Virgin in Heaven, ſtanding upon an Altar, holding a goodly Child in her Arms: At which ſight he marvailed greatly, and afterward heard a Voice from Heaven, ſaying, <hi>Haec ara Coeli filij Dei est.</hi> And he fell to the ground, and worſhipped Chriſt, and believed in his coming. This Viſion he had in his Chamber, where now the Church of St. <hi>Mary,</hi> called <hi>Ara Coeli,</hi> is.</p>
               <p>Under this Church is a Priſon where St. <hi>Peter</hi> was impriſoned, where is now a fair Chappel, in which is a Pit, wherein St. <hi>Peter</hi> did baptize many Martyrs. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> was led out of that Priſon by the Angel; and there is great and mighty pardon.</p>
               <p>In this Church alſo is one of the Images of our Lady, which St. <hi>Luke</hi> painted. This Image was made after the ſame form and manner that our Lady ſtood at the Croſs of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, mourning, weeping and lamenting. This Image is of great virtue, and worketh daily many miracles, as ye may ſee in a certain Table that hangeth by the aforeſaid Image.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:56276:37"/>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Mary</hi> the New is 1000 years of pardon; and in Lent 200 years.</p>
               <p>In this Church alſo is an Image of our Lady which St. <hi>Luke</hi> painted in <hi>Troas</hi> of <hi>Greece.</hi> This Image an Angel brought from the <hi>Frangapanes</hi> unto <hi>Rome,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid Church; which Church being burnt in the time of Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> the third, this Image ſtood, and was nothing hurt.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Luke</hi> had two ſtrings to his bow, Phyſick and Painting; Gods word ſpeaks the former, but as for the latter, we have none but Mr. Pope's word for it: and let the Papiſts believe him if they will, Proteſtants are ſo ſaucy as not to believe him.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Mary Tranſpontin,</hi> in which are the two Pillars unto which the bleſſed Apoſtles, St. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>St. Paul</hi> were bound when they were ſcourged, is 300 year of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church called <hi>Sancta Maria de Campo,</hi> is 40 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St <hi>Mary in Porticum,</hi> is 200 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In this Church is a certain precious ſtone called a Saphir, wherein (as they write) is graven by the hands of the holy Angels, the Image of Chriſt, and of our Lady, and was delivered miraculouſly from Heaven, to a certain Noble-man, called <hi>Galla.</hi> And to this Stone alſo is granted great Pardon.</p>
               <p>I never knew the Angels to be Gravers before; and it ſeems they kept their Graving-ſhop in Heaven: but are not their Tools with which they Graved theſe Images, to be ſeen alſo. Certainly they would be excellent Reliques, and would give a little credit to this incredible ſtory.</p>
               <p>In the Church of our Lady <hi>De aqua Salina</hi> is 1000 years of pardon, and in the day of the Conſecration of the ſame, is remiſſion of all ſins.</p>
               <p>In the Church of our Lady <hi>De Apoſtolis</hi> is 200 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Mary,</hi> called, <hi>Schola Graeca,</hi> is 100 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of our Lady, called <hi>Scala Coeli,</hi> is alſo great pardon.</p>
               <p>This is one of the firſt Temples that was built in the world unto the honour of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> It is called <hi>Scala Coeli,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This Church is of great height where St. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> ſaw this ſight.</note> becauſe in it bleſſed St. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> deſerved to ſee a Ladder which reached up to the very Heavens. In this Church whoſoever ſays Maſs, or cauſe it to be ſaid for the the Souls that are in Purgatory, the aforeſaid Souls are delivered out of hand,<note place="margin">But the miſery is, no Maſſes can be gotten without mony.</note> through the virtue of the Maſs, and the Merits of the bleſſed Virgin: Moreover, whatſoever thing is devoutly asked in that place, it is ſtraightway, without all doubt, obtained. And there is great abundance of pardon, <hi>a poena &amp; culpa toties quoties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Mary,</hi> called <hi>Imperatrix,</hi> is great Indulgence, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold pardon, even to the number of 6000 years. In this Church is an Image of the bleſſed Virgin, which ſpake to St. <hi>Coeleſtine</hi> the Pope, ſaying, <hi>Why dost not thou pray unto me more often; ſeeing that when thou goeſt by my Image, thou cloſt always ſalute and reverence it.</hi> St. <hi>Coeleſtine</hi> hearing this voice, fell down upon his knees and prayed, and deſired before that Image forgiveneſs. And more, this holy Father hath granted to them that kneel before this Image, and ſay with a good intent, three <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> and as many <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> 15 years of pardon, <hi>toties quoties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Church of our Lady, called, <hi>Libera nos a poenis inferni,</hi> i.e. Deliver us from the pains of Hell, is great plenty of pardon. St. <hi>Sylveſter,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who delivered <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Emperor from his Leproſie, and afterward bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized him, Conſecrated and hallowed this place, which being the Chappel of the bleſſed Virgin, is called, <hi>Libera nos a poenis inferni.</hi> He hath alſo granted to all and ſingular perſons that devoutly come unto that place, and give ſomewhat to the maintenance thereof, 11000 years of pardon, <hi>toties quoties.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:56276:38"/>
               <p>In the Church of our Lady <hi>De Conſolatione,</hi> is an Image of the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin which hath wrought many Miracles; and there is in the ſame Church full remiſſion of all ſins on the ſecond <hi>Sunday</hi> of the month of <hi>June,</hi> from the firſt Even-ſong unto the laſt, granted by Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth.</p>
               <p>In the Church of our Lady, entituled, <hi>Maria inviolata,</hi> is the Oratory in which bleſſed <hi>Luke</hi> painted four Images of the glorious Virgin. One of theſe Images he made after ſuch ſort, as he himſelf knew and ſaw the bleſſed Virgin; and therefore he painted, and ſet her forth with a Ring on her finger: which Image remaineth at this preſent day in the aforeſaid Oratory. And foraſmuch as the bleſſed Virgin doth work many miracles in the ſaid Image, therefore is there great reſort of People unto the ſaid Image, which receive there great help and comfort, great indulgence and pardon, and are repleniſhed with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Graces, and ſingular Benefits.</p>
               <p>In the Church of our Lady <hi>De populo,</hi> is great Indulgence and Pardon: For Pope <hi>Paſcalis</hi> hath given and granted to all that devoutly viſit this Church at the Feaſt of the Dedication of the ſame, and bring ſomewhat for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the ſaid Church, from the <hi>Friday</hi> after the third <hi>Sunday</hi> of Lent unto the <hi>Octaves</hi> of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> for every day 1000 years of pardon, and as many Lents. Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth alſo hath endowed this Church with marvailous, and many great Indulgences, inſomuch, that all and ſingular perſons that of a good mind come and viſit this Church at the Feaſts of the Nativity, Purification, Annunciation, Viſitation and Aſſumption of <hi>Mary</hi> the Virgin, or at any one of them, ſhall have for every time full remiſſion of all their ſins.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Here follow certain other Churches, with their Indulgences and Pardons.</head>
               <p>IN the Church of St. <hi>Agnes</hi> is every day 48 years of pardon; and in the Feaſt of the ſame Saint, 200 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Suſan</hi> is 300 years of pardon.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Tabine,</hi> the Wife of St. <hi>Alexius,</hi> is 2000 years of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and as many Karins.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Praxed</hi> is remiſſion of the fourth part of all ſins: and in the ſame Church is the Pillar that Chriſt was bound unto when he was ſcourged. The old Latin book ſaith, that in the aforeſaid Church there is daily 12000 years of pardon, and as many Lents, and the forgiveneſs of the third part of all ſins.</p>
               <p>In this Church alſo is an Altar, upon which Pope <hi>Paſcalis</hi> ſung 5 Maſſes for a certain Soul departed: which 5 Maſſes being once ended, he ſaw with his corporal eyes, the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> to fetch the Soul out of Purgatory, and to carry it into the boſom of Almighty God, as ye may ſee it painted upon the wall of the aforeſaid Church: In conſideration whereof, the aforeſaid Pope <hi>Paſcalis</hi> by his Apoſtolick Authority, hath given and granted to ſo many, as either ſay Maſs themſelves, or cauſe Maſs to be ſaid in the aforenamed Church, power to deliver one Soul out of Purgatory, <hi>toties quoties.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:56276:38"/>
               <l>In the Church of St. <hi>Katharine</hi> is 200 years of Pardon.</l>
               <l>In the Church of St. <hi>Felix</hi> is 40 years of Pardon.</l>
               <l>In the Church of St. <hi>Barbara</hi> is 100 years of Pardon.</l>
               <l>In the Church of St. <hi>Lucy</hi> is 100 years of Pardon, and as many Lents, and the third part of all Sins forgiven.</l>
               <l>In the Church of St. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> is 100 years of Pardon.</l>
               <l>In the Church of St. <hi>Pernil</hi> is 1000 years of Pardon.</l>
               <l>In the Church of St. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> is 100 years of Pardon, and as many Karins.</l>
               <l>In the Church of St. <hi>Clare</hi> is 100 years of Pardon.</l>
               <l>In the Church of St. <hi>Vinnian</hi> is 3000 years of Pardon, and in Lent 5000 years of Pardon.</l>
               <l>In the Church of St. <hi>Agatha</hi> is 28 years of Pardon.</l>
               <l>In the Church of St. <hi>Margaret</hi> is 200 years of Pardon.</l>
               <l>In the Church of St. <hi>Chriſtine</hi> is 40 years of Pardon.</l>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Clement</hi> is 40 years of Pardon, and as many Lents, yea, and forgiveneſs of all ſins at the Feaſt aforeſaid. And in Lent all theſe Indulgences and Pardons are doubled; granted of ſpecial grace by Pope <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> to ſo many as devoutly viſit the aforeſaid Church, or give ought thereunto. Alſo Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third by his Apoſtolique authority hath granted this privilege, That ſo many as with good devotion come to pray in the aforeſaid Church, ſhall have the third part of all their ſins for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given.</p>
               <p>In the Church of bleſſed St. <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle, <hi>ad carceres,</hi> is granted of divers Popes to them that of a good mind viſit this Church, or help any thing at all unto the maintenance of the ſame, Every day the forgiveneſs of the third part of all their ſins, and 200 years of Pardon. And it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the moſt holy Fathers of their ſpecial grace that this Indulgence and Pardon ſhall be doubled on every Feaſt day.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Bibian</hi> is great Indulgence and Pardon. For Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> the Third hath granted to ſo many as devoutly viſit this Church,<note place="margin">A great Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don on my word.</note> 3 years of Pardon, and as many Lents <hi>toties quoties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, at the Feaſt of all Saints there is Six hundred thouſand years of pardon. In this place alſo St. <hi>Bibian</hi> planted a certain Herb, which being dried and made into Pouder, is very profitable to deliver men from the Falling-Sickneſs.</p>
               <p>This Saint was inclined to be a Phyſician; Was not he a Painter as well as St. <hi>Luke?</hi> Well, this Herb certainly is a very precious Relique.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Euſebius</hi> is granted to all them that Devoutly come unto it,<note place="margin">Who would let ſuch a Church fall, but Heretiques.</note> and put their helping hand to the maintenance thereof 7454 years of Pardon, and as many Lents.</p>
               <p>The Miſery is, this Pardon is Chargeable, but the Ware is good, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us not grudge to be bountiful</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Vitus</hi> is 7000 years of Pardon, and as many Lents.<note place="margin">Let him Eat a good Breakfaſt after it, he may chance to fill his belly.</note> There is alſo in the ſame Church ſuch and ſo great grace through the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the Holy Martyrs <hi>Vitus, Modeſtus,</hi> and <hi>Creſcentia,;</hi> that if ſo be any man be bitten with a Mad-dog, or any other Beaſt, and take a piece of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:56276:39"/>Bread and dip it in the Oyl of St. <hi>Vitus,</hi> and ſo eat it, he ſhall ſtrait-ways be made whole.</p>
               <p>Excellent Cures by this Chymical Oyl of St. <hi>Vitus.</hi> I ſuppoſe a good Plaſter will not do amiſs; for the ſtone doth well to be added to the Goſpel. Which Proverb was occaſioned by a certain Man's meeting with a fierce Dog, upon whoſe ſight he fell a repeating the Goſpel of St. <hi>John,</hi> Cap. 1.1. but the Dog making up to him, he took up a Stone, and caſting it at the ſurly Cur, made him retreat; I ſee, ſaith the poor Man, the Stone doeth well with the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>In the Church of St. <hi>Potentian</hi> is granted by Pope <hi>Simplicius</hi> to all and ſingular Perſons, that devoutly viſit the ſaid Church, one year of Pardon, and one Lent, and the forgivneſs of the third part of their ſins. But Pope <hi>Celeſtine,</hi> Pope <hi>Boniface,</hi> Pope <hi>Clement,</hi> Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> Pope <hi>Urban,</hi> and Pope <hi>Alexander,</hi> of their Godly zeal have doubled the aforeſaid Pardon.</p>
               <p>Who would not turn Papiſt at this rate? but why a third part of his Sins, but ſome other Church muſt have a little privilege? By all which, I ſee the Pope is an excellent Carver, if he pleaſe he ſhall be Carver to the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Foot-Boy's Cobler's Apprentice; for certainly he is a deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Gentleman.</p>
               <p>It is to be noted, that in this Church there is a Chappel behind the High Altar, in which Chappel St. <hi>Peter</hi> (as they ſay) ſung his firſt Maſs: There is alſo great Pardon.</p>
               <p>I never underſtood that St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſung Maſs before, but a man may ſee that Popery is the Fountain of knowledg, and being that St. <hi>Peter</hi> did grace this Chappel,<note place="margin">This is Charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but any thing to go to Heaven.</note> it will follow that there muſt be a great Pardon belong to this Chappel, but the Prieſts had rather have great ſtipend, or elſe there will be but ſmall ſtore of Muſick.</p>
               <p>And for a ſmall Concluſion we ſhall Note, that all Indulgence of <hi>Rome</hi> is in Lent doubled. Again in the way of his Pilgrimage unto <hi>Rome,</hi> he is truly aſſoiled of all deadly ſins and of all other, whatſoever they be: So that his Soul is not only by this means free from the pains both of Hell and Purgatory, but it is alſo ſtraightway by the Miniſtry of the Holy Angels, carryed up into the glorious Palace of the Heavenly King. O bleſſed is that man or woman, that is partaker of theſe Indulgencies and Pardons, for he may be ſure to make a bleſſed end, let his Life be never ſo Sinful.</p>
               <p>This would be excellent Doctrine to preach to the <hi>Turks;</hi> as for Hereticks, they deſerve not one tittle of this kindneſs, but it ſuits wonderful well with the reſt of the Pope's doctrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:56276:39"/>
               <head>Here follow the Indulgencies and Pardons, which certain Popes have granted to all ſuch as devoutly ſay certain Prayers, which hereafter ſhall be named.</head>
               <p>TO all them that be in the ſtate of grace, that daily ſay devoutly this Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er before our bleſſed Lady of Pity, ſhe will ſhew them her bleſſed viſage,<note place="margin">Be ſure you get into this ſtate of Grace, or elſe the fat is in the fire.</note> and warn them of the day and of the hour of death, and in their laſt end the Angels of God ſhall yield their Souls to Heaven, and they ſhall obtain 500 years and ſo many Lents of Pardon, granted by our Holy Father Pope <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifacius. Obſecro te Domina Sancta Maria,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Who ſaith devoutly this ſhort Prayer daily, ſhall not depart out of this World without penance and miniſtration of the Holy Sacrament: the which was ſhewed by an Angel to St. <hi>Bernard. Ave Maria, Ancilla Sanctae Trinitatis,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Our Holy Father Pope <hi>Sixtus,</hi> hath granted to all them that devoutly ſay this Prayer before the Image of our Lady and her Son 11000 years of Pardon. <hi>Ave Sanctiſſima Maria,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Our holy Father Pope <hi>Sixtus,</hi> hath granted at the inſtance of the moſt High and Excellent Princeſs <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> late Queen of <hi>England,</hi> and Wife to our Soveraign Lord King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, (God have mercy on her ſweet Soul and all Chriſtian Souls) to all them that every day in the morning af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 3 tollings of the <hi>Ave</hi> Bell, ſay three times the whole ſalutation of our Lady, <hi>Ave Maria gratia plena,</hi> that is to ſay, at ſix of the Clock in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 3 <hi>Ave Maries:</hi> At 12 at Noon 3 <hi>Ave Maries:</hi> and at ſix of the Clock at Evening: for every time ſo doing, is granted of the Spiritual Treaſure of the holy Church 300 dayes of Pardon, <hi>toties quoties.</hi> And alſo our Holy Fathers the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> with other 9 Biſhops of this Realm, have granted 3 times in the day 40 days of pardon, to all them that be in the ſtate of Grace able to receive pardon, the which begun the 26th day of <hi>March,</hi> Anno 1492, in the ſeventh year of the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh. And the ſum of the Indulgence and pardon, for every <hi>Ave Maria gratia plena,</hi> is 740 dayes, <hi>toties quoties. Suſcipe verbum Virgo Maria,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This Prayer was ſhewed to St. <hi>Bernard</hi> by the Meſſenger of God, ſaying, That as Gold is moſt precious of all other Metal, ſo exceedeth this Prayer all other Prayers. And whoſo devoutly ſays it, ſhall have a ſingular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of our Bleſſed Lady, and of her ſweet Son Jeſus. <hi>Ave Maria, ancilla Trinitatis humillima.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Holy Father Pope <hi>Bonifacius</hi> hath granted to all them that devoutly ſay this lamentable Contemplation of our Lady ſtanding under the Croſs, weeping and having compaſſion on her ſweet Son Jeſus, 7 years of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and 40 Lents. Alſo Pope <hi>John</hi> the 22d. hath granted 300 days of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. <hi>Stabat mater doloroſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:56276:40"/>
               <p>Theſe be the 15 O's which the Holy Virgin St. <hi>Bridget</hi> was wont to ſay daily before the Holy Rood in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church at <hi>Rome.</hi> Who ſo ſaith them an whole year, ſhall deliver 15 Souls out of Purgatory of his next Kindred, and convert 15 Sinners unto good life; and other 15 Righteous men of his Kindred ſhall perſevere in good life. And whatſoever he deſireth of God he ſhall have it, if it be to the Salvation of his Soul.</p>
               <p>To all them that before the Image of Chriſt ſcourged, devoutly ſay 5 <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Noſters,</hi> and 5 <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> and a Creed, piteouſly beholding the Arms of Chriſt's Paſſion, are granted 32755 years of Pardon. And Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> of his great clemency and fatherly goodneſs, hath doubled this aforeſaid Pardon. <hi>Adoro te Domine, Jeſu Chriſte.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Epiſtle of our Saviour, ſent our Holy Father Pope <hi>Leo</hi> unto the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror <hi>Carolus Magnus,</hi> of which we find written, That whoſoever beareth this Bleſſing upon him and ſaith it once a day, he ſhall obtain 40 years of Pardon, and 80 Lents; and he ſhall not periſh with ſudden death. <hi>Crux Chriſti ſit mecum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Prayer made St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> affirming, That whoſoever ſaith it daily kneeling, ſhall not die in Sin, but after this life he ſhall obtain everlaſting Joy and Bliſs. <hi>Reſpice ad me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Our Holy Father Pope <hi>Bonifacius</hi> the Sixth hath granted to all them that devoutly ſay this Prayer following, between the elevation of our Lord and the third <hi>Agnus Dei,</hi> 10000 years of Pardon. <hi>Domine Jeſu Chriſte, qui hanc ſacratiſſimam carnem,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Our Holy Father Pope <hi>John</hi> the 22d. hath granted to all them that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly ſay this Prayer after the elevation of our Lord Jeſu Chriſt 3000 days of Pardon for deadly Sins. <hi>Anima Chriſti ſanctifica me,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The ſame Pope hath granted 100 days of Pardon to all them that ſay this Prayer at the Elevation of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Ave caro Chriſticara,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Our Holy Father <hi>Innocentius</hi> Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> hath granted 7 years of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to all them that ſay this Prayer devoutly at the Elevation of our Lord in the Maſs. <hi>Salve lux Mundi,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Our Holy Father Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fourth, hath granted to all them that be in the ſtate of Grace, ſaying this Prayer following immediately after the Elevation of the Body of our Lord, clean Remiſſion of all their Sins perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually enduring. And alſo Pope <hi>John</hi> the 22d. at the requeſt of the Queen of <hi>England,</hi> hath granted unto all them that devoutly ſay this Prayer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Image of our Lord Crucified; as many days of Pardon as there were wounds in the Body of our Lord in the time of his bitter Paſſion, which were 5465. <hi>Precor te, amantiſſime Domine Jeſu Chriſte,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This Prayer was ſhewed to St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> by revelation of the Holy Ghoſt: and whoſo devoutly ſaith this Prayer, or hears it read, or beareth it about him, he ſhall not periſh in Fire, nor Water, nor Battel, nor Judgment.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:56276:40"/>And he ſhall dye no ſudden death, and no venom ſhall poiſon him that day. And whatſoever he asketh of God, he ſhall obtain it; if it be to the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Soul. And whenſoever his Soul ſhall depart from his Body, it ſhall not enter into Hell. <hi>Deus propitius eſto mili peceatori,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Our Holy Father <hi>Innocentiue</hi> the Third, hath granted to all them that ſay this Prayer following, devoutly, Remiſſion of all their Sins confeſſed and contrite. <hi>Domine Jeſu Chriſte Fili Dei vivi,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This Prayer following made the worſhipful St. <hi>Bede</hi> of the ſeven laſt words which our Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſpake hanging on the Croſs. Whoſo ſays this Prayer devoutly kneeling, neither the Devil, nor wicked men ſhall hurt him. And he ſhall not dye without Confeſſion. <hi>Domine Jeſu Chriſte, qui ſeptem verba,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Theſe 5 Petitions and Prayers made St. <hi>Gregory,</hi> and hath granted to all them that devoutly ſay theſe 5 Prayers, with 5 <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> and 5 <hi>Ave Maries,</hi> and 5 <hi>Credo</hi>'s, 500 years of Pardon. <hi>Ave manus dexter a Chriſti,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This Prayer ſhall ye ſay in the worſhip of all the Bleſſed Members of Chriſt devoutly. And ye ſhall have 300 days of pardon for every Salve. And there be 13 Salves. <hi>Salve tremendum,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This Prayer is made by our Holy Father Pope <hi>John</hi> the 22d. and he hath granted to all them that devoutly ſay this Prayer, beholding the glorious Viſage or Vernacle of our Lord, ten thouſand days of pardon. And they that cannot ſay this Prayer, let them ſay 5 <hi>Pater Neſters,</hi> 5 <hi>Aves,</hi> and 5 <hi>Creeds;</hi> and they ſhall have the like Pardon. <hi>Salve Sancta faeies,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Another Oracle to the bleſſed Vernacle or Viſage of our Lord Jeſu Chriſt: Whoſo ſaith it devoutly, ſhall have 300 years of pardon granted by our Holy Father Pope <hi>Innocentius. Ave facies praeclara,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Whoſo devoutly beholdeth theſe Arms of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, ſhall obtain 6000 years of pardon granted by our Holy Father St. <hi>Peter,</hi> the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and by 30 other Popes of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Succeſſors after him. And our Holy Father Pope <hi>John</hi> the 22d. hath granted to all them that be very contrite and truly confeſſed, ſaying this devout Prayer in the Commemoration of the bitter Paſſion of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, 3000 years of pardon for deadly Sins, and other 3000 for venial Sins; and ſay firſt a <hi>Pater Noſter</hi> and one <hi>Ave Maria. Diripuiſti Domine, vincula mea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Holy Father Pope <hi>Innocentius</hi> the Second, hath granted to all them that ſay this Prayer devoutly in the worſhip of the Wound that our Lord had in his bleſſed Side, when he was dead, hanging on the Croſs, 4000 days of pardon. <hi>Ave vulnus lateris noſtri,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This moſt devout Prayer, ſaid the Holy Father St. <hi>Bernardin</hi> the Grey Friar, daily kneeling, in the worſhip of that moſt Holy Name Jeſus. And it is well to believe, that through the Invocation of that moſt excellent Name of Jeſus, St. <hi>Bernardin</hi> obtained a ſingular reward of perpetual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:56276:41"/>of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And this Prayer is written in a Table that hangeth at <hi>Rome,</hi> in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Church, near to the high Altar, where our Holy Father the Pope is wont to ſay Maſs. And whoſo devoutly with a contrite heart daily ſays this Oriſon, if he be that day in the ſtate of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal pain, it ſhall be changed into the Temporal pain of Purgatory. And if he hath deſerved the pain of Purgatory, then it ſhall be forgotten and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given through the infinite Mercy of God. <hi>Obone Jeſu,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> hath granted to all them that ſay this Prayer devoutly, in the worſhip of St. <hi>Anne,</hi> and our Lady and her Son Jeſus, 10000 years of pardon for deadly Sins, and 20 years for venial Sins, <hi>toties quoties. Ave Maria,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bocatius</hi> ſaith, That the hairs of that Angel of the Seraphical Order, which came down from Heaven (as the Papiſts feign) unto filly ſimple St. <hi>Francis</hi> the Grey-Friar, in the likeneſs of a young man, and printed in his Hands, Feet and Heart, the ſigns and tokens of the five wounds of Chriſt; are kept in a certain Monaſtery of <hi>Franciſcan.</hi> Friars in <hi>Italy,</hi> as moſt Heavenly and Holy Reliques.</p>
               <p>In the ſame Monaftery alſo are divers Reliques of the aforeſaid <hi>Francis,</hi> namely his Night Coul, and his Breeches. Theſe are highly reverenced, and had in great price.</p>
               <p>It ſeemeth the very Coeleſtial Bodies muſt be abuſed by theſe Forgers of Lies:<note place="margin">Note.</note> here they pretend Angels to have Hairs, which is falſe, for Hair is an Excrement, and Coeleſtial Bodies have no Excrements; but it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth they ſpare none: The Angels muſt have their Hair pull'd off to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate their Covetouſneſs; But that this Angel ſhould put the five wounds of Chriſt upon ſilly Fanatick St. <hi>Francis,</hi> none but ſtark Fanaticks will believe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>ANd now, Good Reader, I have given thee an account of their monſtrous Merchandize, and horrid Cheats of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> diſcovering to thee their feigned Reliques.</p>
            <p>Let me tell thee how happy a Nation thou liveſt in, how God did bleſs the Church of <hi>England,</hi> when he did diſcover the folly of all theſe wicked Crew of Popelings, which with theſe Thouſands of Cheats did pick the Peoples Pockets, as they do at this day; and to my knowledge in other Nations.</p>
            <p>And ſhould the Pope and his Popelings prevail to introduce the Romiſh Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in <hi>England</hi> again, all theſe ſwarms of Fopperies will undoubtedly flow in upon us again: Yea, the Traitor <hi>Colman</hi>'s as well as the Traitor <hi>Tom Becket</hi>'s Bones, may hap become holy Reliques. Therefore for the Honour of Chriſt, and for the good of your own Souls, and the Souls of your poor Babes, and all Poſterity, be earnest with God by Prayers, and with your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:56276:41"/>and Servants, and Neighbours, by Counſel to prevent it, That that cloud of the darkneſs of Popery may never overſhadow this Nation any more. And let all Proteſtants, as good Chriſtians and Lovers of the Souls of their Poſterity, join heart and hand againſt it, that ſo our Kings and Nobles, and all our Governours and People may never be ſubject to the Cenſures or Pretended Eccleſiaſtical Jurisdictions of that abominable proud Pretender and Father of all Errors and Miſchiefs, the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to that purpoſe, be faithful in Diſcovering all their Prieſts and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Intereſts, and Deſigns, to the uttermoſt of your Skill.</p>
            <p>And Encourage all ſorts of Proteſtants whatſoever that fear God, honour the King, and are willing to be ſubject to the Civil Magiſtrate, though Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting from the reſt of Chriſtians in ſome ſmall Matters and Indifferent things, and ſo live together in Love and Neighbourly Friendſhip, as they of <hi>Rome</hi> may never have hope again by our Diviſions to Impoſe upon us their monſtrous Hereſies and Phanaticiſms; and living in Unity of Affection and Civil Peace, put the Pope and all his Crew from all hopes of ſetting up their Trade of picking Engliſhmens Pockets, by ſhowing their feigned Reliques, and pretended Pardons and Indulgences. From which, that <hi>England</hi> may be ever free, is the Prayer of him that is the Lover of the Proteſtant Intereſt, and of his King and Country,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Titus Oates.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
